<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>            
   <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_096.jpg" n="96" xml:id="img_0096"/>
            
               <head><title>Nepal Hill Art and
               Women's Traditions</title></head>
            <byline>
               Barbara Nimri Aziz</byline>
            <p>
               Chait Purnima, the full moon. Warm
               spring air drifts through deep disap-
               pearing valleys. It rustles across Kobek
               village and reminds me a month has
               passed since my arrival in this Hima-
               layan hamlet. l’ve been studying econ-
               omy and social change in eastem Nepal
               for almost a year now.</p>
               <p>It was during an earlier visit to do
               anthropological work that 1 first began
               to learn about the Limbu people. Ex-
               ploitation of Limbu land rights by high
               caste Brahmins had been well publi-
               cized, and recently the Limbu had been
               one of the few ethnic groups in the
               country to criticize the government s
               policy regarding minorities. 1 had also
               heard about the economic independ-
               ence and sparkle of Limbu women from
               medics and development officers im
               pressed by their culture, so 1 decided to
               visit the region. It was easy for me to
               include them in a comparative study of
               three different ethnic groups, each one
               living on a main north-south trade
               route artery. I had already surveyed a
               Sherpa community and a village com-
               posed of Newar and Tamang farmers.
               The Limbu are not only a different race
               from the other two, but their rice culti-
               vation and their culture are so different
               that 1 often felt, living among them, 1
               might easily be in North Burma or
               Southeast Asia.</p>
               <p>On my second day in the village, 1
               moved into the house of a fairly pros-
               perous Limbu family and arranged a
               corner for myself in an empty hayloft
               behind the main house. It gave me the
               privacy I needed while allowing me to
               be close to the family. As the weeks
               passed, I found myself spending almost
               all my time around the main house with
               Danamaya and her family.</p>
               <p>The house is one of a cluster of two-
               story farmhouses on a steep hillside.
               Lemon bushes and groves of bamboo
               veil the next house, but we can hear
               neighbors in their courtyards. Those
               familiar sounds blur the boundaries be-
               tween family and neighborhood. The
               dark interiors of these mountain dwell-
               ings are primarily used for cooking, for
               sleep and for storage. No one works in-
               side.</p>
               <p>The busy routine of domestic work
               proceeds on the veranda and in clean-
               swept courtyards, fusing imperceptibly
               with social life. It is here that villagers
               stay through the pleasant, dry winter
               months. But now, with the arrival of
               spring, activity shifts from these ver-
               andas to muddy fields on slopes above
               and below the village. Early wheat
               wants cutting, and the patchwork of
               terraces must be softened so that tender
               millet and rice sprouts will take hold.
               At the time of the full moon, how-
               ever, the fields are empty. People are
               freed from agricultural labor for the
               holiday and remain at home feasting
               and visiting. Today, neighbors will
               converge on our veranda. They know
               we plan to make a special Limbu orna-
               ment. Around the straw mat at our
               door will sit the artisans of the village-
               a team of women. All of them can
               weave the Limbu tartan cloth and knot
               straw mats. They are renowned brew-
               ers of beer and spirits. The polishings
               of rice and pressing of oil are but two of
               their many skills in the preparation of
               food.</p>
               <p>I have invited these women to come
               make a Limbu necklace, a naugiri, so
               called because of its nine (nau) golden
               jewels (giri) set among the mass of
               beads arranged one by one by deft fin-
               gers. Since my arrival in the hills of Ne-
               pal, 1 have encountered a range of
               peasant cultures: robust Sherpa herders
               and farmers, the richest of the high-
               land people; progressive Newar traders
               and shopkeepers, many of whose
               daughters are in school; Rai hill people.
               a large ethnic group, also good farmers;
               Magar villagers who seem impover-
               ished by the standards of other groups
               who are squeezing them out; Brahmin
               and Chetri high caste people, frugal
               and industrious, whose women
               sometimes become ascetics and join
               hermitages near their tropical shrines.
               All of these people wear elegant, home-
               made jewelry. Limbu women, however,
               stand out for their industry, their bold-
               ness, their assertiveness and their
               pride. Their chunky naugiri necklace,
               worn day and night, in the fields and at
               weddings, typifies the general status of
               these women; it has become, for me, a
               symbol of their vigor, and one which I
               want to take with me when 1 leave.
               When 1 expressed interest in having
               my own naugiri, Danamaya, my host,
               and her friends were delighted. The
               first question was where to get one for
               me. 1 wouldn’t want an old one bought
               from the bank, my friends assured me.
               Those worn jewels have value only as
               security against land purchase loans. I
               must have a new one, they insisted. But
               new necklaces cannot be purchased.
               l’hey are not produced for a market. A
               Limbu woman obtains her naugiri,
               made especially for her by women in
               her family, at the time of her marriage.
               My surrogate family here in Kobek will
               make mine.</p>
               <p>I committed myself to this scheme
               with the purchase of the basic material
               -a thola (about a half ounce) of pure
               gold costing 500 rupees (850) on the
               Limbu market. I bought this from a vil-
               lager recently returned from military
               service in Malaya. Next, 1 was intro-
               duced to the local goldsmith. His de-
               crepit hut (on the outskirts of the vil-
               lage because of his pariah caste) has a
               second-story veranda. Here he fashions
               jewels with his fingers and toes for the
               constant stream of Limbu customers.
               Over the course of a week 1 watched
               him tap the worthless-looking lump of
               metal 1 had entrusted to him into lus-
               trous, paper-thin yellow sheets. The
               precious metal was finding its beauty in
               his experienced hands. Finally he
               molded and engraved each of the nine
               leaves of gold he had made into indi-
               vidual jewels, knuckly and assertive.</p>
               <p>Between each of these chunks, we
               women will set thousands of glassy
               green beads. 1 bought these at the
               weekly market out of a dazzling array
               of bangles and beads imported from In-
               dia and sold by squatting vendors hud-
               dled in rows, one beside the next, on
               the floor of the market square. I also</p>
            
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_0973.jpg" n="97" xml:id="img_0097"/>
            <p>
               bought red cloth from which to cut the
               furry washers that will be set on both
               sides of the gold. And finally, for the
               rope on which to string all this, we cut
               the yellow nylon cord from my back-
               pack.</p>
               <p>On the morning of Chait Purnima,
               the essentials for our day’s work are
               ready for our guests who will shortly
               converge on our veranda mat. A five-
               gallon pot of kodo (millet beer) sits
               gurgling in the darkness of the house.
               With it are six bottles of raxsi, a clear
               ginlike drink distilled from fermented
               kodo. The beer is not of as fine a qual-
               ity as 1 would have liked—sweet and
               aged for months in cool, sealed pots
               such as 1 have had in the homes of
               other women. Such kodo is not for sale;
               it is for guests and a family’s own enjoy-
               ment. What is sold is coarse and aged
               for only a week. That is all we have to-
               day, prepared by my host Danamaya
               and sold to me for this occasion. Good
               raxsi, customarily made for sale, is
               more readily obtained. Danamaya sold
               me three bottles; another three came
               from a neighbor, glad to have cash be-
               fore market day when she had expected
               to sell this brew, glass by glass, at the
               side of the road.</p>
               <p>1 mention this trade for several rea
               sons. First, it is an essential medium of
               payment for the assembly of women
               who will fashion this necklace. Second,
               Limbu alcohols facilitate warm memor-
               ies of time spent in the households. And
               not least, the sale of liquor is an impor-
               tant source of cash, the main means of
               women’s marketing experience. Ex-
               clusive brewers of this much appreci
               ated product, these women (like other
               hill women throughout Nepal) refine
               their skills and compete for the cash
               rewards.</p>
               <p>Nowadays, much of the cash a per-
               son accumulates is invested in new
               fields and farming equipment. Never-
               theless, jewelry retains its high value
               and status. Women have a right to jew-
               elry from a very young age. This right
               comes through their family member-
               ship and their economic contribution to
               the household. A nose ring is a girl’s
               first acquisition; she may be no more
               than ten years old when she gets the
               first band. Later, year by year, twirls of
               gold are added to it, sometimes from
               her own earnings, since children are
               given goats to raise and can keep the
               profits from their sale. So by the time
               she is 18, a Limbu girl may have earned
               enough to purchase her first gold ear-
               rings. But the naugiri is a different
               matter. It is acquired with womanhood
               and marriage, a gift from her family at
               the time of her betrothal.</p>
               <p>Five women from our house initiate
               the day’s work. Danamaya takes
               charge from the outset by anchoring the
               nylon rope. She must have done this
               many times before. She rubs the loose
               end of the rope in her palm and patient-
               ly separates its single strands. Forty
               five individual threads fan out in front
               of her from her toe, which anchors the
               knotted end. Each of us takes a single
               strand, then sits around Danamaya.
               We become a human loom fastened to-
               gether by the strings from her toe. Thus
               situated, Danamaya coordinates the
               entire enterprise. She takes each bead-
               ed string as it is filled and hands us an
               empty thread in exchange.</p>
               <p>Such a pivotal role is not new for this
               sober woman who manages our entire
               household. No one appears to object to
               her leadership, a situation which strikes
               me as strange since Danamaya does not
               permanently reside here. It is true this
               is her natal house. But Danamaya gave
               up certain rights when she married and
               took her dowry with her to another vil-
               lage. This house is now her-maitighar
               (maternal house) and Danamaya is a
               visitor along with her baby girl, Deepa.
               In Limbu culture, it is not uncommon
               for women to bring their children to live
               for months in their maitighar while
               their young husbands go off to seek
               work in the Indian and British Gurkha
               forces. Danamaya has decided to do
               this while her husband is away in the
               army. 1 don’t know what he and her
               mother-in-law think of it, but her own
               family is much gratified by Dana-
               maya s long visit.</p>
               <p>We begin to string beads after our
               morning meal. Soon Danamaya s
               neighborhood friend, Lakshmi, joins
               our circle, grasps a nylon thread and
               becomes part of our loom. She holds
               the thread taut and quietly feeds on the
               little green bits, one by one. Lakshmi is
               also visiting her maitighar in Kobek.
               But unlike Danamaya, she does not in-
               tend to return to her marriage house.
               She had remained there, she told me,
               only until her baby was born. The in-
               fant is here with her, and she has no in-
               tention of rejoining her husband, be-
               cause, she says, she doesn t like him.
               As long as she is welcome in her
               maitighar, a Limbu woman in this
               situation can divorce her husband. She
               may also remarry. This is not Lak-
               shmi’s concern at the moment. She has
               joined us in our full moon project, a
               group of women, each clutching a
               string on this human loom, eyes fixed
               on specks of green glass.</p>
               <p>There is no relief. When one string is
               completed and conversation dwells on
               the tedious operation confronting us,
               Danamaya interrupts our dawdling.
               That’s enough, she orders. “Here,
               give it to me. And she hands us an
               empty string.</p>
               <p>An hour passes. Finally Danamaya’s
               left hand holds only a few bare threads.
               In her other are the rest, threaded with
               several inches of beads. We rush to
               complete the remaining strands. With
               all threads beaded, we can now fit on
               the first knob of gold. First a cloth
               washer of bright red is fed onto the
               clump of threads, drawn together to
               squeeze through. We sit back, de-
               lighted as the golden knob shimmers its
               way down the cord. Another disc of red
               cloth fixes the gold in place. This is our
               signal to reassemble around Dana-
               maya. She resumes her anchoring posi-
               tion and again separates the threads,
               allocating one at a time to each of us.
               We bend over our beadwork again.</p>
               <p>The second section of the necklace
               seems to take far less time to complete.
               There are seven of us and we have es-
               tablished a pace independent of any in-
               structions. Soon the 45 threads are
               equally full of green beads. Once again,
               we relax while Danamaya tightens
               them together and pulls on the red
               washer, then the golden giri and
               another band of red cloth. By now the
               pattern of the necklace is apparent.
               Sparkling glass beads, tiny and bright
               green, then a red flash, the soft luster of
               gold, red flash, a block of twinkling
               green, red, another gold knob, red
               again. Time for respite.</p>
               <p>The first to move off our communal
               mat is Ama, who disappears into the
               darkness of the empty house to the
               waiting hearth. She starts a fire from
               red-hot coals nestled under ash. And
               alone, she eases the pot of kodo onto
               the rock grill. In seconds it is warm and
               waiting for us. There is no invitation;
               we simply rise and move inside, gather-
               ing around the hearth. Danamaya
               takes a ladle and stirs the brew, ready
               to scoop out the steaming liquor.
               In front of each of us Mylie sets a
               small dish with a spoonful of black
               spice. This is the pickle, achar, a sharp
               lemony condiment which all Nepalis
               enjoy with their alcohol. Next, we are
               served a larger brass bowl with the
               brew Danamaya has poured out. Some
               of us drink this kodo; others take small
               goblets of raxsi, also warmed to taste.</p>
               <caption>This is Mylie, the only unmarried woman in our
               household. The author had wanted to employ her
               as a research assistant, but the family wouldn’t
               agree, since it would mean the loss of its most val-
               uable worker.</caption>

            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_098.jpg" n="98" xml:id="img_0098"/>
            
               <caption>This woman, a widow, no longer wears the
               naugiri, but she is very fond of her modernistic
               silver ring which, she says, is an old design made
               of very old metal. Silver is no longer valued as
               adornment among these peasants.</caption>
               
               <p>I’m surprised," I remark. "My
               friend, Monomaya is not yet here. She
               told me she would certainly help with
               my naugiri.</p>
               <p>She’ll be here, murmurs Dana-
               maya, as soon as raxsi is ready.
               Hardly have we spoken than into the
               darkness struts Monamaya. Her face is
               that of a timid Oriental peasant, but
               her bearing resembles that of a blust-
               erer. She cheerfully notes our leisure
               and sits down among us as Ama serves
               her an immodest portion of raxsi. “Ah,
               so you re going to have your own Lim-
               bu jewlery, eh, eh?” says Monamaya
               reaching over to take my cigarette. She
               lights one for herself from the smold-
               ering tip. “A sheep got loose and my
               sisters and 1 spent the whole morning
               chasing it home, complains the grin-
               ning latecomer. Everyone takes a
               drink.</p>
               <p>People speak little about Monamaya
               in my presence. They know she and 1
               have become good friends since my ar-
               rival in the village and they respect that
               friendship. It is true Monamaya is a
               social oddity. She doesn’t like to work
               in the fields, an aversion which in this
               rural community is interpreted as irre-
               sponsibility and laziness. Monamaya is
               also the only unmarried woman l’ve
               met here. And she s the only villager
               who walks alone like me on the three-
               day trek to the nearest town. 1 was
               never able to discover the reason for my
               friend’s unpopularity; I continued to
               like her raucous manner.</p>
               <p>When we have drunk our fill, we all
               return to the veranda and remain there
               the rest of the afternoon, until all the
               beading is complete. Monamaya joins
               in and like the other workers she shows
               no incapacity from the bowls of Limbu           
               alcohol we have just consumed around
               the fire. “Kodo and raxsi are nourish-
               ment for us, explains Monomaya.
               Without it, we can’t work; and when
               we take it, we don’t need any other
               food.</p>
               <p>Our work force is now supplemented
               by two elderly women of Salaka lineage
               and therefore clanswomen of my hosts.
               One of these is Buddhamaya, a tall,
               dry-witted lady with aristocratic
               features that glare from her heavily
               wrinkled face. We make some space on
               the mat and Danamaya hands her one
               of the nylon threads. “Who is this for?
               White Didi here, nodding at me.
               (Didi is a widely used Nepali title em-
               ployed as a term of respect for young
               women, both strangers and friends.)
               Buddhamaya continues. “Why do
               vou want this? It is for poor farmers.
               You should have solid gold pieces, here
               here . . . here, stroking me and
               indicating how the gold might encase
               my head and arms like some Aztec-
               Limbu warrior-princess. Even the
               thought itself is an encumbrance.
               No, no, Monamaya earnestly re-
               plies. “White Didi is going to wear this
               to the Chatrapeti festival next week,
               and then she’Il take it with her back to
               America. Everyone there will admire it.
               And Didi will tell the Americans about
               our poor land."</p>
               <p>1 am silent, having already passed
               many hours fruitlessly arguing with
               these and other Nepal hill people about
               the importance of their artistic tradi-
               tions. 1 have not succeeded in convinc-
               ing them that an important distinction
               exists between our admiration and our
               curiosity. They insist my interest is only
               curiosity, and this naugiri will be pre-
               sented as a curio to evoke discussion of
               their culture, which will dwell on econ-
               omics they believe we must interpret as
               poverty.</p>
               <p>I myself have always found it diffi-
               cult to understand how these humble
               farmers can afford such jewelry. A nau-
               giri is the price of a good plowing bul-
               lock, and while every woman wears a            
               naugiri, less than ten percent of house-
               holds possess a pair of oxen. This is
               not, however, a case of naive peasants
               investing only in precious objects. As I
               have said, land is high-priced and peo-
               ple work and save to buy and develop
               new fields. The value of a naugiri is
               hard to fix. Certainly one should not
               compare the cost of a naugiri with that
               of an ox. The naugiri is an obligatory
               expense for every family, like wedding
               feasts when each daughter marries. It is
               an integral part of family social and ec-
               onomic obligations.</p>
               <p>Most Limbus are unable to say why
               they value the naugiri so highly. To
               them its meaning is a whole set of sent-
               iments, deeply implanted, that 1 cannot
               possibly understand, let alone share. It
               is not my dowry. It does not mark my
               marital status. Nor is it my personal in-
               dulgence in ornaments because, as they
               have already noted with some dismay, 1
               don't wear earrings, bangles or
               baubles. Nevertheless, they do want me
               to take this piece of jewelry with me
               when 1 leave. Curio or art, my Limbu
               friends feel it is their gift to me, some-
               thing that symbolizes our bond and the
               cooperative spirit from our months to-
               gether.</p>
               <p>I want the naugiri because it has
               come to symbolize for me the vigor of
               Limbu womanhood. I like its coarse,
               knuckly shape and its dull gold luster.
               But 1 also see it as a beautiful object, a
               true piece of art which in any circum-
               stance, in any culture, retains its beau-
               ty. It is this beauty that I admire. It is
               in this respect that we discover a value
               the Limbus and 1 do not share. To
               them, this naugiri, while it is a well-
               made object, is not particularly beauti-
               ful. For them, an ornament’s beauty is
               a direct function of its weight in gold.
               This is a basic difference in our values.
               And it is because of this that my inter-
               est is seen as curiosity and not admir-
               ation. This is probably the reason why
               these people may eventually allow the
               naugiri or a simpler imitation of it to be
               produced for sale in the marketplace.</p>
            <caption>
               The gold disc earrings and naugiri were borrowed for this portrait since
               the older women had passed theirs on to their married daughters while the
               two young women, not yet married, were still to win theirs.</caption>
               <p>For further reading: L.
               Caplan, Land and Social
               Change in.East Nepal,
               Berkeley: University of
               California Press, 1970;
               B.N. Aziz, Tibetan
               Frontier Families, Dur-
               ham, N.C.: Carolina
               Academic Press, 1978;
               R. and S.K. Jones, The
               Himalayan Woman,
               Mayfield, 1976.</p>
            <p>
               Barbara Nimri Aziz is an an-
               thropologist who lives and
               teaches in New York City.</p>
</div>          
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
