<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Weaving</title>
            <author>Madeleine Burnside</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_030.jpg" n="27"/>
            <head>weaving</head>
            <byline>Madeleine Burnside</byline>

            <p>No mistake. Works at the loom a profusion of thoughts and angrily beats the red into place upon the
               grey. Makes no haste but in a sustained resentment forces them. Places the yarn. The warps are the
               parallel paths of her choices that bear her in a single direction, the teeth of the comb fit them, for a
               moment the colors appear superfluous to the continuing texture. She twists and resents what is seen as
               beauty arising.</p>
            
            <p>At another moment sets the red in blocks in such a way that emotion is confused with attention to the
               work, the beating of the comb an essential part. She says of her children, sometimes I work at the
               loom, sometimes they understand. The difference between my life and theirs is that my disgust is not
               unraveled.</p>
            
            <p>To the rhythm of the shuttle shé breaks the symmetry of the pattern bysturning the fourth arrow
               inwards. In another year she tears her daughter and rémakes the place differently so that scars cross.
               Her efforts are not to achieve but to continue. Rays of light from the window illuminate areas of the
               cloth, the sun marks her shines and creases her face. In the increasing brightness she becomes unable  to discriminate between the fabric and the land.</p>
            
            <p>She wishes to include her children, those changing qualities in her ife, but as she withholds herself
               from her disappointments so she comes no nearer to her desires.</p>
            
            <p>She sits on the floor and for a moment they feel she is accesible to them, her craft gamelike and
               simple, they warm to her, they speak.</p>

            <p>At times weaving is not a pleasant task but A vadteland of drudgere an end to which is not promised.
               She is aware at these times that cutting a rug from the loom does not relieve the ongoing pressure.
               She fasts. She does not sleep. The time opens and closes before her movemente. She continues filled
               with a specific calm spreading her hand on the surface of the loom as, beyond the window, the arms of
               trees are empty, precise, to cátchion the curve of them lines of snow. She considers. It is in this spirit
               that she has named children, placing upon them varn and dye in the hope that they will perform rites
               to announce all the phases of their passing.</p>
            
               <p>And sitting inside the frame she will recast the work, another play of colors whose relations and
               individuals set in her mind the parting of the space. It is time to rewarp the loom; she has come very
               near to the end of the pefmitted period for she has played with the moment here as on other occasions
               she has forced the thread into pláce and had it shy away from her. She again pauses, lingers in the
               empty frame and smiles, having freed herself from the pulling of the hours she,makes perfect
               indifferent gestures at the loom.</p>
            
               <p>She perceives this stage as a part of a chain, the links placed in her life as an offering. She draws the
               edge in or, pulling the thread taut, settles herself within the rigid sides. She gathers her thoughts, they
               pass into the wool as, when it is spun, scenes from the landscape are twisted into it. She spaces the
               measures, this is one thread wrapped around the frame, rising and sinking always the same like herself
               and days.</p>
               
            <p>The weavings are all of this thread that eases from her hand a troubled or a sweet excrescence into the
               world. This is her substance in which the moments are caught, their outline fingered and their matter
               consumed in such a way that they themselves become the fiber of the web.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
     <back>
              <div>
               <p>I am a writer, not a weaver. The text is a metaphor for my craft. The descriptions of weaving are based on
               observations of Navajo women’s traditional skills in Ganado, Arizona, near Canyon de Chelly.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
