<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Conversations &amp; Reminiscences</title>
            <author>Multiple</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_075.jpg"
               n="72" xml:id="img_0075"/>

            <head>CONVERSATIONS &amp; REMINISCENCES</head>
            <p> One function of the artist in modern Western culture has been to seek out the
               despised, rejected or totally overlooked visual objects in her environment and dis-
               cover and reevaluate her aesthetics.</p>
            <p>In an issue devoted to Women’s Traditional Arts, it seemed essential to me to
               seriously reexamine those women who never stopped creating, though their work is
               often bypassed by liberated women artists who have turned away from the trappings of
               their fe- male environment and past.</p>
            <p>The following letter was sent to many women all over the United States. Here are some
               of the replies.</p>
            <quote> Dear<lb/> The fourth issue of Heresies Magazine is entirely devoted to womens
               traditional arts. we know you are a highly skilled craftswoman. we would be very
               pleased if you would allow a taped interviey to be made where you could talk about
               your craft, How you learned it, who you learned it from, to whom you have taught it,
               and how , and what it means to you, are some of the questions we are interested in.
               We hope you will demonstrate your craft and allow it to be documented by a
                  photographer.<persName>Martha Edelheit</persName>
            </quote>
            <p>Martha Edelheit is a painter and filmaker who lives in N.Y.C.</p>
            <div>
               <head>CONVERSATIONS</head>
               <head>THREE CONVERSATIONS</head>
               <byline>by Sylvia Kolbowski, Judy Silberstein, Jean Wagner, IDAWRIGHT</byline>

               <head>IDA WRIGHT</head>
               <p>These raspberry leaves are very, very good . . . if you are going to have a child
                  it’s best to start drinking raspberry tea three months before you give birth and 1
                  was brought up that a gypsy woman could have her child, wash it in a mud puddle
                  and walk off, and one of the reasons was they drank raspberry tea and had a very
                  easy labor. The Indian women did the same.</p>
               <p>I grew up in Vermont, just across the river. My grandfather came down from Canada;
                  he was Indian so we used a lot of these things (medicinal and wild edible plants)
                  at home always. My mother used some of these things in cooking, during the
                  depression years. My father didn’t have work then so we used a lot of these
                  things; some of them, for my mother, the first time. My mother’s ancestry was
                  English and she just had never had much chance to learn these things. I learned it
                  mainly from dad and his sister.</p>
               <p>I always had a great interest in flowers and what was this and what was that, and
                  1 can’t remember when I didn’t have a guide of some kind. 1 was encouraged to look
                  things up by myself as well as being told what they were. When I was 11 I went and
                  lived with my grandfather’s half-sister and her husband and they tried to take the
                  Indian out of me, but they couldn’t do it. They really encouraged me to learn the
                  names of plants. But they used to scold because 1 had a bunch of flowers in one
                  hand and a rock in the other most of the time and they were trying to civilize me.
                  But they didn’t. I often wonder now what they really would think to know that l’m
                  teaching the things that they tried to break me of the habits of using. In fact
                  they knew 1 wanted to teach when 1 got out of high school, but they didn’t believe
                  in borrowing money so you could go on to school. So l got married and started my
                  own kindergarten—we had six kids that lived, we had ten children. My husband
                  wanted 12; I would have stopped at two. After my second child was born, a breech
                  birth, the doctor said, “You’d better not have any more children for a while, I
                  told my husband. He said, “Huh, my mother had 13, you can have more than two;” so
                  1 had ten. A lot of people say how did you raise such healthy children? When we
                  were on the farm we never had more than 85,000 a year for years, most of their
                  growing-up years. Five or six, seven thousand at the most would take care of the
                  cattle and the family. I tell them, I brought them up on dandelions and venison,
                  what do you think?</p>
               <p>I’ve taught some of my children about plants. l’ve got daughters- in-law that
                  listen, but don’t quite believe. My husband used to say. “I wouldn’t eat that, it
                  might be poisonous.” I’d say, “What did you eat for supper tonight? “I don’t know,
                  somethin’, whatevever you put on the table.” I’d say, “Well, you just ate it; have
                  you died?” He’s beginning now not to talk that way. It was a long time now, but
                  for years he’d been eating these things and I just didn’t talk about what I put on
                  the table. Then I began teaching a college course, and he began saying, “Oh, I
                  didn’t know about that.” I was ever so happy when college came nearby and 1 could
                  go to school; l’d always wanted to. 1 got my diploma when I was 49. I was de-
                  termined I was going to get it before I was 50. I made it.</p>
               <p>I do all the canning by myself now. I taught my daughters to can. Yes, it is a lot
                  of work, but l’ve done it so many years that 1 wouldn’t know what it’d be like to
                  have a summer vacation and do nothing. I would feel all the time that I should be
                  putting away things for the winter. During the time I had polio I never knew that
                  it had been discussed, but I just was told in my hospital bed that welfare was
                  going to give money to help feed my children. They evi- dently had not asked
                  because I had 500 quarts of canned goods for my family to use.</p>
               <p>Until recently I thought everybody knew something about some of these wild plants.
                  l’ve always lived in the country and people around me always were using things
                  like dandelions, marsh mari- golds and milkweed. There’s so many things, and just
                  never time enough, nor hands enough in my life. This summer l’ve had the best time
                  because I did have someone who could drive, who was willing to take me wherever 1
                  wanted to go. There’s so much still undone.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_076.jpg"
                  n="73" xml:id="img_0076"/>

               <head>DORA SCHOCHET</head>
               <p>I was born in Bialystok. That was Russia then, now it’s Poland. I’m 47 years here,
                  and I came here I was 26, 27. I came on Thanks- giving day; the boat came here on
                  Kosciusko. It docked, I went right to the turkey. It was already different times
                  when 1 came here. Times weren’t good. My two girls were born. 1 had a lot of time
                  in Europe. I never worked in my life. 1 was not a millionaire’s daugh- ter, but a
                  comfortable parents’ daughter. This work was having friends, going out. In Europe
                  a girl is not working. Only boys, and boys are in the business or going to school.
                  When 1 started to go to school, first I learned Yiddish, then I went to public
                  school; it was Russian. When the Germans came in, I learned German. Then the
                  Polish came in; you changed for Polish. And then I was married. I came to this
                  country; 1 went a little school here, and that’s it. Now it’s a dream, what it
                  was. We were girls thinking of good times. My mother always wanted 1 should go to
                  school and learn how to sew, but I never went. I learned it all myself. When I
                  became of age, 10 or 12, she bought a machine and said, “You must sew on a
                  machine, because I could never do it.” We used to wash the whole week. Before
                  washing, you had to fix things, darn things, iron things, but my mother, she
                  didn’t know how. So my mother always thought 1 should know a little. She always
                  wanted me to go to a dressmaker and she will pay to teach me, but 1 never wanted.
                  I did things that I like to do myself. Maybe I was 12 or 13, I started. I was
                  making my embroidery for myself, for my children. My mother told me it was to
                  prepare for marriage. You always prepare. That’s why I thought to make so many
                  things. I thought for children, and I didn’t think of selling it. Oh no, I would
                  never let Babe sell them. Not selling. She can give to her daughter.</p>
               <p>The colors I always did on my own. 1 chose the pictures to my taste. Things that I
                  felt, flowers, faces, lots of curls. You like green, Ilike blue. I didn’t make the
                  designs. I used to buy them, like a pat tern, and we used to trace them. This was
                  so beautiful when it was done, like a picture of angels. After all, angels should
                  be naked, but how could you have a picture with naked angels. Here was white, here
                  was pinkish satin; this was white wool, like a bear on a floor. Satin like a
                  curtain. This was apple green silk; real silk, beautiful silk. It’s not such a
                  nice face one of them, because angels should really have nicer faces than that,
                  but that was the pattern, and 1 couldn’t do any other way, because 1 wasn’t to
                  change the painting. You see, I criticize my own work. Change it? I could not do
                  it. I only could embroider. This has to be done this way, according to the design:
                  some smaller stitches, some longer. Some day 1l’Il wash it, like in Woolite; I’Il
                  iron it, and I’Il frame it in nonglare glass.</p>
               <p>When I came to this country you know I had a lot of stuff. We didn’t have
                  television, only a gramophone, then later on, we had maybe a radio. In my house my
                  girlfriends and 1 used to get to- gether. So we did work; all day long the young
                  women, the elderly women . . . We came here; a friend of mine gave me a lot of
                  stuff to sell for money; but nobody wanted to look at it. So 1 packed it and sent
                  it back. I kept mine, put it away, packed and unpacked, put it away, air it out,
                  put it away again, air it out and put it away again. I made everything to be used.
                  Definite, I thought. When I was here and nobody wanted to look at it, 1 was very
                  much disappointed. I worked so hard. That’s why I stopped to do it here. Look, I
                  could not even give for a gift what I made. They made fun of it. Sure 1 thought it
                  was art. I thought it something worthwhile to do it. In Europe handwork was very
                  much important.</p>
               <p>I’m married 55 years, so I could write a book with a lot of trouble. When I
                  started embroidering I didn’t have any trouble. I did it for pleasure. I didn’t
                  think of it as a career. Maybe if I was to live now, if I would be as young as
                  you, I wouldn’t want to be a housewife, be- cause, let’s face the facts, it’s a
                  waste of time. It’s not appreciated, if you like. Keep on being what you want to
                  be, be successful. I ad- mire women that’s going to work now. I say, it’s really
                  lovely that my daughter Evelyn goes to work. She’s a person, she s somebody.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>GEORGINA GARCIA</head>
               <p> What I do is embroider. This is the kind of embroidery I do at work—it’s called
                  cross-stitch. It’s a sample for a blouse to see if the color is all right. Here in
                  New York is where most of this kind of em- broidery is done. l’m the
                  “sample-maker. Let’s suppose that you’re a customer, you come to see it, you like
                  it and you order three or four thousand dozen to be made for you. Then that order
                  goes to the embroidery machines and while I can embroider one piece. those
                  machines can produce 250 pieces. There are a few women who are watchers, who for
                  example put the cloth on the frames and take care of the machines, but they’re
                  almost always men. Five or six girls work on each frame; there are helpers there
                  also to change the thread, to mark where the embroidery goes. No one actually
                  draws. The machine works on a key punch. It’s beautiful, the embroidery problem. I
                  love it; it’s beautiful. The “sample-makers” are always women. My work is always
                  done by machine, but there are companies that do hand embroidery —like the
                  sweaters that are embroidered by hand. The company I work for has 14 women who
                  work in their houses because they have children. In one hour, I can do both
                  flowers. You have to keep counting the stitches continually or else you’re lost,
                  the flower loses its shape completely. You have to have a lot of patience. When
                  you do the first one it always takes longer, but l’ve had so much prac-</p>
               <p> tice; by the time you do the second or third it’s much easier. I taught myself
                  how to embroider in Cuba. In my house, as in practically every other house in
                  tropical countries, there was a sew- ing machine, a Singer. But, as a young girl I
                  liked to embroider so much that I embroidered sheets. Before I got married I made
                  my whole trousseau. Completely. 1 used to get my designs from people who 1 saw
                  embroider, and used to see the designs in magazines. I have a dress I made when I
                  was 17 years old; I made the whole yoke by hand. I saw the style somewhere, then 1
                  planned out the pattern myself. My mother, she didn’t embroider but she sewed.
                  Look, my two sisters work as duplicate makers in dress factories and they do well.
                  They went to school in Cuba for two years and got their degrees in sewing. In Cuba
                  there was no remedy, if you were from the poor classes, but to learn to sew or
                  embroider. I lived in a rural town in the Las Villas province. The first job I had
                  when I came to this country was making wedding veils. For one year I sewed on the
                  crowns by hand. After that job I did part-time embroidery because I wasn’t
                  practiced enough on the electric machines. In Cuba you have to use a foot pedal.
                  Then I stopped doing the embroidery that I had done for myself because they paid
                  me more for doing something that I liked. When you go out for work you have to be
                  practical and leave <pb
                     facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_077.jpg"
                     n="74" xml:id="img_0077"/> behind. . . . I don’t have a chance any more to do
                  work for my house. Just think, I work at the company for seven hours. Those who
                  embroider get left without their sight. You can’t do this work for many years
                  without losing your sight. Everyday that passes l’m left with less sight. After I
                  come home I work for another four hours. I start at about 6:30 and it’s 10:30 and
                  l’m still sitting at that machine. Tired. Dead, dead, dead, tired, tired. But I
                  need it. I’m paying for my daughter’s college. On Saturdays I work at home till
                  about three or four. And if I don’t finish then I finish Sunday morn- ing. They
                  pay me by the hour.</p>
               <p>There s no difference at all between the work I used to do for myself and the work
                  I do now. I think it’s art. Because not everybody can do it. In my company l’ve
                  brought out three or four stitches that they didn’t know. I’ve seen them in the
                  beautiful embroid- eries that come from Switzerland that are done on special
                  machines. I put myself to it and figured out the stitches. Because I love it. I
                  can’t explain it, I was born with it. More than any kind of embroid- ery I like
                  doing the work 1 do now. I don’t work for the money alone. I need to work, because
                  no one works unless they have to, but when 1 make something 1 put all my
                  concentration on the job. I do everything 1 can to see that the work comes out
                  pretty. And when it doesn’t come out good 1 take it out and embroider it again. 1
                  love my work, that’s the truth. 1 mean look at that picture, 1 was 17 and I
                  already knew how to sew with ease.</p>
               <p>Sylvia Kolbouski, Judy Silberstein and Jean Wagner are artists who live and work
                  in N.Y.C.</p>
            </div>


            <div>
               <head>EDNA C. MILLER</head>
               <byline>by Nancy Davidson</byline>

               <p> Edna C. Miller is a member of the Amish Community, Arthur, Illinois. Age 53, she
                  has nine children—five girls and four boys (age. 9-30). A widow, she supports her
                  family by running a restaurant in her home; her traditional craft is cooking. Edna
                  Miller would not allow her photograph to be taken.“Thou shalt not make unto thee a
                  graven image . . . was given as justification. The passage from Exodus. </p>



               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>How did you learn to cook?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab> Handed down from my mother. Of course, my mother died when I was 11 so I used
                     to work out” for other people until I was married, so I picked up some of it
                     from them.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Are your recipes written or oral?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Well, like our young girls, they will want a recipe to go by where we do a lot
                     of ours from scratch.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Who helps prepare the meals?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>My girls; they can cook just as good as I can.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Do your boys ever help?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>My oldest boy will help serve and my 14-year-old boy does the dishes.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Is that unusual?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>He wouldn’t, not if we weren’t serving meals, l’ve got enough girls, he
                     wouldn’t help with the dishes. I let the children have the tips.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Do you refer to people that are not Amish as “the English”</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>We just didn’t have another name.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>I was thinking about being American.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Oh yes, we are too, aren’t we? That’s true. We all are.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Are most of the people that come to your restaurant Amish or “English”</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>"English" people.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>When you were a girl, what kinds of chores were you expected to do?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Everything on the farm. Milking, feed the chickens, feed the calves, anything
                     there was.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Is there a difference for your daughters?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I’ve often told them they are lucky they don’t have to work like I used to.
                     No, they don’t have as many chores. They even complain about feeding the
                     chickens.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Does having a restaurant change any of the duties that your daughters have or
                     any of the work you might expect them to do?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>If they didn’t work in the restaurant they would have to have a job someplace
                     else. This is our way of living.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>What kinds of things do your daughters do when they "work out."</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I have one who works in a cabinet shop, the others just do housework.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Is the daughter who works in the cabinet shop learning that craft so that she
                     will eventually become a cabinetmaker?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I don’t know. It’s not usually that a girl will—men do. We’ve got several
                     cabinet shops around here. But she knows how. She does the framing with the
                     cabinets and then she also does the bookwork.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>You have raised your children for eight years by yourself. Do you get help
                     from others?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Oh yes, there has been. I have lots of brothers and sisters, they help and of
                     course my husband’s side, they do too.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Do you come from a large family!</ab>
               </sp>


               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yes, there were 19. See my mother died when I was 11 and my father married
                     again. There were ten children from my mother and nine from my stepmother. So
                     there’s quite a get together.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Do many women in the Amish community have their own businesses?</ab>
               </sp>


               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Oh, there’s usually, a widow will try to have something for a living, there’s
                     like cloth stores, just this and that. Some do baking, so we just started in
                     with this. We enjoy it, people are nice and we get lots of compliments on our
                     dinners. And we enjoyed it until the Health Department came in and we were
                     closed for a month, now my business is really hurt.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Why did the Health Department close the restaurant?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>They said people were getting sick. But I couldn’t get any names. We had seven
                     different inspectors, but it kind of died down and some people are coming
                     back.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Have you had any interesting experiences with “the English” people who eat in
                     your restaurant?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>We get tickled at some of the remarks we hear, like “real cow cream” and you
                     know someone even mentioned Amish water and, well, there isn’t such a thing.
                     Just, well, you know, they think we re so different when really we re just
                     people the same as they are.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Do you find it difficult without a husband to deal with discipline?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Well, T’ve always felt the father can do more with them than the mother, which
                     is right, the father should be the head of the home. It is hard for me to do it
                     alone.</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>NANCY:</speaker>
                  <ab>How do you think it’s changed you?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>EDNA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I don’t know, I think maybe stronger. I know I used to just cry if things
                     didn’t go right, but I can’t do that all the time.</ab>
               </sp>
               <p>Nancy Davidson is an artist and mother presently teaching at the University of
                  Illinois.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_078.jpg"
                  n="78" xml:id="img_0078"/>
               <head><title>My Father’s Brother’s Wife’s Mother</title></head>
               <byline>by Hannah Wilke</byline>
               <p> Mrs. Dora Bund, 86 years old, is my aunt’s mother. Earlier this year, I visited
                  her in the hospital where 1 conducted this interview. She has a heart condition.
                  Also present were Mrs. Bund’s daughter, Beatrice Butter (Beaty), her
                  daughter-in-law, Marcia Bund, and my mother, Selma Butter.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>I saw the blanket you made for my mother. How do you make them and why.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>You want in Yiddish or in English...</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Ich can nich sprechen Yiddish. English, please.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I make them. It’s my work . . . I have to do something.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>You never made the blankets until about six years.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>No. It cost too much money. Then my grandson-in-law gave me the wool. For the
                     great-grandchildren 1 got blankets. Every birthday I make blankets. Before I
                     must make money. I sew dresses. Then I stopped sewing, start this.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>So, when you were 80, you stopped working and started to make the
                     blankets.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Even in the nighttime, l’m sick and I can’t sleep. I take my work and sit in
                     the bed, till l’m tired. I make the rule, I knit. When I was ten years old I
                     start to sew. Europe is not like over here. Was in school three hours a day,
                     and I only worked to do something. One day my mother looked for me in the whole
                     park. She can’t find me. I was with the dressmaker. When it was night- time 1
                     came home. Everybody asked me where 1 was. And I say, 1 want to sew. 1 don’t
                     want to go to school. So my mother went to this dressmaker and say, all right,
                     she learn to sew, only she must go two hours to school. My mother paid this
                     lady three dollars for two years to teach me to sew. When the two years finish,
                     I say, this is the last day 1 be over here. The dressmaker tell me, you owe me
                     ten days because you were in shul one day, you were sick one day . . . After
                     that 1 got a different dressmaker. She gave me 815 for two years. Thirty cents
                     a week. I was 14, 15 years old. Must be there all day. Come eight o’clock till
                     eight o’clock. Was a strike. Must be union. And the strike was finished, we
                     worked from eight to five, from nine to six. One dressmaker take me for a
                     dollar a week. I was 16. I work for this woman not too long. My family had a
                     big house then. One dressmaker came by and said to my father and mother, she
                     pay 815 a year rent to put her machine in their window. She said, maybe you
                     would buy a machine and I be partners with you. My father go right away and
                     bought me a new machine for 850. And I stop that othei work. 1 was very small.
                     When the people come and I take measure, 1 can’t reach them. My father was a
                     carpenter. He make me a bench to step up. When I married I got three machines.
                     Four girls work for me.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SELMA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I remember you saying you buried your children in a trench during the First
                     World War.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>My husband was in war. In Poland. After the Germans come in my country.
                     Thirty-six people there was in a trench. Others covered us up. It was a day and
                     a night. In the morning about six o clock the people came and say, come in, the
                     Germans is here! We was three years with the Germans. When my husband came from
                     the war it was four years already.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>And you were still a dressmaker?</ab>
               </sp>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>What kind of dressmaker? Nobody got even to eat. I give up a machine for the
                     bread.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>When did you come here?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>1922.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did you open the store immediately?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>No. Right away I bought a machine. In the house. Because I got two small
                     children.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Your husband was with you too?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>We come together. My husband come in America when he was 16 years old. Till
                     20. He had to leave America to go back to be a soldier. Then we married. Six
                     months after we married, broke out the war and he had to go back. Only my
                     husband became a sick man from the war. He was all life sick. Over here you
                     come soldier from the war, is sick, is got benefits. In my country nobody can
                     get nothing.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>At 60 you opened up the business because your hus- band couldn’t work any
                     more.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab> My husband was 15 years in the house. I come to the store and I sewing dolls.
                     I sew kitchen curtains. All day I was in the store, and at nighttime. People
                     still now got curtains. Never 1 use a pattern. Now I can’t even take the needle
                     in the finger.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Now you have arthritis, but you can knit?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>To knit I can put the needle in there. But even sewing a button I get stuck in
                     the finger.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Which do you like better?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I like to be finished already. What can I like now, tell me? Where is going I
                     must go. I got a grandfather. He say, when time is come, he get a summons, he
                     go to court. When is come for me, must go to court. When my grandfather lived,
                     he say will come a time when will be no walking. People will be flying. And
                     when my papa and grandfather lived was not even taxes and bills.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BEATY:</speaker>
                  <ab>No taxis and automobiles.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I was 15, 16 years old when my grandfather died. We lived together. My
                     grandfather tells my grandmother to go buy a kerchief. I make the hems and he
                     gives me two cents. You be good, this window be for your machine. When he is
                     die, I push right away the machine in this window.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>So if you put the machine in the window you were a seamstress. It would be
                     like a sign on the door. And when your grandfather died, you knew it was the
                     time.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>My grandfather was a baker. He baked bread. My grandfather was rich. My
                     grandfather maybe got 12 children. Al- ways die. Small babies, babies, babies
                     die. Only one children. One dog. Before when I was occupied I forgot. Now is
                     come back.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BEATY:</speaker>
                  <ab>She is the only one left.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Nobody. Only my aunt, was my father’s sister, was come over here.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BEATY:</speaker>
                  <ab>At home she (Dora) did a little dressmaking. Like when I was a teenager. We
                     would take a walk on Clinton Street and I would tell her 1 like the neck of
                     this and this sleeves of this, and she would make it. She used to holler at me
                     because I cried if it didn’t look so good, while she was working. And she would
                     say, to a fool you don’t show half labor. I always had original dresses. She
                     never worked with a pattern. She should have been a designer in a big place
                     with ideas.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Do you call them blankets or art works?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I say this is a blanket I make.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>And you made that up yourself, the idea of stripes and squares.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yeh. Yeh. With stripes, each is a different color, different shape, different
                     size. I sew together and put border around. Make squares is two times as hard
                     as other. Each strip got maybe ten squares, eight inches by eight inches. Each
                     square different design. Make strip 80 inches, then more strips and sew
                     together.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>How long do you take?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I make this in four, five weeks. </ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>You like to make objects that are useful?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I don’t know. I make. I say, you like it, take it.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did you keep any for yourself!</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I got for myself two. I make over a hundred.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BEATY:</speaker>
                  <ab>A toaster cover she made, a hassock cover . ..</ab>
               </sp>


               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_079.jpg"
                  n="79" xml:id="img_0079"/>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>MARCIA:</speaker>
                  <ab>The cover for my rotisserie. The whole house.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>A couch I covered.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>So you are covering all the ugly stuff.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I never want to be rich. Was satisfied with what I got Because when I married
                     I was rich. Paper money is no good money. Still have money from Poland. Got a
                     big house. Lose house because the money worth nothing. When the soldiers came
                     they take away everything. Even Beaty was a baby, got shoes, take away shoes. I
                     got when I was married two dozen shirts. Everything embroidered. The soldiers
                     took away. This night they kill four people, because the people don’t give
                     them. 1 say, take. Is come, the knives was like this. You scream, you see, you
                     must be shot.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>So you were lucky you had something to give them,</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DORA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Take away everything. Wasn’t rich wasn’t nothing.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>HANNAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Real barter has nothing to do with money. It has to do with survival. We all
                     have our own ways to survive.</ab>
               </sp>
               <p> Hannah Wilke is a woman-person-artist who has exhibited at museums around the
                  country and is affiliated with Ronald Feldman Gallery in N.Y.C., Margo Leavin
                  Gallery in Los Angeles and Marian Deson Gallery in Chicago.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head><title>SARAH MANDELL and ENID ALJOE</title></head>
               <byline>by Judith Henry and Dee Shapiro</byline>

               <p> Sarah Mandell doing needle wor</p>
               <p> Sarah Mandell and Enid Aljoe with collaborative piece</p>
               <p> Sarah Mandell, grandmother of Dee Shapiro, is 84 years old, Jewish, born in
                  Russia. For the past 13 years she has been living with her daughter. Enid Aljoe is
                  55 years old, born in Jamaica, West Indies. She has been the housekeeper in Dee’s
                  mother’s house hold for 23 years.</p>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Where did you learn to sew, Grandma?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>In Europe they had no school. They just had someone to teach the children how
                     to work so they could work for nothing. If a woman had a house and was getting
                     work from the neighbors, shirts or blouses, so she took a couple of young girls
                     and taught them how to sew—meanwhile, they were sewing for her the things, and
                     when they knew enough most of them went to America and went into the factories
                     and worked on shirts and blouses. That was all they knew, and those who didn’t
                     know went into domestic work. I was 12 years old in London, I went to school
                     but one of my mother’s friends showed me how to sew buttons on. When 1 came
                     here 1 went to the factory and sewed buttons.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>How many years did you work there?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Not long, I got married. After 25 years I went back to work again in the same
                     factory. I was what you call a finisher, sew- ing buttons, making buttonholes,
                     all handwork. It was the men working the pressing machines, sewing machines and
                     cutting ma chines. After the World War, the women came in and were sewing by
                     machine.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>JUDY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did the men get higher pay?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yes, but it was what you call slave labor.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Could you work your way up in the factory?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>No. I didn’t want to go back to work as a finisher because the operators were
                     getting a union, but they wouldn’t give me a chance to go to the machine, and 1
                     knew how to sew.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Why not?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>Because I would have to get more money and the boss would say, “Oh, I need
                     you, Sarah, for this kind of work and you can’t be bothered going to the
                     machine and work,” because he knew 1 would get more money.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>JUDY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did you do any other kind of handwork?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>I took home lamp shades, that was when I was married and had two children. I
                     made nice money at the lamp shades, 1 wouldn’t say a lot—just a helping
                     hand.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>JUDY:</speaker>
                  <ab>How long have you been doing this (a bed cover similar to a quilt)!</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>About two years. She [Enid) taught me how, and my daughter is in merchandising
                     and gets me swatches of material for nothing. I try not to have two colors the
                     same. If 1 have a good green, I like to finish it with a brown. Enid is very
                     good for colors; sometimes make a mistake and put two colors the same. 1 know
                     l’m not careful.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ENID:</speaker>
                  <ab>Because you’re in a hurry.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>If I wasn’t in a hurry I wouldn’t have great-grand- children. I have one 20
                     years old.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>How did you learn to make these, Enid?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ENID:</speaker>
                  <ab>In Jamaica, the people had sufficient interest in the youngsters, so they
                     would formulate a sewing class at home and they would teach you the different
                     things to do. One of my sisters used to have a class and 1 watched.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Have you thought about selling them?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ENID:</speaker>
                  <ab>Who, me? No.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>How could she get a customer? She wants 8500.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ENID:</speaker>
                  <ab>To be honest, l’m not kidding.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>I’m not kidding either when I know that nobody in the world would give you or
                     me—not even 8200</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did people make those things for sale in Jamaica?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ENID:</speaker>
                  <ab>They would make appliqué things in Jamaica for a living. They would have an
                     organization and the girls get a weekly or monthly salary. Then it goes to the
                     store where the tourist comes in it gets the price. You must know the value of
                     handwork to pay for it</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>What did your mother do in Jamaica?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ENID:</speaker>
                  <ab>She had nine children.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did she do needlework at home?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ENID:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yes, she sewed my father’s shirts and my brother’s shirts.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SARAH:</speaker>
                  <ab>My mother sewed by hand till the minute she died. There were not machines in
                     my mother’s day. Later 1 had a machine already and she used to come over to my
                     house and bring me sewing. She always basted it and made me new curtains all
                     the time.</ab>
               </sp>

               <p> Judy Henry is an artist uho lives in N.Y.C. Dee Shapiro is a pattern painter uho
                  lives on Long Island.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_080.jpg"
                  n="80" xml:id="img_0080"/>

               <head><title>KATHLINE IDELLA THOMPSON, My Mother, and DORA LUCINDA JOHNSON, My
                     Maternal Grandmother</title></head>

               <byline> Phyllis Thompson</byline>
               <p>Dora Lucinda Johnson is 82 years old. The mother of seven chil- dren, she resided
                  on a farm in Seneca, Maryland for 70 years. Since the death of her husband in
                  1974, she has lived with her daughter, Kathline Thompson, in Philadelphia.
                  Kathline Idella Thompson is awidowed mother of four children. Presently, she is a
                  tax examiner for the Department of Internal Revenue in Philadelphia.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>Where were you living Granny, when you were piec- ing quilts?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>Darnestown, Maryland, I reckon.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>Probably out Sugarland where she grew up.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>Out Sugarland. Maybe so, I reckon—maybe it was out Sugarland.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>I don’t know whether she is referring to when she was a child or after she was
                     grown up and married. 1 know very little about where she lived when she was
                     growing up. When I remember about you quilting, you were married then . . . you
                     had us</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>I was grown up? Don’t remember whether I was married or not when 1 was piecing
                     quilt squares . . . 1 used to piece lots of them.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did you create particular kinds of designs or patterns that had names?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>I make four pieces you know, like that, then sew’um together, then make
                     another strip, sew it together, then . ..</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>You worked with four squares sewn together. ...</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yes, I had my squares cut.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>Were all of your quilts in square patterns? Were there circles or
                     triangles?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>Just straight squares ... used to make squares, you know . . . something like
                     that. We sew’um togethei ... we sew all four squares together, take another
                     strip of materia and put on all four sides and sew it together.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>Where did you get the fabric scraps?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>We saved the scraps. My mother did sewing you see and she saved the scraps and
                     things to make quilts—quilt pieces. Lots of people used to bring sewing for her
                     to do.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>She could sew very well then, and made extra money for her family. Did you
                     ever make quilts for your family?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>No. I used to piece quilt squares and things throw rugs to put in the kitchen
                     like that when I was home with my mother. I pieced’um for her - she used to
                     make quilts. She’d get material to put on the back side then take some raw
                     cotton to put in between, then she had a thing called a rack you know, to put
                     the quilt on. We get the quilt on the rack and hang it up and the quilt would
                     be rolled up during the day and down at night when we were working.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>You would hang it up . . . how? From the ceiling?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yes, from the rafters. We’d sit there and sew on it. . . . make little strips
                     across the quilt, about that wide and connect the squares.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>Well, well . . . here is one right here. About how long did it take to
                     complete a quilt?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>It depended on how long I worked on it.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>I’m not sure of course, but I think her mother did this. Aren’t these some
                     that you got from up Granmumma’s house after she died? Because after she had
                     all of us, she didn’t have time to do that.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>Whose is that? They look like some of mine.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>This came out of your trunk. I think she helped do that. This was done on the
                     sewing machine too.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>Well, I used to do some on the sewing ma- chine—some by hand and some on the
                     sewing machine.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>I just ran upstairs and grabbed these while you were talking. They had to come
                     from up Granmumma’s house. She had a lot of time to quilt after her children
                     were grown.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>When we were little girls, we were taught how to sew squares and then Momma
                     would put them together.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did you do any crocheting or knitting?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRANDMOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>Very little.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>The only knitting I know of her doing was these little throw rugs to put in
                     the kitchen.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>Those knitted rugs made out of old stockings and socks. When did you learn how
                     to crochet and knit?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>When I started high school. Well, you know, I learned the basic beginning
                     stitches. I would follow directions to crochet doilies. I never really knitted
                     anything. I just learned plain knitting I liked to crochet. I crocheted quite a
                     few doilies, but they were small. At one time. I used to use them a lot.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PHYLLIS:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yes, I remember when you used them. I recall that there were many women in the
                     Projects who had ruffled doilies in their homes. That was at least 20 years
                     ago. You washed and starch- ed the doilies on Saturdays. Sometimes you used a
                     sugar mixture for starch. How was that done?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MOTHER:</speaker>
                  <ab>I would starch my doilies, but that didn’t make them stand up. My neighbor
                     showed me how to fix a starch out of sugar and water. You soaked the doily in
                     the sugar mixture and it began to dry, you pulled up the ruffled sides and they
                     would stand stiff and remain in place. You know, l’m surprised that the roaches
                     weren’t attracted to them, but they weren’t.</ab>
               </sp>
               <p>Phyllis Thompson is an artist and teacher. Presently she is an Assistant Professor
                  of Printmaking at Cornell University.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>ELSE GRAUPE</head>
               <byline>by Grace Graupe-Pillard</byline>
               <p> My mother, Else Graupe, was born in 1912, in the town of Rheda, Westphalia,
                  Germany.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>How did you get interested in dressmaking?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>I always liked nice clothing . . . As a child I used to make doll’s dresses .
                     . . I had the fanciest dressed dolls . . . They went to the opera in velvet
                     capes . . . If I had my way I would have chosen dressmaking as a profession
                     rather than study medicine [Ms. Graupe attended medical school for one and a
                     half years before Hit- ler’s policy of Aryanization cut off her studies) . . .
                     but no middle- class girl in Germany was ever allowed to make a living working
                     with her hands.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Who taught you?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>A seamstress came to our house and did sewing for the <pb
                        facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_081.jpg"
                        n="81" xml:id="img_0081"/> family. I watched her. . . the way she cut the
                     material . . . she let me help . ..</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Were you encouraged in this talent?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>No.. . no. . . of course not. . . . If you do it for yourself it was okay. . .
                     . but you weren’t encouraged to make it your pro- fession. . . . Soon after the
                     Nazis came to power I had to stop medical school . . . l had to learn a trade .
                     . . so of course 1 went back to dressmaking. I went to Berlin . .. I was lucky
                     . . . 1 got an apprenticeship with Gerson—a store like Bergdorf Goodman. But I
                     had just begun when orders came that Jews could no longer work there. The head
                     of all the tailors (the “meister”) who was al- so Jewish had to leave. So the
                     store asked him to work from his home. . . . He hired four or five women—three
                     were really ex- perienced and two were learning to sew . . I started from the
                     bottom . . . I had to do the sweeping . . . 1 spent three years as an
                     apprentice and then 1 passed my journey- man’s examination.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>... like a guild system?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yes . . . Just when I finished, I had to leave Germany and emigrated to this
                     country. I started here from scratch. Through the National Council of Jewish
                     Women, I got jobs . . . alterations mainly at first . . . then one customer
                     recommended another . .. eventually 1 got private customers.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>What is your method of working?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>First I get the material and then I drape it on a “dress maker’s figure” . . .
                     here a little pleat . . . there a little pleat . . . play around with it. I get
                     an idea of style and then 1 start to cut. always make everything tailored. I
                     believe in letting the material speak for itself . . . giving it an elegant,
                     smart look . . . typically European . . . just use plain, simple, straight
                     lines.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Were there any pieces that particularly excited you?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>I used to make evening dresses with a lot of embroidery .. all hand done . . .
                     I never use patterne ... They took me two weeks, working 1. to 14 hours a day
                     .. . 1 used to love tha because the embroidery just came by itself ... I added
                     all kinds of beads and stui ... but the style was still plain and simple ...
                     all hand done . . .</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did you use a special sewing machine?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>I have my Singer machine which is about 30 years old. 1 once had one with all
                     those gadgets, but 1 threw it right out . ..1 don’t need it.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Do you consider yourself an artist?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>No .. . never . . . for me it was just a living . .</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Well, obviously it was more than a living?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>To tell you the truth . . . it never entered my mind that 1 might have any
                     artistic ability . . . except for one friend ... she always said that 1 was a
                     real artist.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GRACE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Did you ever have the ambition to be a designer?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ELSE:</speaker>
                  <ab>I would have . . . I had several offers to go into business for a big
                     manufacturer. I designed the company’s first two samples from which they
                     manufactured hundreds of thousands of blouses. The boss very much wanted me to
                     be his designer . . . but I didn’t feel right . . . it’s a nerve-wracking
                     business . . . and second your father wanted me to stay at home with you
                     children . . . I always say . . . now 1 am liberated, he can’t hold me back
                     anymore . . . but at that time I wasn’t . . . if 1 were to do it over again
                     today . . . 1 would open my own dress design shop somewhere in midtown Man-
                     hattan. . . . Remember how 1 used to take a suitcase and go to the people . . .
                     I should have had a place . . . they should have come to me . . . 1 wasted so
                     much time . . . but 1 am not sorry . . . 1 really enjoyed my work . . . and
                     love it now more than ever . . . since 1 am free to sew for my best
                     customer—myself [laugh].</ab>
               </sp>
               <p>Grace Graupe-Pillard is a painter who lives and works in New Jersey and shows at
                  Razo Gallery in N.Y.C..</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>IDA KOHLMEYER</head>
               <byline>by Lynda Benglis</byline>
               <p>The first woman of importance to me wass one of my art teachers, Ida Kohlmeyer. I
                  made a special trip to New Orleans to interview her and to speak of her past and
                  our relationship at Sophie New- comb College where I studied art in the 1960s.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>LYNDA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Ida, how did you happen to come to art?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IDA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I’Il begin at the beginning. . . . I was not young, almost 29 years old,
                     grievously immature and becoming aware of the shatter- ing fact that my life
                     was without purpose. I attribute my “growing up to the experience encountered
                     as a soldier’s wife during war- time, and to the sobering thought that life
                     might well come to an abrupt and premature end without much warning.</ab>
                  <ab>My exposure to art had been sporadic and meagre. I turned to it, I think, with
                     a lingering dilletantism, expecting to find it mildly absorbing. I have never
                     been so mistaken about anything before or since. At the urging of a friend, who
                     was aware of my dilemma, 1 enrolled in the John McCrady School in New Orleans,
                     and was there initiated into the exhilaration of creative work.</ab>
                  <ab>The following fall, I signed up as a part-time student at the Newcomb Art
                     School of Tulane University to take drawing and painting. After two years I
                     began working toward a Master of Fine Arts degree. Because of a part-time
                     curriculum, two small children and not too brilliant progress, it took four
                     years to complete the requirements for the degree. The summer of 1956 I
                     attended Hans Hoffman’s School in Provincetown, and during the spring of 1957,
                     Mark Rothko came to Newcomb as artist-in-residence. Both of these artists were
                     great influences in my life.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>LYNDA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I think it was unusual that an artist with your background should have had the
                     seriousness of purpose to pursue your interests with both of these major
                     artists. It was your professionalism that impressed me, for I had never had
                     real contact before with a woman artist. You always were prepared with notes
                     and examples of art works in class, and 1 can <pb
                        facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_082.jpg"
                        n="82" xml:id="img_0082"/> remember never wanting to miss those classes.
                     Further, I was amazed and thrilled that you actually wanted to buy my art work
                     and did! Also, you saw that it was placed in a serious commercial art gallery
                     in New Orleans.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IDA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Lynda, I don’t remember doing this for many of my students, but there were
                     others and this was my extra dividend in gratification as a teacher.</ab>
               </sp>

               <p>Linda Benglis, an artist, was born in Lake Charles, Louisiana, in 1941. She left
                  Louisiana in 1964, lived in New York from 1964-1973, and since 1973, has been
                  living both in Venice, Caspnia, und lII. C., wending an euuadl undunt d üine iun
                  balt puses</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>STELLA CHASTEEN</head>
               <byline>by Barbara Zucker</byline>
               <p> Cakes are like clowns. Both are so deeply imbedded in our culture that their
                  strangeness is ignored.</p>
               <p>The day I got married the car broke down so my parents drove us to our wedding. I
                  sat in the back seat looking up front at the card- board box which held the cake
                  wedged in between my parents. Two circles had been cut out of the top so that the
                  heads of the tiny china bride and groom had enough room to peek out. It looked
                  like people in a surreal sweat box.</p>
               <p>In Florida I once had a student whose art was all about food and feeding people.
                  In one piece a thin girl lay still on a table for hours. wearing the entire meal
                  which spread down around her in carefu. patterns. Spectators consumed bits from
                  her throughout the even- ing. Ethel Ann’s real piece de resistance was her
                  Master’s project an exorcism of her marriage. She made a gigantic wedding cake
                  carved of wood and foam, complete with doves, net, roses and fes toons. In the
                  performance she stood on the cake, wearing her wed ding dress, talking out her
                  marriage. A man in a tux acted the groom and other performers straightened up,
                  made beds, fetchec and carried. She also baked a traditional wedding cake and
                  mixec some punch which the audience consumed. Her work-for-money and her art work
                  overlapped. She cooked each week for an entire church congregation—shopped, baked
                  and served the Sunday meal.</p>
               <p>Stella Chasteen lives in Woodstock with her three children and her husband.
                  Trained in art academies in London, she came to America in the sixties. She
                  stopped painting because she “didn’i know what to paint.” Her cakes, which she
                  makes as an act of love for her children, are wonderful.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>STELLA:</speaker>
                  <ab>My first cake was a car.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>How do you carve it?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>STELLA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I bake the cakes, then freeze them and carve it while theyre frozen. 1 can
                     carve it quite precisely frozen. It doesn’t crum- ble or squoosh. 1 use
                     poundcake because it’s a nice solid consisten- cy, not too heavy. Someone
                     advised me to use toothpicks to hold it together.</ab>
                  <ab>The first one was such a success. The children said, “I want one too, 1 want
                     one too.” They can think up whatever they want. The mountain cake, I had just
                     started teaching Tom how to ski. His birthday is in the winter. You can always
                     tell what he was into that year by what his cake was. The others are more into
                     their fantasies. I did a monster head for Rhody. Sometimes they give specific
                     direc- tions. Tessa’s dog had to be black and white. Rhody’s monster had to
                     have a head that was half blue and half green. After that, at a school
                     fund-raising I made miniature monster heads. I used cashew nuts for horns. All
                     the kids bought up the cakes immediately. I use regular butter frosting and
                     then color it with food coloring and when I want real white I have to get white
                     butter.</ab>
                  <ab>I made Tessa a fairy. It was the most difficult because it was tall and tended
                     to topple over. It was a hot day in June and the fairy kept falling; I had to
                     keep propping it up. I painted the fairy’s face like a china doll. It was
                     holding a magic wand which was a sparkler which I lit.</ab>
                  <ab>There was a show at the Victoria and Albert Museum in London of cakes. A
                     friend saw the show and said my cakes could have been there. I said, “No,”
                     because for me it is very important that the cakes be eaten. I would have a
                     totally different attitude about what I was making if it was going to be around
                     for any length of time. It can be more outrageous, more goofy—it’s carefully
                     considered, but not in the same way as something permanent. Besides, the kids
                     get such a thrill out of eating it. It’s sort of gory: “I want the head, I want
                     the eye, give me the leg!” It’s great!</ab>
                  <ab>I like to make use of edible stuff to decorate them with and find unusual
                     things. For the wheels of Rhody’s car I found cookies that looked like spokes
                     of a wheel. For Tessa’s dog’s ears I used Oreo cookies. I once made Tessa a
                     circus cake. All the ropes and trapezes were made out of shoelace
                     licorice.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Why don’t you have more photographs of them?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>STELLA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I make the cake the morning of the party. It takes about three hours just to
                     decorate. Then l’ve got to get the party together. The rush of the party
                     prevents taking pictures. I never have any film in the camera. For the tropical
                     island cake, you know that health food sugar? I used that for sand for the
                     beaches. I also made a traditional English castle with gray frosting. The
                     grownups looked at the frosting and said, “eeeough, gray frosting!” but the
                     kids thought it was terrific because it looked like a castle. I bought knights
                     on horseback and little flags to fly from the turrets. I love doing it.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Is there anything else that gives you that kind of pleasure?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>STELLA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yes, pottery does, ceramics. Actually, making it is what’s so nice about the
                     cake. It’s all in the doing of it. Then it's gone. It’s not sitting around. The
                     appreciation is immediate. You’ve got all the kids who come to the birthday
                     party.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>You don’t think of them as art?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>STELLA:</speaker>
                  <ab>No, I don’t really.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Why not?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>STELLA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I think of them as cakes.</ab>
               </sp>
               <p>Barbara Zucker is an artist who teaches, writes and loVes her daughter.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_083.jpg"
                  n="83" xml:id="img_0083"/>

               <head>7 WOMEN IN NEW JERSEY:</head>



               <lg>
                  <l>Barbara Schaff—pottery</l>
                  <l>Joan Wortis—weaving</l>
                  <l>Pat Frank—goldsmith</l>
                  <l>Vivian O’David—quilting</l>
                  <l>Adele Blumberg—embroidery</l>
                  <l>Lois Gerb—rug hooking</l>
                  <l>Paula Wachtel—Ikebana (Japanese flower arranging)</l>
               </lg>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>You are talking to a potter who’s into function. I have been through a kind of
                     soul-searching siege about whether I should make ART, capital letters, the way
                     most of my contemporar- ies are doing, and 1 very self-consciously set out to
                     do that, which, of course ended in total disaster because it wasn’t fun, wasn’t
                     free and I didn’t enjoy it very much. 1 make things that are according to my
                     grandmother’s proverb who, may she rest in peace, was Russian ... she said,
                     “You should never have anything in your home but what is useful and beautiful.”
                     I make very simple, very quiet, useful things for everyday because I have this
                     vague philosophy that it en- riches the quality of human life to use handmade
                     things. I don’t be- lieve in using good things only for company—Who is company?
                     1 deserve good things. 1 am a maker of crocks and jugs and cups and mugs and
                     teapots and bowls and everything that you can possibly use in the kitchen. Very
                     primitive, very traditional, tremendousl satisfying.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MADGE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Joan, what about your weaving?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>JOAN:</speaker>
                  <ab>I feel very close to what Barbara is saying. I do functional work.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>It goes against the trend.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>JOAN:</speaker>
                  <ab>Yes, very much against the trend. I make garments for both women and men,
                     primarily for women. I came to it really from a great love of folk art, which
                     l’ve always been attracted to—partic- ularly embroidered things, woven things.
                     I want things to be worn. l’m not making things that you might wear once to a
                     costume ball—1 want people to wear things to adorn themselves and fee beautiful
                     in what I make.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Neither one of us designs anything for use only. Aes- thetic considerations
                     are extremely important. It has to be both use- ful and beautiful.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>This issue is concerned with breaking down these barriers. Not considering
                     yourself an artist because of the attitude toward crafts.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>That’s a tempest in a teapot. Art versus craft.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>JOAN:</speaker>
                  <ab>That position—that your work is an art work, the pots no longer have openings,
                     they are nonfunctional pots, the weaving is no longer weaving—that is for use,
                     for a floor cover or a wall cover to keep out the cold or on the body. It
                     becomes a wall hanging in the same way that a painting is. Those of us who are
                     working in the contemporary crafts market, as Barbara and 1 are, are sometimes
                     made to feel like second-class citizens because we are not arts/crafts
                     people.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PATTY:</speaker>
                  <ab>I think of myself as an artist, and it doesn’t matter what I work in, l’m an
                     artist, period. I think Barbara’s an artist even though she’s very stubborn
                     about considering herself a craftsperson. Anybody who has an idea, takes some
                     material and transforms it in- to something usable, whether you hang it on the
                     wall or put soup into it or stick it on your arm, that is an art object. If
                     nobody in the world likes it except you or your mother, then you have a
                     problem.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PAULA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Poverty.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PATTY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Right. Or you get a job in the supermarket and so you have time to do the
                     other stuff. We’re all artists. Painters are just as much craftspeople, if
                     they’re worth their salt, because they have to learn how to deal with the
                     materials they work with.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>How did you get into jewelry?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PATTY:</speaker>
                  <ab>My mother and aunt dragged me through lots of depart ment stores. My mother
                     would give me jewelry to play with, good costume pieces. I would sit around and
                     stare at them for hours- they were like things I played with as a kid. When I
                     got into college, I had rocks which were semi-precious stones and I thought I
                     would take a jewelry course to cut stones. I had an instant rapport with the
                     silver. 1 sold my first ring in three days and I thought, my goodness, I didn’t
                     sell my first painting. So the monetary aspect of my person- ality . . . hm,
                     there’s gold in them thar hills.</ab>
               </sp>
            </div>

            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_084.jpg"
               n="84" xml:id="img_0084"/>
            <div>

               <head>Part of a discussion by Dee Shapiro and Madge Huntington</head>

               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Now your mother is collecting your jewelry.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PATTY:</speaker>
                  <ab>I can’t keep anything that’s gold around my mother. It’s like the company
                     store; 1 borrowed money from her, then she says, “Let’s work a deal.” She’s got
                     three of my chains.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>Now you know how I feel. l’m into Patty up to my neck in hock.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>JOAN:</speaker>
                  <ab>But isn’t the satisfaction wonderful to have all those things people
                     made.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BARBARA:</speaker>
                  <ab>I’m a trade junkie.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>JOAN:</speaker>
                  <ab>We go to the craft fairs, running around looking at other people’s things and
                     wanting to live with the things that other people have made with their hands,
                     which we couldn’t afford.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PATTY:</speaker>
                  <ab>Right. I can’t afford to keep my jewelry.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MADGE:</speaker>
                  <ab>Vivian, are you a crafts artist aside from being a school principal?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VIVIAN:</speaker>
                  <ab>No. What I think makes me legitimate in this group is that 1 came into
                     quilting via a sister. I lost my sister a year ago and l’ve gone on with the
                     work because it’s something l’ve grown up with. I brought along with me a quilt
                     my grandmother did, it’s over 100 years old.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEE:</speaker>
                  <ab>I think many of the crafts came out of a definite need for the objects as a
                     function in the home.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>JOAN:</speaker>
                  <ab>However, there were the crazy quilts that were done in the latter half of the
                     nineteenth century, and l’ve seen many of them come pristine out of the trunk
                     and never been backed, never been used. Why?</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VIVIAN:</speaker>
                  <ab>I think even with the 11 children, no doubt there would have been one quilt
                     that was put someplace that certain people saw and the rest of you
                     wouldn’t.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ADELE:</speaker>
                  <ab>I’ve always worked with the needle.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VIVIAN:</speaker>
                  <ab>And beautifully.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ADELE:</speaker>
                  <ab>From the time I was five until now, which is a considera- ble number of years,
                     I have always had something in my hand or in my pocketbook. If I travel, I
                     always have something with me. And it’s amazing how you get contact with
                     perfect strangers if you’ve got something in your hands. We were in Cuzco,
                     Peru, and our plane was about five hours late. I was working on that seat
                     you’re sitting on, Dee. An Indian woman with a baby was learning these stitches
                     with me, and it was the most wonderful thing . . . 1 wanted to give her child a
                     doll that we had just bought; she said no, she couldn’t ac- cept it because she
                     made it (the doll). So we were exchanging our crafts and a perfect stranger
                     took pictures of us and sent them to me. Me with this Indian woman learning
                     these stitches. For me, the culmination of a busy day is when we can sit down
                     at 11 o’clock and watch the news and I don’t have to do any other work. You
                     don’t have to watch television, you can listen, you can be with your hus- band,
                     you’re doing something with your hands, and you’re creating something. Before I
                     was married 1 had this tremendous passion to accomplish all of these things.
                     Wherever I went visiting relatives. l’d take my tablecloths along with me. And
                     they used to kid me. don’t know if they were hurt that I was doing it. Some men
                     object il you sit and embroider in front of them at board meetings.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>PATTY:</speaker>
                  <ab>You can be a total participant. You basically make these decisions and it’s
                     just a matter of moving the needle. It’s not coming from the part of you that
                     you need to listen and speak and think with.</ab>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>ADELE:</speaker>
                  <ab>You spoke about wanting to keep what you do. I know that what I make has
                     really very little value, unless I put it on a good piece of linen, but you
                     can’t compare it with a goldsmith’s work. 1 feel very possessive about what
                     l’ve done and I don’t give it to anyone except people that are very close to
                     me. Organizations say now see how much hand stuff you can bring in for the
                     bazaar or for the auction and we’ll have a big sale . . . I give of myself all
                     the time to the community, but never my needlework. I still have the little
                     crooked tea towel I did at age five because my mother wouldn’t throw it
                     out.</ab>
               </sp>
               <p>Dee Shapiro is a pattern painter uho lives on Long Island. Madge Huntington is a
                  self-taught artist working with fabric collage wall hangings who lives in N.Y.C.
                  with her husband and children.</p>

            </div>
            <div>
               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_085.jpg"
                  n="85" xml:id="img_0085"/>

               <head>REMINISCENCES</head>

               <byline>KATHI NORKLUN</byline>

               <p>My grandmother loved flowers. I remember the garden. There were hydrangea, bouncy
                  and big on their wood stems; violets and lilies-of-the valley that we learned to
                  search out in the shadouy spots inour oun yard and pick for Mothers Day, roses tha
                  grew on crooked, thorny stems with rough, toothy leaves, each one a simple
                  perfection out of which my grandmother picked Japanese beetles, dropping them with
                  their glistening green-and-purple backs into a rusty can of kerosene.</p>
               <p>There was a cherry tree whose fruit we never ate because the birds got there
                  first. Beyond that was the vegetable garden. There grandmother’s flowers found a
                  place, one corner graced with arching stems of bleeding hearts and regal purple
                  irises, The house was big, open and inviting, full of textures and smells and
                  old-fashioned colors. The wallpaper in the foyer had lit- tle pastoral figures
                  repeating themselves in identical landscapes along the stairs. The paint on the
                  ceiling above my bed was old, peeling off in places and resembling in one spot an
                  old hag with a long nose. My room was papered pink and green, my grand- mother’s
                  favorite colors, and had the musty, long-used, faded smell that pervaded the
                  house. My grandmother had a wringer washing machine in the cleaning room off the
                  kitchen. It had its own smell of old clothes and soap, and the clean/rotten smell
                  of potato peelings and other organic leavings that were kept separate from the
                  burnable garbage. On the door she kept an old calendar with the saying, “Oh, Lord,
                  Thy sea is so great and my boat is so small."</p>
               <p>She braided rugs. She bought old wool coats at rummage sales, tore them apart, cut
                  them into strips, folded, stitched and braided them into long coils. One of these
                  rugs was on the floor of the dining room, all dark browns and greens and tweeds.
                  My grandmother kept things. In her sewing room there were always piles of clothes
                  from rummage sales, dresser drawers filled with jewelry, gloves and other fine,
                  delicate things. Knick-knacks were all over the house, and a wonderful eight-day
                  clock under a glass bell sat on the mantle in the living room.</p>
               <p>She wore dark print dresses that came down past her knees, and she looked like I
                  thought all grandmothers looked: solid peasant stock from Eastem Europe, apron
                  tied at her waist, hands gnarled from tending her flowers, smelling wonderfully
                  like her kitchen or the earth in her garden.</p>
               <p>There is a church in the town, and my grandmother often provided flowers for the
                  altar from her garden. I used to tremble when my grandmother, in her goodness,
                  walked right up to the altar and arranged the vases on it. The Church teaches
                  humility and service through its female saints; certainly my grandmother belongs
                  with that long-suffering celestial choir Why are there no flowers on my
                  grandmother’s grave? Since she died, eight years ago, 1 have grown up, and my
                  memories of her have been disturbed by the glimpses my mother has given me of
                  another side of this woman.</p>
               <p>She was very bitter, she was ready to die,” my mother told me. My mother’s own
                  anger distilled into bitterness as she talked about my grandfather’s travels with
                  his new wife. My grandmother had always wanted to travel, but never had. “She
                  would not see the priest who came to visit.</p>
               <p>"She . . . had to lie in the bed she made for herself.” What a cold, cruel thing
                  to say. She had encouraged my grandfather to play the role of a man as she knew
                  it, and he did. He hung around with the boys. They grew apart. When she died, my
                  grand- father married a woman who would be a companion.</p>
               <p>My grandmother was caught in the center of a web of caring she had spun around all
                  of us. I find I never really knew her. No one talks of her, no one reminisces. The
                  family has scattered, the children have grown, the house is no longer the center
                  of a vital network. Weeds have taken over the garden; 1 believe my grandfather has
                  mowed it down.</p>
               <p>Grandmother’s bitterness seems to have come from what she did with her life. Yet
                  for me as a child, she was part of an undifferentiated environment of warmth,
                  comfort and beauty.</p>
               <p>Kathi Norklun is a free-lance writer and art historian living in N.Y.C. She has
                  been working on an exhibition of women's domestic imagery.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>BETTY KLAVUN</head>

               <p> My first clear memory of my mother is of her fishing in hipboots in a northern
                  lake, casting with one of her own flies-gorgeous bugs with fantastic wings which
                  she had tied herself from brightly colored feathers and bits of materials.</p>
               <p>In the late thirties Mother and a group of her friends became interested in
                  stenciling. They researched old designs and redesigned them for application on
                  trays, lamps, chairs, boxes. The stencils were cut from a very hard waxed linen
                  paper so that the edges stayed sharp and clear despite much use. To celebrate my
                  wedding Mother stenciled a design on the walls of our living room. These women
                  worked hard and were very serious about their work. They were middle-class women
                  without aggressive or competitive ambitions in the business world. They didn’t
                  object to working commercially but did so only if asked. One might il- lustrate a
                  child’s book; one might paint greeting cards. Mother even translated children’s
                  books into Braille. Despite the profes sional quality of these women s' work it
                  was primarily for their own pleasure and that of their families. The quilts they
                  designed <pb
                     facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_086.jpg"
                     n="86" xml:id="img_0086"/> and sewed went on their own beds. The rugs they
                  hooked or braided went on their floor. My father, however, brought my mother’s
                  stenciled trays to elegant stores like Hammacher Schlemmer’s to sell with the
                  outdoor furniture which he designed and built after his retirement.</p>
               <p>Most discarded items or worn-out materials were preserved as grist for the
                  household mill. Stockings and clothes were kept for rugmaking or cleaning rags.
                  Broken bottles were for scraping furniture, paper bags for absorbing cooking
                  grease, newspapers for laying fires with one special pleated fan to dress up the
                  kindling. The recycling was continuous. It was part of running a home.</p>
               <p>Mother invented all sorts of gadgets which my brother tried to patent. Every
                  possible drawer in the kitchen cupboards opened into the dining room as well as
                  the kitchen. There was a special holder for soaking brushes upright, a knitting
                  yarn winder and lamps that swung on long arms</p>
               <p>Mother respected and understood the unpredictable in nature. She studied the
                  agricultural information published by the state, learning about crop rotation, and
                  even after we no longer had animals, continued to cultivate the fields for hay.
                  She never quite believed that the flowers she crossed and the trees she grafted
                  would take.</p>
               <p>Mother made a vegetable and berry garden, a flower garden and a rose garden. In
                  the cellar under the carriage barn, she grew mushrooms.</p>
               <p>The planning of all her gardens was quite similar to outdoor environmental
                  sculpture. She never imposed a formal design but used the land as she found it.
                  Rocks were centers for small flowers, “hens and chickens,” succulents and herbs.
                  An existing shrub might be tied into the rest of the garden by more massive clumps
                  of tall plants. The land was planned with appropriate flowers for knolls and
                  valleys, sun and shade. In my memory all the flowers were an exaggerated extension
                  of the wild flowers in the field around them. My sister calls this an
                  old-fashioned garden.</p>
               <p>When we had cows, mother made butter and cottage cheese and buttermilk, the
                  by-product. The milking was done by hand and then came the separating of the milk
                  and the cream. There seemed to be a countless number of discs to the separator.
                  Then came the slow endless turning of the handle of the big wooden churn until the
                  butter suddenly came. Mother also raised bees and for a short time we had our own
                  honey until Mother, who scorned most of the protective bee costume, nearly died of
                  bee sting.</p>
               <p>She took great pleasure in growing vegetables and fruit and canning them. We all
                  gathered berries for her jelly making. She was a champion blueberry picker. She
                  made both elderberry and blackberry wine. We probably had one of the first
                  freezers, a memorable event. Half of our favorite vegetable, peas, instead of
                  being eaten fresh, were frozen.</p>
               <p>Late in life she became excited by the possibilities of reproducing old china
                  designs, pots of her own, and glazing. She enrolled at the Sharon Art Center
                  nearby and eventually had her own kilns and worked at home.</p>
               <p>She was a shy, small woman, prophetic in her time, generously responsive, filled
                  with a natural curiosity and a great love of the earth.</p>
               <p> Betty Klavun is a sculptor interested in doing pieces that involve people.</p>
            </div>
            <div>

               <head>LUCHITA HURTADO</head>
               <p> My family lived in Caracas, Venezuela. Ladies at that time, nervously twirling
                  their rosaries, drove down the perpendicular dangerous road to bathe in the sea.
                  It was believed that the ocean had curative powers. Huge bathhouses stood on the
                  coastline, waves pounding and resounding in their cavernous in- teriors, the dusky
                  air pierced with streaks of sunlight while crabs walked the high ledges and the
                  women and children squealed with delight. It was during a sojourn at the beach, a
                  little over half a century ago, that I was born. Memories of my childhood still
                  invade today’s reality. Padre Peñalber, our parish priest, is at least partly
                  responsible for my lifelong aversion to a certain shade of pink. He was a short
                  stocky man with very bushy eyebrows and a thunderous voice. Cassock swinging, he
                  walked staring at the line of children waiting to hear what the color of their
                  angel dresses would be for the Easter mass At that time dark complexioned children
                  were thought to look best in pink and so 1 would try holding my breath, hoping
                  that perhaps my complexion would change. 1 was invariably unsuccess ful in these
                  attempts for when he looked at me, he would always say, “Pink. You are a pink
                  angel Little girls with papier mache wings strapped to their backs were placed on
                  a scaffold around the altar kneeling on a space hardly larger than a small
                  cushion. I never knew whether 1 had sud- denly grown too tall to be an angel or
                  whether, rebelling against the pink I wore, 1 disrup ted the mass by falling
                  asleep kneeling on one of the higher platforms. Whatever the rea- son, 1 was never
                  again chosen to be an angel at Easter. Being a painter, color has always been a
                  very important part of my life. I go through color periods when anything purple or
                  red or green or blue seems magically endowed, but never ever a certain shade of
                  pink. Venezuelan girls were taught to sew at an early age. They didn’t knit—the
                  tropical climate cancelled out any warm clothing—but they did sew, crochet,
                  embroider and make beautiful lace. I don’t believe 1 ever saw a group of women
                  working together on a common project; rather, they worked alone, even if in a
                  group, spending long hours embroidering a pillow case or making a lace doily.</p>
               <p> My grandmother, Rosario, taught me how to sew. If she caught sight of me sitting
                  under a tree enjoying the afternoon breeze, she would ask me to bring her my
                  favorite dress. “Idle hands tempt the devil,” she would say; then together we
                  would undo the hem. Once done, she would say,“Now, sew it up again and let me see
                  how well you can do it.”It never occurred to me to ask her why it was that when I
                  daydreamed I was tempting the devil, whereas when boys daydreamed they were lost
                  in thought, plan- ning some great project.</p>
               <p> I didn’t like to sew then, and it took me years to discover that it could be a
                  pleasurable experience. When I became pregnant with my first son in New York, I
                  learned to enjoy sewing. In the forties, when he was born, the only maternity
                  clothes available in stores were called “butcher boy” dresses with an ugly hole
                  cut out in the skirt. 1 had a vision of a long, silk, black and white striped
                  dress with a velvet ribbon and red geraniums and promptly began to make it. It
                  took me weeks and because 1 set the sleeves in backward, I had to stand with my
                  shoulders at an odd angle. However, what I remember most is how good I felt when 1
                  finished and wore it. When my son, Daniel, was born, the dress had been so
                  constantly worn that, like the placenta, it was discarded in the process. I went
                  on sewing then whenever I coveted some imagined piece of clothing or visualized my
                  infant son in a red vest with blue satin ribbons. Sewing has afforded me great
                  satisfaction through the years.</p>

               <p>Luchita Hurtado is a painter working in Santa Monica, California. She has four
                  children.</p>
            </div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_087.jpg"
               n="87" xml:id="img_0087"/>

            <div>
               <head>ANN SPERRY</head>
               <p> I was a Scotch lass one fall, a Russian princess the next winter. I had feather
                  or fur-trimmed hats to match every coat and lace- collared, lovingly hand-tucked
                  party dresses. The buttons on my blouses were ceramic fruits or mother-of-pearl
                  hearts; enam- eled flowers closed my sweaters. I was the embodiment of my mother’s
                  fantasies—the outlet for her frustrated talents. Trained in Poland as a fine
                  seamstress, she emigrated to America at 18, took a course at the Traphagen School
                  of Fashion and became a dress designer. My father believed that a wife’s place was
                  in the home, and even though her income would have been a welcome addition to the
                  small salary he earned as a Yiddish poet working for the Yiddish newspapers, she
                  stopped working to take care of their home, and me, their only child.</p>
               <p>She designed and sewed every kind of clothing for the two of us; shirts, ties,
                  jackets, pyjamas and bathrobes for my father; curtains, slipcovers, bedspreads for
                  the house. Her sewing machine in the bedroom was overflowing with projects. Scraps
                  of fabrics and pieces of thread were always on the rugs and floor.</p>
               <p>Sometimes she took me with her to hunt for the fabrics—remnants were all she could
                  afford. We would plow through rolled up bundles of cloth wrapped around the middle
                  with a strip of brown paper. The material would tumble out when you pulled one end
                  of the string that tied it together. We searched through boxes of laces,
                  trimmings, scraps of fur, end pieces of em- broidered ribbons, all scraps that
                  could be bought for a few cents by anyone who could think of a way to use them
                  Usually the remnants were wrapped the wrong side out. It wasn’t until we got home
                  and opened them that we were able to see their full beauty. My mother always knew
                  what treasures she had found. “Look,” she’d say, fondling a piece, “this French
                  silk moire, how it reflects the light; this Italian knit, it must have mohair in
                  it, feel how it moves.</p>
               <p>There was such challenge and excitement when she started making something. Almost
                  always, the pattern called for more yardage than was in the remnant, and she would
                  hover over the fabric on the floor, clouds of pattern pieces surrounding her tape
                  measure draped around her neck, folding and unfolding in every conceivable way
                  until she managed to maneuver the two- and-five-eighths yard remnant to make a
                  three-and-a-half yard skirt. It was magical to me; she could make something out of
                  anything, out of nothing. I could almost see the fabric grow to fit the need. Then
                  she would pick up her enormous shears and begin to cut. (1 once used those shears
                  to cut out some paper doll clothes, and got one of the worst spankings of my
                  childhood—those shears were only for fabric.)</p>
               <p>This past summer I found myself in a junkyard, trying to pull a beautifully
                  patinaed piece of two-inch pipe from under a pile of 1-beams. It was a hot, muggy
                  day. I was going to the beach when I spotted this likely-looking heap of scrap,
                  and felt com- pelled to stop. As I tugged at the pipe, sticky and sweating, trying
                  not to stab my sandaled feet with a sharp rusted iron bar, cursing, I wondered:
                  What in the world am I doing here? Why this need to stop and explore every
                  junkyard? Why is my studio full of scraps of stéel pipe and sheeting and odd iron
                  shapes?</p>
               <p>Ann Sperry's sculpture combines fluid painted steel elements with rusted found
                  objects. She lives in N.Y.C. with her husband and three children.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>FAITH RINGGOLD</head>
               <p> Tremember once when I was about 12 years old I tried to make a pair of sandals
                  and a brassiere from some pink satin scraps of material my mother, Willi Posey,
                  had given me. She was the first person to teach me to sew as her mother, Ida, had
                  taught her. The tradition of teaching and sewing in our family probably goes back
                  to our roots in Africa. My mother remembers watching her grandmother, Betsy
                  Bingham, boil and bleach flour sacks until they were “white as snow” to line the
                  quilts she made. Mother also remembers Betsy cutting out basket shapes, triangles
                  and circles out of brightly colored scraps of material to create the design of the
                  quilt.</p>
               <p>Susie Shannon, Betsy’s mother, had taught her to sew quilts. She was a slave and
                  had made quilts for the plantation owners as part of her duties as “house girl.”
                  Undoubtedly many of the early American quilts with repetitive geometric designs
                  are slave- made and African-influenced.</p>
               <p>Ida, my grandmother, made clothes for a living when she came north from
                  Jacksonville, Florida, after her husband died in 1910. He had been a teaching
                  principal setting up schools in Florida and South Carolina, moving frequently to
                  the next place that needed him and could pay for his services. Ida taught with him
                  in the South, but up North there was no job for her and she still had two young
                  children to support.</p>
               <p>My mother made our clothes, and sewed for friends free during the depression
                  years. She created original designs and made and cut her own patterns. By the
                  forties, no longer a housewife, she was making a living sewing and giving seasonal
                  fashion shows of her designs. Many are high fashion today, such as the bat-wing
                  sleeves and knee-length pants.</p>
               <p>My mother was always an artist, but she thinks of herself as a business woman, and
                  measures her success by the number of steady customers she designs for during each
                  season. Today she is in her seventies and her five or six steady customers keep
                  hei in business wearing “Posey” originals.</p>
               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_088.jpg"
                  n="88" xml:id="img_0088"/>
               <p>Faith Ringgold, artist, teacher, writer, is currently completing an autobiography
                  and lecturing and exhibiting nationally.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>HELENE AYLON</head>
               <p> I just came across this photo of my mother in-law, Celia, now dead. She had nine
                  children and lived in utter poverty in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. Her husband worked
                  in a sweatshop and studied the Torah.</p>
               <p>Celia’s art was “making do,” patching up, stretching the dollar. She boasted that
                  the only thing she threw out were egg- shells—“and to begin with, the eggs can be
                  bought cracked for next to nothing.” She knew of a place to buy stale bread which
                  was “better for you than fresh bread.” She’d cut up old telephone books into
                  six-inch squares and use this for toilet paper. Once she came to my house and
                  stared at the soapy water gushing out of the washing machine into the sink. With
                  the speed of lighten- ing, she was triumphantly caught the water in a pail, so
                  that it could be used for washing the floor.</p>
               <p>Now that I think of it, there was one extravagance: the small bouquet of fresh
                  flowers that traditionally enhanced her “Sab- bath Table." This she would arrange
                  and rearrange.</p>
               <p>Helene Aylon is a Neu York painter uho left to live in Berkeley, California, four
                  years ago. She shous at the Betty Parsons Gallery in Neu York and feels that the
                  Art World is a better place since feminism.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>JOYCE AIKEN</head>
               <p>Many of my childhood memories center around the women of the family and their
                  work. Both my mother’s and father’s parents lived 25 miles from us in a small
                  farming community and we visited them each Sunday. My maternal grandmother lived
                  on a ranch that grew grapes and peaches. My twin sister Janice and I never looked
                  forward to those Sunday trips, but our boredom was relieved when Grandma was
                  making a quilt. We would quilt while the men went outside to smoke or sit under
                  the umbrella tree. Sometimes the quilting frame staved up for weeks and no one
                  thought it strange that it took up most of the living room. The depression had
                  brough renewed interest in many kinds of needlework because of the poor money
                  situation and the need to use spare time profitably. The women’s magazines were
                  filled with needlework patterns for embellishing dresses, towels and table linens.
                  Neither my mother nor my grandmother could read a crochet pattern, but both could
                  easily work from a piece already made. With friends they formed a women’s group in
                  the early 1930s to trade new ideas for crochet projects or stitches. In 1934 after
                  we moved to a new town Mother went to the Methodist Church once a week to make
                  quilts for the missionairies She would take us along and we would play on the
                  floor around the “sewing ladies.” Within a few years this group would be sewing
                  for the Red Cross and the war effort. Twenty-five years earlier my mother had
                  learned to knit for the service men during World War I.</p>
               <p>My father’s mother, Emma Braun, was a rugmaker who had learned her craft as a
                  child in Canada. There was a small room in her house that held her rug frame,
                  fabric scraps and burlap. She was constantly searching for good burlap sacks and
                  wool <pb
                     facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_089.jpg"
                     n="89" xml:id="img_0089"/> clothing from the Salvation Army stores. When wool
                  was hard to find, she dyed cotton sheet blankets for rug strips. She de signed her
                  own patterns and carefully drew them on the burlap before starting to hook. 1 was
                  about 11 years old and visiting her in the summer when she taught me the process
                  of washing and preparing the rags, stretching and sewing the burlap to the frame,
                  and doing the hooking. Rugmaking is a solitary craft and Emma Braun was a very
                  private person. She said that when other women went to quilting bees, she
                  preferred to stay home and spend part of each day working on a rug. She hooked
                  about 40 rugs in her lifetime, the largest one, 8’ x 10’. The last rug I remember
                  her making was made for me when she was 82.</p>
               <p>There are few days in my life when I am not involved with some kind of handwork.
                  My mother and I talked about it recently and discovered we were both filled with
                  guilt if there was spare time available and we had no “projects” to work on. She
                  thought it was our nature to be that way. I think it is because neither of us ever
                  saw our mothers idle.</p>
               <p>Joyce Aiken is a Professor at California State University at Fresno in crafts and
                  feminist art. She has published a number of crafts books and works in fabric and
                  wood.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>PAULA KING</head>
               <p>I am an ex-mother, ex-housewife who grew up in a home where evidence of my
                  creative heritage was displayed on every bed. My mother never completed a quilt
                  herself—they were all given to her by women relatives for her wedding- but she
                  sewed all our clothes, made curtains, slipcovered couches and insisted that my
                  sister and 1 learn to sew well. When I was married at 18, she gave me a sewing
                  machine. During my ten years of marriage, my need to be creative was suppressed,
                  except for decorating the house, making things for the kids, conquering new
                  recipes. Following my two marriages I spent five years in the heterosexual Left at
                  a time when both feminism and art, of any but the most bla- tantly political kind,
                  were condemned as a bourgeois self-in- dulgence. It wasn’t until I stopped doing
                  political work with men and began to identify with the women’s community that 1
                  felt supported enough to deal with my own creative needs. The fact that
                  quiltmaking skills have become a focus for me is tied up with my former
                  identification as a homemaker and with my self-image as a nonartist. Although I am
                  now a lesbian and no longer have any but minimal duties as a mother, the home and
                  all the roles connected to it are still po tent material for me. It is with women
                  in those roles that 1 mainly think of sharing my work.</p>
               <p>I have been doing stitchery for three years now. 1 restrict- ed myself to using a
                  needle, thimble and a hoop and set out to experience how it was that women had
                  sewn for most of thei creative history. I began to understand that both the form
                  and the content might have political meaning, and that the very act of making
                  stitchery in a way that was respectful of tradition could be a celebration of the
                  creative spirit of gener- ations of women who have never been considered artists.
                  This last year most of my energy has gone into developing stitchery as a political
                  art form. I am not at all interested in having stitchery elevated to its rightful
                  place among the arts. That would make it susceptible to male standards of criti-
                  cism, and stitchery, at least at the amateur level, is one of the few crafts still
                  controlled by women</p>
               <p> Because stitchery is not defined as art and because many women have some
                  knowledge of the skills involved, it is no as intimidating as other art forms.</p>

               <p>Paula King is currently employed by Rape Relief Hotline in Portland, Oregon. She
                  is involved in organizing around the issue of violence against women, and—along
                  with 95 others- vus pus aeguiltesd oi oriminal vespan at die Puigen Miusbear Pouer
                  Plant.</p>
            </div>


            <div>
               <head>DEBORAH JONES-DOMINGUEZ</head>
               <p>When I found a beautiful quilt in my aunt's closet recently I remembered a little
                  Bo-Pep quilt I had had as a child and the stories told to me by my father about
                  his family</p>

               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_090.jpg"
                  n="90" xml:id="img_0090"/>
               <p> During the second hall of the nineteenth century, his materal grandmother and her
                  sisters came to Amprica from the British Isles. They brought with hem the lore of
                  quiltmaking. Orphans, they had learned needlework from the women in charge of the
                  households in whih they were raised. These women's lives were practical and
                  unadorned. They lived in rural communities, and during the long winter months
                  mobility outside the home was curtailed. The men, railroaders and coal miners,
                  were gone from the home for long periods, leaving the women time to work at
                  quilting in the evehnings after their chores. From their elders the young girls
                  learned stitching and other "womanly" skills. Their abilties were increased by
                  working very young in factories producing needlework.</p>
               <p>The proces of quiltmaking began with a metal template for shapes to be used in the
                  designs. From this template a dozen cardboard copies were made of each shape. The
                  cloth was then pinned to the cardboard and cut around its perimeter. The women
                  were able to cut these small shapes quickly and precisely from whatever goods were
                  on hand, such as ginghams and calicoes. In piecework the cloth shapes were
                  laboriously sewn together a piece at a time, joining the units from the center
                  outward. The components of many quilts were worked on at the same time and were
                  stacked, ready for use. In designing the quilts the women were self-sufficient;
                  the home magazines that published quilt designs were seldom used. When the women
                  were not pleased with theeir work, they stripped the threads out and cut the cloth
                  to use it as another shape in a different design. They continuously rearranged
                  colors in the designs or made variations on shapes to create their own unique
                  patterns. Once they established what was best for that particular "block" or
                  circle they took care that the symmetry and séwing were precise; there was nothing
                  ever left over.</p>
               <p>Appliqué differed from piecework; the units were hemmed to one another piece of
                  cloth, which served as a base to form a design, instead of being pieced together.
                  All the raw ends of cloth were turned under and sewn around the edge with small,
                  invisible stitches. Often the symmetry of the appliqued design was stitched into
                  the quilted background. When they gathered around the table to work together, the
                  women sometimes joked about friends whose stitching was coarse.</p>
               <p>When the clans came together for quilting bees, many of the women brought
                  unfinished quilts already cut and assembled. It was a time for catching up on all
                  the family news. During the bees they applied the units the the base. They knew
                  the overall plan and moved easily through the process. Then there were two long
                  poles about two feet apart stretched eight feet in length across the old-fashioned
                  dining room. They were unwrapped from one end to the other with the quilt. As one
                  pole wrapped, the oher unwrapped in of it, traveling in tandem as the work
                  progressed. Four women workeg along each side of the quilt while an additional two
                  worked on the borders.</p>
               <p>Women studied their friends', neighbors' and relatives' stitching and designs.
                  They copied from each other and each was proud when she created something unique.
                  Cloth was traded among friends from as far away as 30 miles. This compensated for
                  the sameness that existed in a neighborhood in which there was heavy trading.
                  People went out on their swings in the evenings, sauntering around the
                  neighborhood exchanging pleasantries and inviting friends in to "see my quilts."
                  The quilts, carried around on family visits for display, kept the tradition alive.
                  Sometimes one would hear stories about very old and valuable quilts, made of
                  cotton with cotton seeds still in the fiber. This was not seen as a sign of
                  imperfection but age; old quilts were more valuable because the cotton used was
                  not refined by cotton ginning.</p>
               <p>Deborah Jones Dominguez is a painter and teacher uho lives and vorks in NY.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>MIMI SMITH</head>
               <p> Photographic arrangements by Sarah Lyman Bayard</p>
               <p> Sarah Lyman Bayard, my grandmother, lived to be 34. She had no formal education.
                  As a young girlshe boarded a ship alone and sailed from her village, her parents
                  and ten brothers and sisters to America. Her entire life was sent doing work with
                  her hands. She had no concept of what I call art, and the only time I ever heard
                  her mention the word was shortly before she died. She told me that upon arriving
                  in this country she had worked as a stitcher in a sweatshop. After her children
                  were born she earned money by sewing piecework at home. She would spend many, many
                  hours making men’s suits. “When I finished a man’s suit it was a work of art."</p>
               <p>During the last seven years of her life she moved all of her belongings into a
                  room in my parents’ house. Her most prized possessions were her pictures. They
                  covered two pieces of furniture in her small room. She had certain systems for
                  arranging the pictures. Some were pinned to each other in rows with straight pins,
                  others were just piled or leaning against each other in groups. The arrangements
                  and displays were constantly changing. Guests were always invited to see the
                  changing exhibitions. She was always seeking newer pictures. She told me that she
                  had never had her own life and that all of the people in the pictures had been her
                  life. She said that dusting and hanging the pictures were now her work. She died
                  in 1975. This photo was taken a few days after her death.</p>
               <p>Mimi Smith is an artist who lives in N.Y.C.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
