<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_109.jpg" n="109" xml:id="img_0109"/>
            
               <head><title>Embroidery from the Northwest</title></head>
               <byline>Zette Emmons</byline>
               <p>In the 700,000 villages of India, the peasant woman is born into a set of prescribed rituals which she is responsible for maintaining and
               transmitting. Traditional art is one form these rituals take; in Northwestern India, an area historically rich in all kinds of textiles, peasant
               women embroider. A classification of textiles made in India for domestic use includes “skilled work of weavers and dyers, who work close to
               large market towns; articles of luxury made under court patronage or in the court tradition; folk embroidery; and fabrics of the aborigina
               tribes.”* The first two forms of production are dominated by male weavers and craftsmen working in a commercial structure. The fourth is
               outside the mainstream of Indian village life, though folk embroidery draws upon many aboriginal antecedents which have become tangled
               with Islamic and Hindu influences.</p>
               <p>The depth of religious feeling and devotion that permeates Indian village life does not exist in the West in any comparable way, and it is fron
               this regard for the deities that the impulse to create something beautiful and worthy seems to come. Outer and inner worlds are merged in a
               relationship kept flowing and harmonious by the constant application of visible symbols and signs. Everything is part of everything else; there
               is none of the “disconnectedness” that is so much a part of life in the West. When the woman embroiders, she is conscious of the decorativenes
               of what she does, but she also has the satisfaction of honoring the world of the spirits residing in the plants and animals which she imitates in
               thread. Even the poorest village woman is capable of making her life more bearable and secure by the application of decoration to her house on
               herself. A Krishna proverb which applies to village women at work is—“I take the form desired by my worshippers.”2
               Women wear blouses, full skirts and shawls, all heavily embroidered. They spend their spare time embroidering not only their own clothing
               or trousseaus for their daughters, but also natis (children s headdresses), toranas (wall hangings), animal trappings and small bags for carrying
               jewelry and other small items. To wear someone else’s clothing would be unthinkable. When the wearer dies or when a garment is worn out,
               the old garment is cast off.</p>
               <p>Patterns to be embroidered are drawn onto cloth, which is worked in flat sections and sewn together when finished. Chain, cross and but-
               tonhole stitches cover the surface with patterns; satin stitching fills large areas with color. Small mirrors or pieces of mica are used extensively,
               interspersed fancifully with the embroidery. Mirrors also decorate walls, furniture and even chicken coops. They are not only attractive.
               flashing in the sun, but also frighten away demons.
               In the designs of peasant women in all parts of India, the essences of the animals, flowers and gods are revealed, emphasized by repetition.
               Dots, triangles and lines are arranged in panels surrounding abstracted symbols and objects. Even buses, bicycles and airplanes may be incor-
               porated into the work. The sense of color is more pronounced in the Northwest than in any other part of India. Traditional dyes have been
               derived from indigo, cochineal (red made from crushed insect bodies), iron filings (black), saffron and various other plants yielding yellows and
               oranges. Pupul Jayaker of the All-India Handicrafts Board describes the emotional content for peasant women of the colors they use.</p>
               <quote>Red was the color of Chunari, a tie-dyed sari, and was the symbol of sohog, the first days of marriage and love-play. It was
               the garment worn by the Abhisarika, the young woman seeking in the darkness of night her waiting beloved. Saffron or
               gerua was the color of Vasant, of spring, of young mango blossoms, of swarms of bees, of southern winds and the passionate
               cry of mating birds. Maroon and black were the colors of mourning. Blue or nil, the color of indigo, was also the color of
               Krishna, the cowherd child-god who bore the name of Navjaldhar—he who is of that color, that of the newly formed cloud,
               dormant with the darkness that is rain. But there was another blue, Hari nil, or the color of water which is reflecting a clear
               spring sky.</quote>
               <p>Daughters learn embroidery from their mothers who teach not only the techniques but the mythology that provides much of the subject mat
               ter for their images. Styles in the village gradually change according to the inclination of successive generations of artists and the impact of
               cultures. Islamic influence is seen in the geometric mazes and flower patterns; the bright colors and looser flowing lines are Hindu in origin.
               In the twentieth century industrialization has made inroads on every Indian village, no matter how remote. The survival of women’s arts,
               especially embroidery is being threatened by the adoption of bright, mill-made cloth. Synthetic dyes have largely replaced traditional ones. Im-
               itation printed or machine-sewn embroidery also appears now in place of the real thing. In recognition of this the All-India Handicrafts Board
               has provided incentives for maintaining quality by turning some previously noncommercial arts into quality-controlled commodities. This
               often has the opposite effect of the one intended, because the spark of life may go out of work produced for an unknown market whose needs
               are irrelevant to the rural craftsperson. Gandhi believed that it was possible and desirable for India to return to a village-centered economy in
               which the machine would be relegated to a minor role and the villager dictate the pace of life. Although his ideas are out of favor in present-day
               India, there is still a sentimental longing for that kind of simplicity in which the drive to create and survive comes out of the soil. The peasant
               woman holds on to the old ways for the time being, but there is no doubt that even she will become a victim, willing or not, of the changes that
               have afflicted the West since the industrial revolution.</p>
               <p>'John Irwin, Textiles and Ornaments of India (New York: The Museum of Modern Art, 1956), p. :
               Anand, Mulk Raj, “The Hand and the Heart,” MARG (Bombay: Marg Publications, 1969), p. 6.
               Irwin, p. 20.</p>
            <p>
               Zete Emmons vas born in San Francisco and studied at the University of California at Berkeley. She spent 1971-1972 in India documenting folk art on a grant from Berkeley and
               presently lives in Kingston, R.I</p>
</div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
