<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
                   <div> 
         <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_051.jpg" n="51" xml:id="img_0051"/>
            
               <head><title>Trapped Women: Two Sister Designers Margaret and Frances MacDonald</title></head>
                      <byline>Josephine Gear</byline>
            <p>
               The large, white, airy and austere room
               with its severely elegant chairs and tables
               and attenuated, weeping ladies transfixed in
               pale olive or light mauve-colored gesso
               panels around its walls, is now full. Te-
               cups chink against saucers, silk-clad wrist.
               are held at a delicate angle, feather-plumed
               hats bob up and down, white lawn and lace
               covered bosoms heave sighs of contentment
               cheeks flush, tongues loosen, and the buzz
               of women s talk rises a quaver or two above
               the level thought acceptable if this room, a
               tearoom, had been found in London. But
               the like of this room, and others designed by
               Charles Rennie Mackintosh, architect, and
               his wife, Margaret Macdonald, a decorative
               designer, was not to be found in London noi
               in any other smart city in turn-of-the
               century Britain, but in Glasgow, dirty, ro-
               bust, tough and far-from-genteel Glasgow
               the industrial capital of Scotland.</p>
               <p>In the late 1890s in the heart of this city's
               sober business district a few strikingly dif
               ferent and simple tearoom facades ap-
               peared. Their exteriors, interiors, furniture
               and fittings displayed unconventional solu-
               tions, ethereal elegance and flights of im-
               aginative thinking not seen before in the arts
               of this city. Glasgow was in the throes of an
               artistic renewal.</p>
            <p>
               Margaret Macdonald (1865-1933), who
               contributed designs to the tearooms, and
               her sister Frances Macdonald (1874-1921
               were two of a number of women artists who.
               for a short while, helped make the arts alive
               in Glasgow. What follows is a brief account
               of their lives, set against the background of
               Glasgow, and a discussion of a few of the
               objects the sisters designed and made.</p>
               <p>The liveliness of the arts in this industrial
               capital (Europe’s sixth largest city) grew in
               part from its sound economic base. In the
               previous half-century the heavy industries of
               the area, mining and shipbuilding for ex-
               ample, enjoyed boom growth.' And some of
               the profits, often via the increased income
               and leisure time of Glasgow’s upper ancd
               middle classes, found their way into the sup-
               port and patronage of local arts. How pleas-
               ant to sit in a new tearoom designed by Scot-
               tish artists of national prominence, with
               works by local and internationally known
               painters hung about on the walls, to sit there
               and eat a quick lunch or to linger leisurel,
               over afternoon tea. How very natural to
               stroll from the tearoom, seek out the
               painters or the craftsmen or women in near
               by studios, chat with them about their work
               and sometimes, proudly, bear home a paint
               ing, a watercolor, or even a beaten metal
               panel by one of the Macdonald sisters.
               In those days it was safe to bet your last
               brass farthing that any artist whose work
               turned your head had been a student at the
               Glasgow School of Art. Founded in 1840
               the school grew out of the firm convictior
               that well-trained artists and designers could
               promote both the nation’s esteem and trade.
               Its founders had both insight and acumen.
               Under the bustling leadership of the school's
               young headmaster, Francis Newbery, and
               his wife, Jessie, students in the 1880s and
               1890s received excellent training and
               energetic promotion.2 Newbery’s students
               were also fortunate in that their emerging
               maturity and talents coincided with their
               city’s peak industrial, intellectual and ar
               tistic growth.</p>
               <p>Francis and Jessie Newbery fostered the
               talents of four students in particular: the
               Macdonald sisters and two young men
               Charles Rennie Mackintosh and Herbert
               MacNair, interior and furniture designers.
               The sisters were day students and the men
               were evening students; Newbery, in a cri-
               tique of their works, told the four about the
               similarity of their styles, and suggested they
               meet.” In about 1895 the sisters and their
               two friends formed a group, calling them
               selves simply “The Four."</p>
            
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_052.jpg" n="52" xml:id="img_0052"/>
           
            <p>
               Before they met Charles and Herbert, the
               sisters had already established themselves as
               designers and craftswomen, showing great
               versatility in the range of objects they made
               and the materials with which they worked:
               embroidered hangings and covers, gesso
               panels, leaded glass panels, clocks, posters,
               water colors, book illustrations, and their
               specialty, repoussé metal panels. Margaret
               and Frances Macdonald worked well as a
               team. Not only did they cooperate on ideas
               and drawing, but they often bent over the
               same metal panel to work side by side. They
               enjoyed life. They shared a studio and held
               salons for all the leading writers and artists
               of Glasgow. The sisters were more than able
               to hold their own. During the short years of
               “The Four’s” life, from about 1895 to 1899,
               the two women continued to work very
               closely together. “The Four” exhibited to
               gether and exchanged ideas and designs.</p>
               <p>The men, for example, designed furniture in
               which the sisters’ decorative gesso panels
               were inset. The sisters evidently found the
               collective working arrangement to their ad-
               vantage: during these years they produced
               their most original and vigorous designs.
               In 1899 Frances married MacNair and
               the two moved to Liverpool where he had a
               teaching post. The next year Margaret mar-
               ried Mackintosh. The MacNairs’ move to
               Liverpool brought the sisters’ working ar
               rangement and the collaboration of “The
               Four” to an end. After 1899, the four artists
               produced independently or collaborated
               with their marriage partner on design pro
               jects. Although groups of artists were quite
               common in those decades (members of the
               various small English arts and crafts organ-
               izations around William Morris, Arthur
               Mackmurdo and Walter Crane worked anc
               exhibited together), no two artists during
               this period seemed to work and live in such
               close harmony as the two sisters. Their life
               and work together in the Glasgow studic
               gave a certain intensity to their work, an in-
               tensity which was lost after they separated
               in 1899.</p>
               <p>The strand of another independent,
               spirited and middle-class woman, Catherine
               Cranston, is yet to be woven into the story
               Catherine became a principal patron of
               Charles and Margaret Macdonald.“ As the
               creator and owner of the tearooms she com
               missioned husband and wife to design the
               rooms’ every aspect, from their structure
               and decoration to designs for posters and
               menu cards. In the tearooms the arts and
               crafts mingled freely and complemented
               each other.</p>
            
            <p>
               Better yet, Catherine Cranston’s women
               customers found the environment suppor-
               tive. The tearooms created a social phenom-
               enon by becoming “virtually the first places
               of their kind where even the richest and
               most elegant of Edwardian female society
               might properly meet without chaperons.”5
               Unlike the tearoom clientele, Margaret
               and Frances lived free from the shadows of
               chaperons. By the standards of their day
               they were liberated. Details of their lives
               before marriage are poorly documented, so
               it is difficult to locate the source of their in-
               dependence. Since independence and crea-
               tivity are so strongly linked, however, and of
               great interest in the biographies of women
               artists, I shall undertake a reconstruction of
               their early lives.</p>
               <p>In the late 1880s Margaret and Frances
               Macdonald returned from England with
               their father. It is probable that the sisters
               raised in England, at first felt foreign in
               Glasgow. Events that uproot or bring great
               changes to lives are often those encouraging
               a sense of self and a desire to do something
               with one’s life. Possibly the move to Glas
               gow acted as a stimulus to the sisters. At any
               rate, Margaret and Frances knew who they
               were, knew what they wanted to do and,
               soon after their arrival in Glasgow, first</p>
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_053.jpg" n="53" xml:id="img_0053"/>
            
            <p>
               Margaret, then Frances entered the School
               of Art.</p>
               <p>Once in the school, the sisters found sup-
               port for their ideas in the presence of other
               like-minded women, such as Jessie Newbery
               and their contemporaries, Jessie King,
               craftswoman and book illustrator, and Jane
               Fonie, an interior designer. A tradition of
               active women had been established at the
               school in 1882 when a group of former
               students founded the Glasgow Society of
               Lady Artists’ Club, the oldest women’s club
               in Britain."</p>
               <p>The sisters acquired backbone at the
               school. They were trained in drawing from
               the model, drawing freehand, anatomical
               and botanical drawing, as well as ornamen-
               tal design. The school encouraged them to
               develop their own distinctive styles at an
               early stage. Soon their unrefined and un-
               tamed energies led to bizarre shapes, to
               angular and cutting edges to their female
               forms.</p>
               <p>Shortly after leaving the school the sisters
               reputations traveled as far as London. In
               1896, the London Arts and Crafts Exhibi-
               tion Society invited “The Four” to send fur-
               niture, craftwork and posters in the mod-
               ern style” to that year’s exhibition. The sis-
               ters sent four pieces, two of which they had
               worked on together: a clock of beaten silver
               with beaten brass weights and an aluminum
               pendulum, a muffin stand, a beaten alumi-
               num panel, The Star of Bethlehem, by
               Francis and The Annunciation by
               Margaret.</p>
               <p>The themes of these early figurative piec-
               es express the sisters two constant icon-
               ographic interests, women and babies. Fre-
               quently the woman/ Virgin appears trapped
               and isolated within their work. And, though
               Christian subject matter did not recur as
               often in the later pieces, apparently the in-
               tensity of their religious convictions never
               dimmed. What a pagan and savage inter-
               pretation they gave to their Virgin and Child
               images. London eyes boggled.</p>
               <p>In the mid-1890s the English arts and
               crafts movement was dominated by William
               Morris’s most faithful disciple, Walter               
               Crane. His designs pleased everyone, but
               then they were too innocuous to do other-
               wise. The polite London art crowd moving
               from a Crane to a Macdonald cried out,
               The Spook School!"8</p>
               <p>We can see why. Look at a mirror frame
               (Figure 5) made by Frances in 1896-1897.
               Two excruciatingly thin female figures with
               ghoulish eyes point accusingly at each other
               over the seed cases of the Honesty plant.
               The seed pods look like death’s heads. And
               how spooky is the round copper sconce
               made by both sisters in 1896-1897 (Figure
               1). Imagine it nailed to the wall of a dark-
               ened room and lit by the fluttering light of
               candles in its holders. Visualize how the eyes
               in the round copper plate, and in its sup-
               ports, might enlarge and shrink in the jump-
               ing shadows of candlelight. Now look at the
               two female figures, with scraggy, flattened
               forms and hanging breasts imprisoned with-
               in the rectangular panels of a pair of beaten
               brass candle sconces (Figures 2 and 3),
               designed by the two sisters in the same
               years. Strange details give the figures in
               these sconces an apocryphal air: attached to
               one figure is an orb, supporting a baby
               suckling at the breast; on the other a cres-
               cent moon superimposes its cruel edges and,
               in the outspread hands of the same figure,
               vivid marks, more like stigmata than wrin-
               kles, are slashed in the open palms. The air
               of suffering and martyrdom in these figures
               is so marked that I find myself speculating
               whether the sisters, consciously or uncon-
               sciously, made associations between these
               two female figures and the sacrificial roles
               lived out by the majority of women they
               knew. But not themselves; at this point they
               were still free.</p>
               <p>The sisters might have felt dashed by the
               epithet “The Spook School” since the Arts
               and Crafts Exhibition Society never asked
               them or “The Four” to exhibit again. How-
               ever, Gleeson White, editor of the influen-
               tial arts magazine The Studio, responded
               enthusiastically to the originality of their
               designs and visited Glasgow to find out
               more about the arts and crafts movement
               there. After his visit, The Studio published
               a two-part article on the Glasgow artists
               with part one almost entirely devoted to the
               Macdonald sisters’ works.9</p>
               <p>Gleeson White was impressed that the
               sisters not only designed all the pieces he
               saw but, apart from some joinery work, they
               handled, beat and wrought even the large
               and heavy pieces themselves, including two
               floor-standing clocks. Neither sister was
               covetous of her individual contribution to
               the pieces they jointly designed and execut-
               ed. They refused to be drawn into games of
               identification.</p>
               <p>After looking at their early emaciated
               figures, the inflated look the sisters’ works
               acquire in the early 1900s comes as a sur-
               prise. Reproduced here is a panel Margaret
               designed in colored plaster for the Rose
               Boudoir (Figure 6), shown at the Interna-
               tional Exhibition, Turin, 1902. Some of
               Frances’s figures acquire a similar full-
               blown look in these years. In the early 1900s
               the sisters changed their models; the in-
               fluence of Japanese prints and works by the
               pre-Raphaelites superseded the earlier
               sources of Celtic art, Aubrey Beardsley and
               Jan Toorop.1° In the 1900s an inventive note
               appeared in Margaret’s use of junk mater-
               ials: colored glass, rope and plaster. The
               materials cost little and gave a rich, jeweled
               effect. But the rawness, the evil, the spirits
               that had made their early metal pieces fairly
               rattle, had gone. No amount of fancy cur-
               vilinear lines or innovative mixing of media
               could atone for this. Do success and mar-
               riage account for this transformation of the
               sisters works?</p>
               <p>No matter the causes, each new develop-
               ment the sisters and their husbands brought
               forth was eagerly seized upon by their au-
               dience on the Continent. In 1900 they were
               invited to furnish and decorate an entire
               room at the eighth Secessionist Exhibition in
               Vienna. In 1902, along with other Glasgow
               artists, they exhibited works in the Scottish
               section of the International Exhibition of
               Decorative Art in Turin. Everything the
               four artists sent to the two exhibitions sold.
               Between 1899 and 1905, articles, reviews
               and illustrations of their works appeared</p>
            
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_054.jpg" n="54" xml:id="img_0054"/>
            
            <p>
               frequently in influential journals such as
               Dekorative Kunst and Deutsche Kunst und
               Dekoration; Ver Sacrum, the official publi-
               cation of the Vienna Secession, devoted an
               issue to them.</p>
               <p>Suddenly, in 1905, curiosity about the
               four artists declined on the Continent. Even
               in Scotland the number of commissions
               began to drop; England never revived the
               brief interest it had displayed in 1896.
               Though Charles and Margaret had a highly
               successful exhibition in St. Petersburg in
               1913, where everything but the carpet sold,
               and though one other show was planned for
               Paris in 1914, the successes of their first
               heady decade were never repeated.</p>
               <p>It becomes impossible to find published
               reproductions of the sisters works after
               1905. One of the last I found is a gesso panel
               made by Margaret in 1905 (Figure 4). Un-
               deniably, this is the most powerfully model-
               ed piece yet seen, but the subject shows a
               dangerous stagnation. It is no more than a
               summation of themes explored earlier by the
               sisters. For whom were those plaster tears
               meant to fall? Catherine Cranston's
               tearoom clientele? Or Margaret and her
               sister? Did Margaret begin to feel she was
               cast in a mold much as her rope and glass
               ladies? Did she mourn her lost independ-
               ence? Were her spirits and her creativity
               slipping away? I believe so, and I am sad-
               dened.</p>
               <p>I am against passive readings of history.
               People, their deeds, as well as those they
               avoided doing, affect us mightily. The Mac-
               donald sisters capitulated.1 They allowed
               their strident voices of the 1890s to fade into
               soothing murmurs and echoes of what once
               they were. How dared they! (They make it
               harder for us to shape ourselves into the
               creative and independent beings we would
               like to be. We need all the positive models
               we can get our hands on, and here are two
               more negative ones.)</p>
               <p>Did this change in their art reflect the
               constraints of their times? Yes. It was dif-
               ficult for women in turn-of-the-century
               Glasgow to train and practice as architects,
               as the Macdonalds’ husbands did. Both sisters would have benefited from the training
               and practice of this profession. The status of
               crafts, despite the sincere activities of
               William Morris who tried to unite the arts
               and the crafts (and all the activities and or-
               ganizations that this engendered) remained
               very much a poor relative of their rich aunt.
               Fine Art. Margaret and Frances worked at
               their drawing boards and hammered out
               their metal panels. They probably wondered
               what the studio people were up to. Fine art-
               ists (among them women) painted decadent
               images of women—think of Beardsley’s art.
               Could Margaret and Frances humbly work-
               ing in the lower echelons of the crafts not
               pick up those cues? As craftswomen work-
               ing in a stratified society, it might not have
               occurred to them to push their early in-
               dependent spirits farther than they did..</p>
               <p>The Macdonald sisters’ best years were
               all too short. Their career spanned the per-
               iod of the realliance between the arts and
               the crafts and its subsequent deterioration.
               Neither Glasgow’s renaissance of the arts
               nor women’s independence survived two de-
               cades. The cycles of local movements were
               taken up within the larger motions grinding
               inside the machinery of Western capitalist
               society in the years preceding World War I.
               When the confidence, energy and profits of
               the middle and upper classes decreased in
               those years, the effect was soon seen in the
               arts. In the depression of the 1930s, one of
               the last of Glasgow s tearooms, 12 its wood,
               brick, colored glass, rope, pale mauve and
               green gesso ladies, crumbled under the
               hammers of demolition workers.</p>
            <p>
               1 The first five cities were London,
               Paris, Berlin, Vienna and St. Petersburg.
               Glasgow’s other heavy industries were engi-
               neering, textiles, chemicals, printing and
               papermaking. C.A. Oakley, The Second Ci-
               ty (Glasgow and London: Blackie, 1975).</p>
               <p>2 In 1895, at the request of L’Oeuvre Ar-
               tistique, Francis Newbery sent three cases
               of his students work to the Arts and Crafts
               Exhibition in Liege. T. Howarth, Charles
               Rennie Mackintosh and the Modern Move-
               ment (London: Routledge and Kaegan Paul </p>
            <p>
               
               3 Information told to Howarth by Her-
               bert MacNair, p. 25.</p>
               <p>4 Her brother, Stuart Cranston, was al-
               so in the tearoom business. Catherine Cran-
               ston appears to have been the important pa-
               tron of Mackintosh and Macdonald. The
               tearooms’ busiest hours were 11:00 to noon,
               4:00 to 5:00 p.m. Smoke-rooms were set
               aside for the men. Margaret Macdonald’s
               contributions to the tearooms were not as
               important as her husband’s were. There-
               fore, the tearooms are not discussed further.
               See Howarth on Mackintosh’s tearoom de-
               signs.</p>
               <p>5. H. Jefferson Barnes, Furniture by
               Charles Rennie Mackintosh, (Glasgow:
               Glasgow School of Art, 1969).</p>
               <p>6 The Glasgow Boys, Part Two: The
               History of the Group and Illustrations (Ed-
               inburgh: The Scottish Arts Council, 1971),
               p. 77.</p>
              <p> 7 Catalogue of the Fifth Exhibition,
               1896 (London: Arts and Crafts Exhibition
               Society, 1896), exhibit nos: 285, 475, 508,</p>
               <p>8 The sisters’ work was reviewed in The
               Studio, IX, December, 1896, pp. 202-203.</p>
              <p> 9 The Studio, XI, July, 1897, pp. 86-100.</p>
               <p>10 Ford Madox Brown’s Take Your Son
               Sir, 1856-1857, Tate Gallery, is the source
               of compositional inspiration for Margaret’s
               piece, as R. Schmultzer, Art Nouveau (New
               York: H. N. Abrams, 1962), p. 240, among
               others, has pointed out.</p>
               <p>11 Mentioning the care Margaret took of
               her husband (he became an alcoholic), Rob-
               ert Macleod writes how patiently and de-
               votedly she had borne “the years of trial
               and disappointment. Charles Rennie Mac-
               kintosh (Feltham, Middlesex: Country Life,
               1968), p. 150.</p>
               <p>12 Oakley (p. 185) states that none of the
               tearooms have survived intact, though part
               of the famous Willow Tearoom was doing
               service, quite recently, as Daly’s Bridal
               Boutique.</p>
               <p>Josephine Gear is an art historian presently teaching at
               the Parsons School of Design in New York.</p>
          </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
