<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
            xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#"
            xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#"
            xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#"
            xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
            xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#"
            xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/"
            xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" xmlns:fabio="https://purl.org/spar/fabio#"
            xmlns:bf="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#"
            xmlns:cito="https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#"
            xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#">
            <rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/">
               <![CDATA[{
	"@context": {
		"dcterms:created": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:created"
		},
		"dcterms:issued": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:issued"
		},
		"oa:motivatedBy": {
			"@type": "oa:Motivation"
		},
		"@language": "en",
		"rdf": "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#",
		"rdfs": "http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#",
		"as": "http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#",
		"cwrc": "http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#",
		"dc": "http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/",
		"dcterms": "http://purl.org/dc/terms/",
		"foaf": "http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/",
		"geo": "http://www.geonames.org/ontology#",
		"oa": "http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#",
		"schema": "http://schema.org/",
		"xsd": "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#",
		"fabio": "https://purl.org/spar/fabio#",
		"bf": "http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#",
		"cito": "https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#",
		"org": "http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"
	},
	"id": "https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2023-09/editorial_group.xml?organization_annotation_20230922115841345",
	"type": "oa:Annotation",
	"dcterms:created": "2023-09-22T15:58:41.345Z",
	"dcterms:modified": "2023-09-22T15:58:41.345Z",
	"dcterms:creator": {
		"@id": "1",
		"@type": [
			"cwrc:NaturalPerson",
			"schema:Person"
		],
		"cwrc:hasName": "admin"
	},
	"oa:motivatedBy": "oa:identifying",
	"oa:hasTarget": {
		"@id": "https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2023-09/editorial_group.xml?organization_annotation_20230922115841345#Target",
		"@type": "oa:SpecificResource",
		"oa:hasSource": {
			"@id": "https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2023-09/editorial_group.xml",
			"@type": "dctypes:Text",
			"dc:format": "text/xml"
		},
		"oa:renderedVia": {
			"@id": "https://leaf.bucknell.edu",
			"@type": "as:Application",
			"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
			"schema:softwareVersion": "3.2.2"
		},
		"oa:hasSelector": {
			"@id": "https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2023-09/editorial_group.xml?organization_annotation_20230922115841345#Selector",
			"@type": "oa:XPathSelector",
			"rdf:value": "TEI/text/body/div/p[2]/orgName"
		}
	},
	"oa:hasBody": {
		"@type": "org:Organization",
		"@id": "http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q20857976",
		"dc:format": "text/plain"
	},
	"as:generator": {
		"@id": "https://leaf.bucknell.edu",
		"@type": "as:Application",
		"rdfs:label": "LEAF-Writer",
		"schema:url": "https://leaf-writer.lincsproject.ca/",
		"schema:softwareVersion": "3.2.2"
	},
	"cwrc:hasCertainty": "cwrc:high"
}]]>
            </rdf:Description>
         </rdf:RDF></xenoData>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_005.jpg"
               n="5" xml:id="img_0005"/>

            <head><title>From the Editorial Group</title></head>
            <p> Women’s Traditional Arts? Initially we met anticipating discussions of
                  <objectName>quilts</objectName>, pottery and weaving rugs. But discussions of
               quillwork, poetry, and weaving narratives came up too. It became clear that basic to
               our concerns was the politics of aesthetics. And in these discussions we couldn’t
               examine either the artifacts or their politics without a constant awareness that our
               process was collective. We found that collectivity and deadlines make strange
               bedpersons. Like any revolution, any revelation, collectivity was the best of times,
               it was the worst of times.</p>
            <p>As a self-selected group of women we all shared a commitment to our topic and a
               commitment to the <orgName key="Heresies Collective"
                  ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q20857976" cert="high">Heresies
                  Collective</orgName>, the 21 women who are the magazine’s originators and
               publishers. Nearly half the editorial group which produced this issue are Heresies
               Collective members too. The others of us responded to the Heresies invitation which
               offers feminists the space and the means to explore and analyze women’s issues in
               depth. Our editorial responsibility ranged from discussing issues, soliciting
               articles, reading and responding to submissions and working editorially with writers,
               to the technical production of the magazine. This lengthy process required
               willingness to put aside learned notions of efficiency. Criticism and self-criticism
               were the feedback structures that allowed us continually to re-examine our process
               and our ideas. We had to respond to different levels of experience and tried to avoid
               their expression in conscious or unconscious hierarchies.                Our concern
               about structure had its emotional edge. We began as eleven. We are now nine. Our
               fledgling process was as full of pain and anxiety as it was of intelligence and
               optimism. We needed to weigh the comparative values of professional writing versus
               amateur investigation and set our own standards which emphasized the communication of
               issues rather than just cherished notions of good writing. Each editor had a sense of
               an insider/outsider tension. On the one hand, there was an unspoken set of
               assumptions shared by some members of the group, vocabulary and gestures which grew
               out of a common history, a common consciousness. On the other, there was a fear that
               this set of assump tions implied a clique.</p>
            <p>What kind of process did we create? We felt we were constantly tripping over
               ourselves. We were frustrated and embarrassed at all the doubling back and overlap in
               our discussions, especially when we were met with questions like, "If she’s a pain in
               the ass, why don’t you kick her out?" "Why do you waste so much time with democracy?"
               "Hierarchies are inevitable. Why don’t you face it?" "Isn’t a collective a camel
               designed by a committee?" What we created was awkward, was exhilarating. As involved
               as we all were with making the magazine beautiful. exciting, intellectually
               stimulating, this became secondary to the problem of how we could possibly
               accommodate ourselves to each other’s needs as creative women.</p>
            <p>How could we collectively make a magazine that represented us all? How comfortable
               were we with each other’s voices, with each other’s images, with each other’s ideas?
               We did not want this issue to be an organ for self-promotion. But fired by our
               discussions and prompted by questions raised in submitted articles, many members of
               the editorial group submitted articles for publication. Analogies were made to
               archeological digs and contemporary anthropology, and the more excited we were by the
               information of our contributors, the more immediately we wanted to participate
               ourselves.</p>
            <p>The Women’s Movement is in a new phase. Consciousness-raising continues to be basic
               to any feminist enterprise. We are shifting the arena of our political activity from
               the private to the public. In projects like Heresies this shift takes the concrete
               form of a magazine, the creation of a forum, the extension of ideas and images into
               places where they can be discussed and critiqued. This development requires a
               scrutiny which at times seems inimical to the support and solidarity that are the
               goals of consciousness-raising. But to resort pessimistically to the conclusion that
               deadlines demand bureaucracies is to overlook that we are still developing the sort
               of consciousness and fantasy that can project alternatives. A dialectic of content
               and process evolved in the production of this issue. Every positive aspect had its
               negative underbelly, and vice versa. Our understanding of women’s traditional arts
               expanded in response to the material submitted to us, and there were recurring
               motifs: time, efficiency and domesticity. Recognizing that time was a common
               denominator all women shared—time for one woman might mean cooking, for another
               weaving, for us, producing this issue—we began to realize the positive aspect of our
               flexibility in handling time (we were certainly not behaving “efficiently”), but we
               were simultaneously aware that the model for this attitude to time came from the
               family where the woman’s work is never done and always done and where the <name
                  cert="high" evidence="internal" full="yes" instant="unknown" type="event"
                  xml:space="default">endlessness of tasks</name> is depleting and domesticating.
               From her house flows much of the art                that this issue considers.</p>
            <p>In order to understand women’s traditional arts and our responses to it we had to
               deconstruct and reconstruct to be able to see clearly the interrelationships between
               art objects and the conditions in which they are produced. This cycle of dismantling
               and re-creating characterized our own creative process too. The boundaries women have
               worked within and challenged were familiar to us. Traditionally, women’s working
               spaces have been defined by their tent, hut or home, their psychological spaces by
               the rhythm of domestic demands. We often become attached to our working and
               psychological spaces to the extent that our process disintegrated when we moved from
               place to place and phase to phase. Confronted with women’s traditional arts, our
               loyalties were torn; we wanted at the same time to celebrate and lament. Trying to
               reconstruct a part of the history of women’s artmaking obliged us to tolerate these
               contradictions, to negate, affirm and transcend simultaneously what has characterized
               women’s work. In this way, re-evaluation of the past and how it impinges on the
               present does not necessitate a fresh start, but a self-reflective critical
               appropriation of a past which, though created by the “anonymous toil” of unknown
               women, belongs to all of us.               </p>
            <p>Language conveys attitudes and feelings and at the same time reflects and constructs
               consciousness. We were sensitive to the need for scrutinizing our words when we spoke
               together, for questioning clichés. Elements of a new vocabulary emerged in our
               discussions, a vocabulary which helped us view women’s traditional arts in the ways
               we have.</p>
            <p>“Filters” are the biases we bring to our projects. By acknowledging them, we wanted
               to challenge the myth of objectivity, to let our various feminist partisanships show.
               “Femmage” is the practice of collecting, recycling, reshaping and juxtaposing the
               artifacts of everyday life, a mode echoed in our production of this magazine.
               “Anonymous toil” is the labor that invisibly supports the honored products of
               culture. “Matronizing” attitudes are characterized by a smug feminism that knows the
               answers and ceases to be self-critical. Because we were dealing anthropologically
               with other cultures and editorially with other writers, we found ourselves fighting
               against falling into this stance. The entire process—from initial meetings to
               eventual publication—took nine months. Obviously a full-term pregnancy. The toughest
               part was to achieve the fine balance between the sentimental and the
               intellectual.</p>
            <p>Initially, our aim was to investigate women’s traditional arts. This led us to
               another question: what will women of the future make and what will their contexts be?
               We are at a peculiar and exciting edge: one foot in the socially stratified past, the
               other in our utopian fantasy of the future.</p>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
