<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_122.jpg"
               n="119" xml:id="img_0122"/>
            <head><title type="main">"BY THE LAKESIDE THERE IS AN ECHO</title>
               <title type="sub">Towards a History of Women’s Traditional Arts</title>
            </head>
            <byline>Valerie Hollister and Elizabeth Weatherford</byline>
         </div>
         <div>
            <epigraph>
               <p>"By the lakeside there is an echo. As they stand there with an open book the
                  chosen passages are re-uttered from the other side by a voice that be- comes
                  distance and repeats itself . . . I say that that which is is. I say that that
                  which is not also is. When she repeats the phrase several times the double, then
                  triple, voice endlessly superimposes that which is and that which is not. The
                  shadows brooding over the lake shift and begin to shiver because of the vibrations
                  of the voice. —Monique Wittig, Lés Guérilleres</p>
            </epigraph>

            <caption> Delicate terra-cotta figurines were molded in clay by Agni women (Ivory Coast)
               as portraits destined for royal tombs</caption>
            <p> For a more complete history of women’s art we must know the actual circumstances of
               women’s creativity and aesthetic contributions to culture. Scholars of traditional
               societies* assume that men’s “art” is sacred and dangerous to women and children,
               while women’s “craft” is significant only in the daily sphere and of no prime
               importance. These assumptions obscure the real and complex situation of women’s
               artmaking and totally block an appreciation of their art.</p>
            <p>We approached this article from different experiences. One of us, an anthropologist,
               is concerned with the current debates in feminist anthropological theory about
               women’s power or lack of it. One argument states that in all cultures women, no
               matter how actively they participate in the society’s life, are always considered
               inferior to men. Is this analysis true or are we so dependent on fragmentary
               reporting, usually based on the information of men, that we have not developed a way
               of knowing either women or their own evaluation of what they do? The other of us, a
               painter, interested for many years in the arts of Africa and the lives of African
               women, began this collaboration unknowingly influenced by the traditional arts of
               women. Both of us had been moved by the beauty of women’s art in traditional
               societies and wished to consider the ramifications of women’s public and private
               artmaking. This arti cle comes out of our readings and conversations.</p>
            <p>By assembling and analyzing the sparse information on the art of women in traditional
               societies we hope to raise questions which will provoke further research. We have
               organized our discussion into categories which emphasize questions about the scope of
               women’s art and its relationship to their societies and to women’s status within
               those, societies.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head><title>THE ART OF WOMEN’S RITUALS</title></head>
            <div>
               <p> Birth, initiation, marriage and death are ritually celebrated by women in most
                  societies and many female cults worship a patron goddess or god, but we can find
                  only scattered references to the ritual art objects women make. Early missionary
                  accounts of earth goddess rites in Nigeria’ state that ceramic votary objects and
                  clay goddess figures were made by the priestesses and their female initiates.
                  Recent reports do not mention women making these clay figures.? Agni women of
                  Ghana and Mangbetu women of Zaire make ritual funerary ceramics with portrait
                  heads. (This anthropomorphic art is considered atypical of women’s artmaking.)
                  Ceramic “figurines,” abstract in form, are made by adult women in many African
                  societies for the initiation rites of girls to explain the women’s view of women
                  and sexuality. Made of sundried clay, these are rarely collected by museums and
                  little known by scholars.? Is women’s ritual art not found because researchers
                  assume that women do not make ritual art? We presume far more examples exist
                  Extensive documentation of these objects is necessary to expand our knowledge of
                  women’s art and their lives.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head><title>ART AS SYMBOLS OF AUTHORITY</title></head>
               <p> Masks, free-standing figures and other carvings (appar- ently always made by men)
                  are used as symbols of secular authority in traditional societies. Western
                  anthropologists and collectors have been especially impressed by these forms,
                  since they conform more closely to Western definitions of art. As the most
                  frequently collected traditional artifacts, they are the most available for study
                  These objects are believed to be invested with power anc the person who uses them
                  wields that power. (Since they are usually commissioned, the artist is not
                  identified with the object s power.) The literature implies that since women do
                  not use these symbols of authority, they have little public power. The following
                  examples show that these assumptions are not true.</p>
               <p>In Sierra Leone and Liberia, the all-female Bundu society commissions masks for
                  use as symbols of their authority. The helmet mask and woven body covering worn by
                  the women lend an awesome appearance to their dance performance and are invested
                  with such power that they are utilized both in funeral rites and in intimidating
                  males or females who insult women. In the Ivory Coast <note> *Tribal and peasant
                     societies, with a nonmechanized technology, and with much social and political
                     life centered on a kin group consisting of many generations connected by blood
                     or marriage ties, not partaking indigenously of the Western cultural or
                     economic tradition. 119</note>
                  <pb
                     facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_123.jpg"
                     n="120" xml:id="img_0123"/>
                  <caption> Woman dancer of the Bundu society wearing commissioned helmet
                     mask.</caption>
                  <caption> Woman from Hupa (north California) tribe in typical dress embellished
                     with sea shells. Credit: Smithsonian</caption>
                  <caption> Fulani woman (the western Sudan) wearing traditional hair style.
                     ﻿120</caption> Senufo women commission carvings for use in their divination
                  society, the Sandogo.“ Women’s divination is considered essential to determining
                  outcomes of important events and discovering causes for social disruptions.
                  Although male-commissioned Senufo masks have been well analyzed, the art of the
                  Sandogo society is frequently not discussed, giving an unbalanced view of women’s
                  power in this culture. In stratified societies, such as African cultures in which
                  power was wielded jointly by female and male sovereigns, art work was commissioned
                  by both, but we do not know in what ways it represented the female aspects of
                  power.</p>
               <p>Besides commissioned objects, women use dance to affirm their authority. Among the
                  Kom and other groups in the Cameroons women participate in a disciplinary
                  performance called anlu, if a parent or pregnant woman is insulted or beaten or an
                  old woman abused, if incest occurs, or when the women of the village want to use
                  discipline against men.</p>
               <quote>“Anlu is started off by a woman who doubles up in an awful position and gives
                  out a high-pitched shrill, breaking it by beating on the lips with the four
                  fingers. Any woman recognizing the sound does the same and leaves whatever she is
                  doing and runs in the direction of the first sound. The crowd quickly swells and
                  soon there is a wild dance to the tune of impromptu stanzas informing the people
                  of what offence has been committed, spelling it out in such a manner as to raise
                  emotions and to cause action . . Then the team leaves for the bush to return at
                  the appointed time, donned in vines, with painted faces, to carry out the full
                  ritual . . . Vulgar parts of the body are exhibited as the chant rises in weird
                  depth ... [Account by Kom man].5</quote>
               <p>During the Aba riots of 1921 when 10,000 Ibo women demonstrated against the
                  British, their final, most powerful show of force was a performance like anlu. In
                  what other instances do women’s arts of authority exist and what forms do they
                  take?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head><title>PERSONAL DECORATION</title></head>
               <p> In many cultures personal ornamentation, perhaps more than any other art form,
                  provides the basis for a complex system of signs. The body becomes a background on
                  which messages about rank, wealth, sexual maturity, marital status and occupation
                  are expressed. Clothing, jewelry, tattooing, scarification, body painting and hair
                  styling are consciously designed to convey these messages. Young Zulu and Swazi
                  women in southeastem Africa make necklaces as courting poems in which the beads
                  are carefully ordered, each bead a metaphor for a range of meanings. White beads,
                  for example, symbolize all that is good, and have cleansing and purifying powers.
                  They appease ancestors, bring good luck and represent the heart and love itself.“
                  Because societies like these do not use writing, such codifications of messages
                  are especially significant.</p>
               <p>Excessive neck lengthening, knocking out of teeth, amputation of fingers, wearing
                  of multiple weighty anklets, necklaces and bracelets, footbinding and clitoral and
                  labial excisions are all done in the name of beauty Why is women’s personal
                  decoration apparently more extreme than that of men of their cultures, and why do
                  women s clothing and jewelry so often seem to hinder their <pb
                     facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_124.jpg"
                     n="121" xml:id="img_0124"/>
                  <caption> Women’s wall murals in South Africa combine archaic and modern tech
                     niques. This work portrays the village of the artist, a Ndebele woman Kulele
                     Mohlangu. Credit: Thomas Matthews, African Arts</caption> mobility? To what
                  extent is personal decoration an expression of self-identification and to what
                  extent is it a sign of women’s being property and a reinforcement of women’s
                  inferior status?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head><title>THE UTILITARIAN ARTS</title></head>
               <p>Although frequently centered in the home, women’s utilitarian arts form a
                  fundamental and pervasive part of the public visual aesthetic. Women create a
                  visual enviror ment by the arrangement and cleanliness of their tents or
                  compounds; the making of pots; the incising of calabashes; the weaving, dyeing and
                  embroidering of cloth, baskets, mats and rugs; the application of quill and
                  beadwork to cloth and skins; and the painting of murals and application of
                  decorations to the interior and exterior walls of houses. In spite of the
                  documentation of the existence of these arts, there is little analysis of them or
                  of the status of the women who make them. Why has the impact of women’s art on
                  their cultures been so neglected by scholars when it plays such a pervasive role
                  in people’s lives?</p>
               <p>Women’s traditional art has received little attention from Western writers not
                  only because it is utilitarian but because it is almost always abstract. Neither
                  the iconog- raphy, the formal structure nor the symbolism of women’s abstract
                  images and patterns has received serious attention and analysis with a few
                  exceptions, such as a study of bokolanfini, “mud” cloth made by Bamana women of
                  Mali, which describes the designs as abstractions of specific historical events.”
                  The assumption that women’s abstract designs have no meaning is directly related
                  to the idea that traditional women artists are not creative. How do women’s
                  choices of image and pattern reflect their traditions, their own inventiveness and
                  concerns of their society?</p>
               <p>In traditional societies men as well as women produce utilitarian art. Yet even
                  when they work with the same materials their form, content and technique differ
                  markedly (for example, Plain buffalo-skin robe designs and the loom widths in West
                  Africa and Spanish America). There has been no satisfactory explanation of these
                  differences. Western art scholars seem to favor psychobiological ex- planations,
                  often ignoring the impact of historical events, such as colonialism and the
                  introduction of foreign technologies.</p>
               <caption> Detail, Bokolanfini cloth. Resist-printed by painting negative areas with
                  mud and decorated with motifs representing a nineteenth-century battle. The cross
                  represents a Mauritanian woman’s cushion, which symbolizes no bility. Credit:
                  Marli Shamir</caption>

            </div>
            <div>

               <head><title>FEMALE MUSICIANS, BARDS AND SINGERS</title></head>
               <p>Musical instruments are frequently particular to one sex or the other. Among the !
                  Kung of the Kalahari Desert men play hunting bows, with one end placed in their
                  mouths. Adolescent girls play the pluriarch, the “women’s” instru- ment, which
                  consists of several small bows attached to a box plucked by the fingers.” Adult
                  women apparently are not musicians as often as men. In the context of dance !Kung
                  women frequently provide the percussive back-up for men’s dances by hand clapping.
                  For their own dances, melon tossing, women sing elaborate lyrics and provide their
                  own hand clapping. Men can join the women’s dance although women cannot join that
                  of men. How do musica instruments and musical performances by women reflect their
                  roles and status in other spheres?</p>
               <p>Through their lullabies women’s song universally pro- vides the earliest
                  environment in which children develop language and musical sensibilities. When
                  women work and perform rituals together and for each other, song and dance play an
                  important part, but have rarely been record- ed. The songs’ explicit erotic
                  content (often satiric and bantering) may have militated against fuller
                  description.</p>
               <p>Where women have major economic and social roles, as in tropical Africa, women s
                  participation and leadership in public song and dance performance is traditional.?
                  In other cultures where the sexual spheres are more clearly hierar chical, men s
                  and women’s music is segregated. In rural Yugoslavia there are two categories of
                  songs, “heroes’ songs and “women’s” songs. Sung before an audience by a single
                  male, heroes’ songs idealize the male as heroic war- rior. All other songs are
                  called women s songs and are usually sung in groups by women, children or men: by
                  describing suffering and everyday reality, they reveal women’s skepticism and
                  resistance to the heroic ideal.10</p>
               <p>In many agrarian cultures when women sing alone before a public audience they are
                  considered prostitutes. A respectable woman is therefore restricted in her public
                  activities.1 Nomadic Arabic desert cultures, however, en- courage women poets of
                  distinction to compose commen- taries on their society, which are sung in public.
                  Among the Bagarra of the Sudan women bards sing the history of the group, lead
                  warriors into battle with songs and in the system of tribal justice sing of the
                  crime and punishment of the convicted. “In performance a (bard) always stands out
                  in the position of respected authority, her wit is ap- preciated and her
                  techniques for composition are copied by young women aspiring to her position of
                  influence in the community.12 In what contexts are women’s musical per- formances
                  a commentary on their culture’s history; and in what contexts do women articulate
                  their own history, myths and opinions through dance and song!</p>

               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_125.jpg"
                  n="122" xml:id="img_0125"/>

               <caption> Osage ribbon-work blanket. The hand motif may have represented family
                  members, or perhaps it had a more mystical meaning.</caption>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head><title>WOMEN ARTISTS’ COMMUNITIES</title></head>
               <p> Traditional women artists work in groups either by col- laborating on one object
                  (such as the long tapa cloths of Polynesia) or by establishing networks for
                  techniques and innovations to be exchanged and for traditions to be taught. Women
                  artists working as a community have been emphasized in research on Pueblo and
                  African potters; Pomo, Yurok and Karok (California) basketweavers; and Plains
                  quill and bead workers. Although expertise is recognized and acknowledged among
                  these women, their artmaking is not highly competitive. In the village of Ushafa,
                  Nigeria, women who “make the best ware only make special pots when commissioned to
                  do so ... otherwise, their pots are made to be indistinguishable from the rest.”13
                  How do women artists interact and criticize each other’s work in traditional
                  societies, and do their communities differ from those of men artists?</p>
               <p>Since colonialism, commissions by traders who deal in traditional artifacts have
                  tended to isolate experts from the other artists. Modern governments, by creating
                  new training centers for the unskilled, have usurped the tradi tional roles of the
                  experts. How does the alteration of their artistic communities affect women s art
                  and status in their cultures?</p>
               <caption> Contemporary female bard of the Baggara of the southern Sudan Republic.
                  Credit: R. C. Carlisle</caption>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head><title>WOMEN’S ART AND CULTURAL CHANGE</title></head>
               <p> With the introduction of new materials, the substitution of imported objects and
                  the influence of new images. colonialism and cultural contact have altered the art
                  of women in traditional societies. Women’s response has often been inventive,
                  appropriating objects and images and putting them to novel use. In a Ghana village
                  women decorate the exterior doorways of their houses with imported china plates,
                  turned to expose the manufacturers inscriptions, which they consider picturesque.”
                  Many colonized peoples, curious about other cultures, have incorporated their
                  observations into their art, sometimes as ironic commentary, sometimes as an
                  exploration of ’exotic” designs. North American Indian women devel- oped vine and
                  flower patterns in their beadwork based, perhaps, on the crewel arts of the
                  northern European colonists. The art of non-Western women has been appre- ciated
                  in turn by Western women and used to decorate their homes. Near Eastern and native
                  American rugs, for example, are a traditional women’s art which has had a special
                  place in the aesthetic environment of Western people. In contrast to the intense
                  interest of art historians in discovering exactly when Western artists first saw
                  African masks, the influences of the women’s art from traditional societies on
                  Western art of all kinds remains undocumented.</p>
               <p>The impact of colonialism has been contradictory for women. In some cases it has
                  weakened the hold of patriarchs over women. In others, by ignoring women’s
                  traditional economic independence, it has provided education and employment
                  primarily for men. If women are educated, they are required to sever connections
                  with their own traditions. Most women, however, seem to retain the traditional
                  fabrics and dress longer than men do, indicating, perhaps, both their skepticism
                  about the benefits of modernization and their attempt to keep their cultural
                  traditions intact. Modernization has sometimes eroded the barriers which
                  traditionally prevented women from using anthropomorphic and zoomorphic images and
                  from carving in wood and ivory.15 In addition, since colonialism, wider markets
                  for both old and new forms of women’s art have developed.</p>
               <p>Colonization and modernization have also had quite negative impacts on women’s
                  artmaking. Institutions that once commissioned art produced by women, such as the
                  refined tapa cloth used in Hawaii to wrap god-figures,16 have often disappeared as
                  the result of contact with West- ern missionaries. The basis for sharing resources
                  by women and men has also changed. Baule women thread- makers lost their
                  traditional ownership of the cloth men wove from their thread when it was replaced
                  by manufac- tured thread.1” Many of the utilitarian arts—local cloth. decorated
                  hides, baskets and ceramics—have been replaced by imported cloth and plastic and
                  metal containers. As traditional art forms are replaced by ones made from modern
                  materials and by modern techniques, they may be- come rare commodities, sold to
                  tourists and collectors.</p>
               <p>Through such sales the entire history of women s art may disappear from the
                  culture which produced it.</p>
               <p>Although under modern influence women’s traditional arts may continue, usually new
                  images, styles or techniques are developed. How have these changes occurred? What
                  changes in quality and meaning take place when women artists use new materials and
                  begin to produce art for unfamiliar buyers? With the expansion of <pb
                     facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_126.jpg"
                     n="126" xml:id="img_0126"/>
                  <caption>Cuna women dancing. The molas which serve as panels on their blouses are
                     sewn in appliqué and embroidery, using several layers of brightly colored
                     cloth. This is the most complex visual art of the Cuna. Credit: F. Louis
                     Hoover.</caption> the marketing of their arts has their economic base been
                  eroded or strengthened? And, in those cases where the women’s traditional art has
                  disappeared, how do women adapt to this loss?</p>
               <p>We have reviewed some of the scattered evidence of the kinds of art women make in
                  traditional societies and we have asked questions to stimulate further
                  investigation. The few available in-depth studies were written mainly in the 1920s
                  and 1930s by women anthropologists studying native American cultures.18 These
                  ethnographers ap- proached their field research with the attitude that withir
                  those cultures women’s participation was real, perhaps central, and as women they
                  had greater access to informa- tion from women. Many of the questions we want
                  answered now were not asked by them. In order to com- pile a more complete history
                  of women’s artmaking, more ethnographies are needed, informed by feminist ideas.
                  Women’s art from traditional societies excites us with its beauty and its
                  relevance to life. We want to know more about the circumstances in which it is
                  made, used and ap preciated. Only then will be begin to understand fully how women
                  create culture.</p>
               <p>We are at the lakeside. To construct a feminist history of women artists we must
                  consider all that has been writ- ten and unearth more. We must consider all that
                  has been left out, as well. We must talk with each other, and out of the dialogue
                  will come new ideas, new critiques. Through the superimposition of what we have
                  known and what we are insisting on knowing, we can dispel the shadows which have
                  remained too long.</p>
               <caption> Karok basket, twined with knobbed lid, decorated with yellow porcupine
                  quills and rich brown maidenhair fern stem. Credit: Denver Museum,
                  YKa-58</caption>

               <caption> lowa beaded moccasins (c. 1860) beaded in blue, green, red, pink, yellow
                  and black. A fine example of a colorful abstract style which developed neai the
                  Kansas-Nebraska border. (Private collection/American Indian Art)</caption>
            </div>
            <div>
               <list>
                  <item>1. P. Amaury Talbot, Tribes of the Niger Delta (London: Sheldon Press,
                     1932), p. 94 and figures. In this and other works Talbot describes the roles of
                     Nigerian women in the various cults of their tribes. These may include the
                     making of figurines, symbol-laden pots, and wall decorations of shrines. It is
                     unclear if women created figures for mbari houses, but they created portrait
                     ceramics of ancestors and famous priestesses. Whether, and how, their religious
                     art differed in form and function from that of men deserves further
                     investigation.</item>
                  <item>2. See Herbert M. Cole, “Art as a Verb in Iboland, African Arts Autumn 1969,
                     pp. 34-41; “Mbari is Life, Spring 1969, pp. 8-17; “Mbari is Dance, Summer 1969,
                     pp. 42-51.</item>
                  <item>3. See Hans Cory, Ceramic Figurines: Their Ceremonial Use in Primi- tive
                     Rites in Tanganyika (London: Faber and Faber, 1956).</item>
                  <item>4. Anita Glaze, “Power and Art in a Senufo Village, African Arts, Spring
                     1975, pp. 25-29, 64-67</item>
                  <item>5. Eyewitness account cited in Shirley Ardener, “Sexual Insult and Fe- male
                     Militancy, in Perceiving Women (New York: Halsted Press, 1975), pp.
                     36-37</item>
                  <item>6. Regina Twala, “Beads as Regulating the Social Life of the Zulu and the
                     Swazi, reprinted in Everyman His Way, ed. Alan Dundes (Englewood Cliffs, N.J.:
                     Prentice-Hall, 1968), pp. 368-369</item>
                  <item>7. Pascal James Imperator and Marli Shamir, “Bokolanfini, Mud Cloth of the
                     Bamana of Mali, African Arts, Summer 1970.</item>
                  <item>8. N. England, cited in Seth Reichlin, “Bitter Melons”: A Study Guide
                     (Somerville, MA: Documentary Educational Resources, 1974), p. 27</item>
                  <item>9. Alan Lomax and Forrestine Paulay, Dance and Human History (film).
                     Distributed by University of California Extension Media Center</item>
                  <item>10. Mary P. Coote, “Women’s Songs in Serbo-Croatian,” Journal of American
                     Folklore, 90 (1977), pp. 331-33</item>
                  <item>11. Norma McLeod and Marcia Herndon, “The Bormliza: Maltese Folk song Style
                     and Women, in Women and Folklore, ed. Claire Farrar (Austin: University of
                     Texas Press, 1975), pp. 81-100.</item>
                  <item>12. Roxanne Connick Carlisle, “Women Singers in Darfur, Sudan Re- public,
                     Anthropos 68, 1973, pp. 785-798.</item>
                  <item>13. Jane and Donald Bandler, “The Pottery of Ushafa, African Arts, Spring
                     1977, pp. 26-31.</item>
                  <item>14. Barbara Guggenheim, private communication.</item>
                  <item>15. Simon Kooijman, “Tapa Techniques and Tapa Patterns in Poly- nesia in
                     Primitive Art and Society, ed. Anthony Forge (London: Ox- ford University
                     Press, 1973), p. 110.</item>
                  <item>16. Mona Etienne, “Women and Men, Cloth and Colonization: The Transformation
                     of Production-Distribution Relations among the Baule (Ivory Coast), Cahiers
                     d’Etudes Africaines 65, XVII (1), 1977 (n.p.).</item>
                  <item>17. For example, Ruth Bunzel, The Pueblo Potter (New York: Dover
                     Publications, reprint, 1969) and Lila M. O’Neale, “Yurok-Karok Basket Weavers,
                     University of California Publications in American Archaeology and Ethnology 32,
                     1932, pp. 1-182.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div>
            <p> Valerie Hollister is a painter of partial figures influenced by all kinds of
               decorative art. She lives in Swarthmore, Pennsylvania.</p>

            <p>Elizabeth Weatherford is a cultural anthropologist teaching at the School of Visual
               Arts in New York City. 123</p>
         </div>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
