<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
                  <div>            
   <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_057.jpg" n="57" xml:id="img_0057"/>
            
               <head><title>WOMEN OF THE BAUHAUS</title></head>
               <byline>Martha Kelle</byline>
               <p>Women comprised about a third of the student bodv of the Bauhaus, the famous 1920s experiment in an
               education, and about ten percent of the faculty.(1) Through the writings of these women, we can see the politics               
               of the craft/art split in their time—the sexual division of materials, the rejection of the cult of personalityla
               affirmation of anonymity), the struggle to amalgamate art and craft into a larger social sphere via industr
               etc. These issues are of continuing interest today—for artists, teachers and feminists.</p>
            
               <p>After six months in the preliminary Bauhaus course, students moved on to one of seven workshops in crafts
               The workshop organization was sometimes diagramed in circular form to avoid the implication of a hier
               archy. Let's look at where women worked in a Bauhaus linear listing. (2)</p>

            <table>
               <row>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell>STONE</cell>
                  <cell>WOOD</cell>
                  <cell>METAL</cell>
                  <cell>CLAY</cell>
                  <cell>GLASS</cell>
                  <cell>COLOR</cell>
                  <cell>TEXTILES</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell>(cabinet making)</cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell>(mural)</cell>
                  <cell>(weaving)</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Faculty</cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell>Marianne Brandt</cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell><list> 
                     <item>Helene Borner</item>
                     <item>Gunta Stölzl</item>
                        <item>Anni Albers</item>
                        <item>Otti Berger (sub)</item>
                        <item>Lilli Reich</item>
                  </list></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Students with work in
                     English-language publications</cell>
                  <cell>Alma Buscher</cell>
                  <cell>Marianne Brandt</cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell>Lou Scheper</cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell>
                     <list>
                        <item>Gunta Stölz</item>
                           <item>Anni Albers</item>
                           <item>Ruth Hollos</item>
                           <item>Ruth Citroen Vallentin</item>
                           <item>Gertrude Hantsch</item>
                           <item>Hedwig Jungnik</item>
                            <item>Suse Ackermann</item>
                        <item>Korona Krause</item>
                        <item>Margarete Kohler</item>
                        <item>Marianne Heyman</item>
                       <item> Mila Hoffman-Lederer</item>
                        <item>Ida Kerkovios</item>
                        <item>Benita Otte</item>
                        <item>Martha Erps</item>
                        <item>Lies Beyer</item>
                        <item>Agnes Roghe</item>
                     </list>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            
            <figure><caption>
               Anni Albers: Knotted rug, smyrna wool (1925)
               Black, shades of gray and red. Gascard-Diepold
               Collection, Berlin.</caption></figure>
            <p>
               What were the sociopolitical implications
               of the fact that most of these women were
               relegated to the weaving workshop? Anni
               Albers at first objected to being there.</p>
               <quote>I was tempted by the glass workshop. Un-
               fortunately it was decided that no other stu
               dents could be admitted for work there. ..
               Weaving? Weaving I thought was too sissy.
               I was looking for a real job; I went into
               weaving unenthusiastically as merely the
               least objectionable choice . .. Gradually
               threads caught my imagination. (3)</quote>
                     
               <p>Helene Nonne-Schmidt, writing in the
               Leipzig journal Vivos voco in 1926, saw the
               role of women in weaving as an affirmation
               of a traditional women’s art, but today her
               position has sexist implications.</p>
               <quote>The artistically active woman applies hersel)
               most often and most successfully to work in
               a two-dimensional plane. This observation
               can be explained by her lack of the spatia
               imagination characteristic of men. Of course
               there are individual differences and differ-
               ences of degree here, just as the nature o)
               the sexes seldom is either purely masculine
               or feminine. In addition, the way the wom-
               an sees is, so to speak, childlike, because
               like a child she sees the details instead of the
               over-all picture. The woman’s way of seeing
               things is not to be taken as a deficiency
               rather it is simply the way she is constituted
               and it enables her to pick up the richness o
               nuances which are lost to the more compre
               hensive view. But let us not deceive our
               selves into thinking this aspect of her nature
               will change, despite all the accomplishments
               of the Women’s Movement and despite al
               the investigations and experiments. There
               are even indications that woman is counting
               on her limitations, considering them a greal
               advantage...<lb/>
               Within the Bauhaus and its workshops the
               woman is primarily interested in the work o
               the weaving workshop and there finds the
               widest range of opportunities. Weaving rep-
               resents the fusion of an infinite multiplicit)
               to unity, the interlocking of many threads to
               make up a fabric. It is quite evident to wha
               extent this field of work is appropriate to a
               woman and her talents.<lb/>
               The ability of woman to become absorbed in
               detail and her interest in experimental
               "play" with surfaces suit her for this work...(4)</quote>
               <p>What were some other political implica
               tions of the fact that weaving was, as Gunta
               Stölzl put it, “primarily a woman’s field ol
               work?” One answer that comes up is the
            
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_058.jpg" n="58" xml:id="img_0058"/>
            <figure><caption>
               Marianne Brandt: Spherical Lighting fixture
               with safety chains, ca. 1928.</caption></figure>
            <figure><caption>
               Marianne Brandt: Small pot for tea essence with
               deep tea strainer (1924) Brass container, silver-
               plated, inside, ebony handle. Set-in strainer
               made of silver. Bauhaus-Archiv, Darmstadt.</caption></figure>
            
               political value of material. Some art materi-
               als are “higher than others; paint, bronze
               and marble are distinguished from “low
               art materials such as clay, fiber, glass, wood
               and metal because of cost and accessibility
               In this regard, the Bauhaus attitude seemed
               crucial and ironic. On the one hand there
               was the declaration about raising no “arro-
               gant barrier between artist and craftsman.
               On the other, a barrier was raised within the
               crafts, though a few women circumvented
               it. And it seems significant that the weaving
               workshop was at the bottom of a (not alpha-
               betical) list of workshops offered in the first
               brochure published by the Bauhaus.</p>
               <p>The career of Anni Albers expresses some
               of the irony of the Bauhaus attitude. Albers,
               who studied painting before entering the
               Bauhaus, had a long successful career as a
               weaver and teacher, but since 1965 she has
               turned to another art form, printmaking. It
               is as though, after fighting to prove that
               weaving is an art, she has given up. “Weav-
               ing, she said in a recent interview with
               Gene Baro, “is not generally recognized as
               an art, but as a craft. I find that when the
               work is made with threads, it’s considered a
               craft; when it s on paper, it’s considered
               art." (5) Yet Albers’s early writings abound
               with support of the Bauhaus’s unpreju-
               diced attitude towards materials and their
               inherent capacities. She explains this atti-
               tude in numerous instances that relate as
               well to anonymity in design.</p>
               <quote>.. . all art is form in some material . . .(6)</quote>
               <quote>Any material is good enough for art. (7)</quote>
               <quote>Design is often regarded as the form im-
               posed on the material by the designer. But is
               we, as designers, cooperate with the mater-
               ial, treat it democratically, you might say
               we will reach a less subjective solution of
               this problem of form and therefore a more
               inclusive and permanent one. The less we,
               as designers, exhibit in our work our per-
               sonal traits, our likes and dislikes, our pe-
               culiarities and idiosyncrasies, in short, our
               individuality, the more balanced the form
               we arrive at will be. It is better that the
               material speaks than that we speak our-
               selves. The design that shouts “I am a pro-
               duct of Mr. X” is a bad design. As consum-
               ers, we are not interested in Mr. X but in his
               product, which we want to be our servant
               and not his personal ambassador. Now, if
               we sit at our desk designing, we cannot
               avoid exhibiting ourselves for we are exclud-
               ing the material as our co-worker, as the di
               rective force in our planning. (8)</quote>
               <p>What about the women in areas other
               than weaving? Margarete Sachsenberg was
               business manager of the Bauhaus from
               1926-1932, organized the transfer of the
               Bauhaus to Berlin and set up the adminis-
               tration there. Gerda Marx was a physical
               education instructor. In 1932, supervision of
               the interior design workshop and seminar
               was assigned to Lilli Reich; before this, she
               was Mies van der Rohe s closest associate as
               an interior designer. When he was director
               of the Bauhaus, van der Rohe appointed her
               to direct the weaving workshop as well.
               Reich was among the last group of faculty in
               Berlin who voted to close the Bauhaus
               under pressure from the Nazi regime.</p>
               <p>The work of a woman in the cabinet-
               making workshop was one of the first Bau-
               haus products to receive favorable public
               response. Alma Buscher’s design for child-
               ren s furniture was “thought out equally
               well with respect to practicality, economy
               and form. When she designed a toy cab-
               inet, it was made for children to play and
               build with; most of it could be taken apart
               and reassembled. (9)</p>
               <p>In the metal workshop, Marianne Brandt
               studied with Moholy-Nagy.</p>
<quote>               At first I was not accepted with pleasure-
               there was no place for a woman in a metal
               workshop, they felt. They admitted this to
               me later on and meanwhile expressed their
               displeasure by giving me all sorts of dull,
               dreary work. How many little hemispheres
               did I most patiently hammer out of brittle
               new silver, thinking that was the way it had
               to be and all beginnings are hard. Later
               things settled down and we got along well
               together. (10)</quote>
               <p>Illustrations of Brandt’s work in indus-
               trial design can be seen in Wingler s Bau-
               haus: globe lighting fixtures, her famous
               Kandem lamp, egg cooker, tea and coffee
               set. A number of these works—along with
               weavings by Stölzl and Albers—are in the
               Museum of Modern Art’s permanent collec-
               tion.</p>
               <p>Through Alma Mahler, Walter Gropius
               (founder of the Bauhaus) met Johannes It-
               ten and appointed him teacher of the first
               preliminary course at the Bauhaus. (11)
               Through Itten s influence, Gertrude Gru-
               now was hired to teach “Studies in Har-
               mony.</p>
               <p>Fifty-five years old at the time of her ap-
               pointment, Grunow was a woman of
               ’strong spiritual force” with extraordinary
               ability to empathize with students — "an
               intuitively sure hand in dealing with young
               people. Felix Klee referred to her as “the
               good spirit of the Bauhaus.” (12) According to
               her synesthetic thinking, one basic entity,
               the same original phenomenon, is per
               ceivable in sound, color and form. Her quo-
               tation is from a Bauhaus publication. (13)</p>
              <quote> The supreme law, according to which all
               order is structured, is called equilibrium.
               Nature, having placed the organ of equilib-
               rium in the ear, has given man a guardian
               and protector of order, the ear thus being
               designated to be the immediate and highest
               judge of order within the organism. The<lb/>
            
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_059.jpg" n="59" xml:id="img_0059"/>
            <figure><caption>
               Alma Buscher: Children’s Room Dresser, 1924.
               Wood lacquered in light color. Mrs. Siedhoff,
               Frankfurt.</caption></figure>
            <figure><caption>
               Gunta Stölzl: Tapestry, Jacquard fabric (1928-
               29) Whereabouts unknown. Watercolor sketch in
               the Bauhaus-Archiv, Darmstadt.</caption></figure>
            
               strong effects that sounds have on man can
               be attributed to equilibrium. The ear, dur-
               ing strain on the organism, senses the living
               order of that organism in its own specific,
               highest form of sensation, namely as sound
               (of any kind, even noise). Every living force,
               and thus every color, corresponds to a law-
               ful order, to a sound . ..</quote>
               <p>Further, with regard to the “weight” of
               color:</p>
               <quote>The act of weighing derives from the mind
               judiciously, progressing materially from
               the heaviest, the structurally firmest to the
               lightest, most ephemeral, most flexible. The
               scales and degrees increase and once more
               require a special order of colors (forces).<lb/>
               The order of colors . . . occurs as a circular
               one and constitutes an outward oriented
               tension of forces . . . The circle, a circle of
               gravity and equilibrium . . . is a fundamen-
               tal phenomenon and is of the same impor-
               tance to statics as the golden section had
               been for measurement.</quote>
               <p>Finally, let’s look at the view of Bauhaus
               women on the community of the Bau-
               haus; somehow the social organization of
               the Bauhaus enhanced its influence. Anni
               Albers describes it as</p>
               <quote>... a creative vacuum . . . unformalized,
               unformulated, even contradictory in its var-
               ious areas. (14)</quote>
               <p>Called by Felix Klee, "our Bauhaus
               mother," (15) Tut Schlemmer, wife of the the-
               ater director Oskar Schlemmer, described
               the climate of the Bauhaus as “like being on
               top of a volcano." (16) She recalled:</p>
               <quote>the continuous unrest that forced everyone
               to express a fundamental opinion of pro-
               found problems almost daily . . . It was
               wild and enthusiastic . .. Boys had long
               hair, girls short skirts. No collars or stock
               ings were worn, which was shocking and ex-
               travagant then .. . We developed a Bau-
               haus dance—a kind of hop expressing the
               joy of living. . .. In retrospect I believe I
               understand the secret of how the Bauhaus
               could develop in the face of incredible diffi-
               culties; we simply loved it . . . and felt re-
               sponsible. (17)</quote>
               <p>One gets a feeling here for the “unity in
               diversity” that Gropius described as an ob-
               jective of the Bauhaus. Lou Scheper, who
               participated in Klee’s course and Schlem-
               mer’s theater as well as in Itten’s mural
               workshop, said:</p>
               <quote>This community corresponded neither to
               the concept “commune nor the concept
               “cloister, even though individual Bauhaus
               people preferred the ascetic’s cell. The Bau
               haus community was the sum of significant,
               independent individuals who could develop
               more richly in association than in isolation
               .. . One talked "big"—of the postwar mood
               of political hope and artistic expectations, of
               the search for the unified work of art. Play
               and creative imagination and also a tenden
               cy toward mysticism, even to spiritual fai
               healing and to sectarianism and in additio
               a delight in nature taken from the yout
               movement are the badge of Bauhaus mem
               bers of that time, who were more artist
               than technicians, more craftsmen than con
               structors. It was only later that . .. th
               Cathedral of Socialism was replaced by...
               Art and Technology. Though the Bauhaus
               had originally started to produce unique,
               handcrafted pieces, it later developed ..
               the models for industrially produced art
               cles. Both were products of the same feeling
               for form, the sense of function and mater
               ials, and both were a consequence draun
               from the social tasks of the time. (18)</quote>
               <p>The craft areas of the Bauhaus (as re-
               flected in its name, meaning “Building-
               House”) were conceived to produce a uni
               fied architectural whole. Women largel
               were consigned to the additive craft
               while men worked in the structural “essen-
               tial” areas. Women, except for Lou
               Scheper, worked with soft or malleable ma-
               terials, and on objects that were mobile (fur-
               niture, weaving) rather than structurally
               permanent. Although the Bauhaus is gen-
               erally regarded as the most innovative art
               school of the twentieth century, its sexual
               division of craft continued traditional ideas
               about women’s work and men’s work.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1) From a roster count in Hans M. Wing-
               ler, The Bauhaus: Weimar Dessau Ber-
               lin Chicago (Cambridge: MIT Press.
               1969) pp. 615-621.</item>
               <item>2) Herbert Bayer, Ise Gropius, and Walter
               Gropius, Bauhaus 1919-1928 (New
               York: Museum of Modern Art, 1938,
               3rd printing, 1959), p. 23.</item>
               <item>3) Gene Baro, Anni Albers (Brooklyn: The
               Brooklyn Museum, 1977), p. 6.</item>
               <item>4) Reprinted in Wingler, p. 116.</item>
               <item>5) Baro, p. 8.</item>
               <item>6)“Art—A Constant in Anni Albers, On
               Designing (Wesleyan, Connecticut:
               Wesleyan University Press, 1959), p. 46.</item>
               <item>7) “One Aspect of Art Work”, Albers, p. 32.</item>
               <item>8) Albers, p. 6.</item>
               <item>9) Wingler, pp. 429, 503, 440, 532.</item>
               <item>10) Wingler, pp. 308, 311.</item>
               <item>11) Wingler, p. 2</item>
               <item>12) Eckhard Neumann, Bauhaus and Bau-
               haus People (New York: Van Nostrand
               Reinhold, 1970), p. 9.</item>
               <item>13) Wingler, p. 69.</item>
               <item>14) Interview with Neil Welliver, Craft
               Horizons, July/August, 1965, p. 42.</item>
               <item>15) Neumann, p. 43.</item>
               <item>16) Neumann, p. 155.</item>
               <item>17) Neumann, p. 154, 156.</item>
               <item>18) Neumann, p. 114.</item>
               </list>
                  </div>
      </body>
               <back>
               <div><p>Martha Keller is an artist who teaches at School Cra,
               College in Lavonia, Michigan.</p></div>
      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
