<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_117.jpg" n="117" xml:id="img_0117"/>
           
               <head><title>Turkmen „omen,
               weaving and
               Cultural Change</title></head>
              <byline> Mary A. Martin</byline>
            <p>
               Turkmen carpets are fine examples of weaving done by
               nomadic tribal women. In the last 100 years the context of
               weaving these carpets has changed considerably; formerly
               women produced them in the home for local consumption,
               now contract weavers and female and male factory workers
               produce for urban and foreign markets. In the nineteenth
               century the Turkmen lived in the Kara Kum desert in that
               part of Central Asia which is now the Soviet Socialist Repub-
               lic of Turkmenistan. This tribe primarily raised sheep and
               occasionally farmed. They sometimes raided neighboring
               areas. Nomads, they lived in tents called yurts which could
               be packed up and taken with them when they moved from
               one grazing area to another.</p>
               <p>Traditionally women made textile items for domestic use.
               For their yurts they made felt walls and decorative bands.
               They also knotted or embroidered individual bags for carry
               ing tent poles, utensils, provisions and other household pos-
               sessions. A special carpet was hung at the entrance of the
               yurt and another was hung to function as a door.
               Carpets woven by women were central to household, cul-
               tural and religious life: used for entertaining, given as gifts,
               spread for community gatherings, used to furnish guesthous-
               es, and used for prayers. Turkmen society regarded a wom-
               an’s weaving skill much as it esteemed a man s code of valor;
               weaving defined a woman’s status, indirectly gave her access
               to wealth, was the one domaiń in which a woman was able to
               distinguish herself.</p>
               <p>In the latter half of the nineteenth century the life of the
               Turkmen changed because Russia took permanent political
               and military control and inhibited Turkmen raids of sur-
               rounding populations. At this time many Turkmen moved to
               Afghani territory although it was not until the 1920s that
               large numbers fled to Afghanistan to escape Soviet collectiv-
               ization.</p>
               <p>In Afghanistan the Turkmen competed for pastures and
               living space with other ethnic groups—Pashtun, Aimaq,
               Hazara, Tajik, Baluch, Arab and Uzbeg. As the pasturage
               was limited in Afghanistan and Turkmen flocks reduced,
               many Turkmen settled into villages; few continued to live as
               nomads in yurts. If families did not raise enough sheep to
               provide wool for their weaving needs they had to purchase
               it—no longer from other Turkmen but from other tribes,
               such as the tent-dwelling Pashtun. Individual or market
               trading formerly carried out with kinsmen and other Turk-
               men was now done with groups who were neither.</p>
               <p>The move to Afghanistan severely affected carpet weav-
               ing. For ten to fifteen years after arriving in Afghanistan
               Turkmen women did not make carpets.* When they began
               making carpets again, they had to overcome this break in
               tradition. They remembered carding, spinning and weaving
               techniques, but colors and patterns changed. Young girls
               had grown up without learning the traditional designs. When
               older women had died, they had taken with them the knowl-
               edge of traditional patterns and of dye recipes. Changes in
               color in twentieth-century carpets may also be related to the
               difficulty of obtaining customary vegetable dyes and mor-
               dants in a new ecological setting. The breed of sheep and
               quality of wool also differed in the new environment. De-</p>            
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_119jpg" n="118" xml:id="img_0118"/>
            <p>
               signs once unique to particular tribal sections, isolated from
               each other in the past, changed as they came into direct con-
               tact with each other. Women now married into other groups
               which led to the mixing of traditional designs.</p>
               <p>The society in which Turkmen live has been transformed
               since the nineteenth century, affecting the women who tradi-
               tionally weave the carpets as well as their relation to the
               mode of production of these carpets. Production has shifted
               its locus from kinship units to a nonkinship context, the fac-
               tory. The family mode of production could not meet the ris-
               ing demand for carpets, thus contract weaving and factories
               increased.</p>
               <p>The first factories in the provinces employed only men,
               but women were weaving out of the home in women’s centers
               or prisons at that time. In the past few years factories in
               Kabul have begun to train and employ women who weave in
               rooms separate from the men. Because of the profit to be
               gained from weaving, non-Turkmen women have begun to
               take up carpet weaving—often by apprenticing themselves to
               Turkmen women in their homes or by going to the factories
               to learn. Weaving now serves as one of the few nondomestic
               occupations open to women in Afghanistan. At a time when
               the family-centered tribal society is breaking down, carpet
               weaving allows women an opportunity to participate in a
               more complex, non-kin-based economy.</p>
               <p>Since the days when Turkmen women lived on the Rus-
               sian steppes and wove for their families, conditions have
               changed. The women who remained in the Soviet Union
               were employed in state-controlled factories before the women
               who moved to Afghanistan.</p>
               <p>Afghani Turkmen women still weave under traditional
               conditions or on contract; primarily it is non-Turkmen
               women in Afghanistan who have begun factory work. Where
               Turkmen women oversee the process in factories, the high
               quality of weave has been maintained.</p>
               <p>Turkmen women have always had an important influence
               on weaving, originally produced for exclusively domestic use
               but now produced for market consumption as well. Although
               the traditional colors and designs have changed because of
               political boundaries, migration and altered modes of produc-
               tion, Turkmen women continue to produce fine examples of
               weaving.</p>
               <p>Note: Material for this article comes from travel through
               Turkmen regions in Afghanistan in 1971 and observations in
               a Kabul carpet factory in December 1975 and February
               1977. Special thanks are due to Hajji Ewaz Badghisi, his
               wife, Bayram, and daughter, Aidgol, for their patience in ex-
               plaining the techniques of weaving and dyeing. 1 also wish to
               acknowledge the assistance of Dr. Brian Spooner and Pat
               Barr for their part in helping me learn about the Turkmen
               and their weaving in the twentieth century.
               *Brian Spooner, “Afghan Carpets,” Expedition 15 (2),
               1973, p. 15.</p>
            <p>
               Mary A. Martin is a cultural anthropologist who has worked in Iran and Afghanistan.
               She lives in Philadelphia.</p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
