<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Waste Not Want Not</title>
            <author>Meyer, Melissa</author>
            <author>Schapiro, Miriam</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_069.jpg"
               n="69" xml:id="img_0069"/>

            <head>Waste Not Want Not: Femmage</head>
            <head>An Inquiry into What Women Saved and Assembled</head>

            <byline>Melissa Meyer</byline>
            <byline>Miriam Schapiro</byline>
            <div>               
               <p> Virginia Woolf talks about the loose, drifting material of life, describing how
                  she would like to see it sorted and coalesced into a mold transparent enough to
                  reflect the light of our life and yet aloof as a work of art. <note>1. Virginia
                     Woolf, Self Explorations, Diarists in England and America, Exhibition catalog
                     (New York: 42nd St. Public Library, May 2-September 15, 1977 (excerpted from "A
                     Writer’s Diary").</note> She makes us think of the paper lace, quills and
                  beads, scraps of cloth, photographs, birthday cards, valentines and clippings, all
                  of which inspired the visual imaginations of the women we write about. In the
                  eighteenth century, a nun in a German convent cuts delicate lace from thin
                  parchment and pastes it around minutely detailed paintings of saints. Performing
                  an act of devotion in the service of her God, she makes what later, in the secular
                  world, are called the first valentines.</p>
               <p>An Iroquois woman in 1775 sews five elliptical quillwork designs at the base of a
                  black buckskin bag, quillwork borders at the top and additional moosehair
                  embroidery at the bottom and sides. Hannah Stockton, a New Jersey woman, in 1830
                  dips into her scrap bag in the tradition of waste not want not and finds just the
                  right pieces with which to appliqué her quilt.</p>
               <p>In the 1860s, Lady Filmer photographs the Prince of Wales and his shooting party.
                  Later she cuts up these photos and creates a composition of them in her album,
                  producing the first photocollage. <note>2. Women of Photography, An Historical
                     Survey, Catalog (San Francisco: San Francisco Museum of Art, April 18- June 15,
                     1975).</note></p>
               <p>Rita Reynolds, resident of Southend, England, keeps a scrapbook during World War
                  II. In it she glues birthday cards, valentines and clippings from her local
                  newspaper which record the progress of the war. As the world situation worsens,
                  the scrapbook reflects its gravity.</p>
               <p>
                  <term>Collage</term>: a word invented in the twentieth century to describe an
                  activity with an ancient history. Here are some associated definitions:<lb/>
                  <term>Collage</term>: pictures assembled from assorted materials.<lb/>
                  <term>Collage</term>: a French word after the verb coller which means pasting,
                  sticking or gluing, as in application of wallpaper.<lb/>
                  <term>Assemblage</term>: a collection of things, often combined in the round.<lb/>
                  <term>Assemblage</term>: a specific technical procedure and form used in the
                  literary and musical, as well as the plastic arts, but also a complex of attitudes
                  and ideas . . . collage and related modes of construction manifest a
                  predisposition that is characteristically modern. <note>3. William C. Seitz, The
                     Art of Assemblage (New York: Museum of Modern Art, 1961), p. 10. </note>
                  <lb/>
                  <term>Découpage</term>: (literally, cutting) a mode of decorating painted
                  furniture with cutouts of flowers, fruit, etc. Also, the ar of decorating surfaces
                  with applied paper cutouts.<lb/>
                  <term>Photomontage</term>: the method of making a composite picture by bringing
                  photographs together in a single composition and arranging them, often by
                  superimposing one part on another, so that they form a blended whole.</p>

               <div>
                  <byline>Rita Reynolds</byline>
                  <head>SCRAPBOOK</head>
                  <p>This store-bought scrapbook (circa 1940s) was found in a London Flea Market. On
                     first impression it seems banal, yet there is novelty in its contents:
                     newspaper clippings, decals, some birthday and holiday cards with portions
                     silhouetted (some are left whole) and commercially colored animal pictures.</p>
                  <p> Rita Reynolds, in selecting her pictures, showed what was important to her,
                     revealing her personal priorities. The seemingly unrelated information adds up
                     to pre-war and wartime episodes that make "that loose drifting material of
                     life" in fact coalesce into a work of art. <note>10. Virginia Woolf, 42nd
                        Street Public Library Exhibition (see #1).</note> This, then, is a visual
                     artist equivalent of a diary.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_070.jpg"
               n="70" xml:id="img_0070"/>
            <div>
               <p>
                  <term>Femmage</term>: a word invented by us to include all of the above activities
                  as they were practiced by women using tradi- tional women’s techniques to achieve
                  their art—sewing, piecing, hooking, cutting, appliquéing, cooking and the like
                  -activities also engaged in by men but assigned in history to women.</p>
               <p> Published information about the origins of collage is misleading. Picasso and
                  Braque are credited with inventing it. Many artists made collage before they did,
                  Picasso’s father for one and Sonia Delaunay for another. When art his torians
                  mandate these beginnings at 1912, they exclude artists not in the mainstream. Art
                  historians do not pay atten tion to the discoveries of non-Western artists, women
                  artists or anonymous folk artists. All of these people make up the group we call
                  others. It is exasperating to realize that the rigidities of modern critical
                  language and thought pre vent a direct response to the eloquence of art when it is
                  made by <hi rend="italic">others</hi>.</p>
               <p>Our information on women artist-makers of the past was inspired by the definitive
                  texts on collage written by critics and art historians Herta Wescher, William
                  Seitz, Harriet Janis and Rudi Blesh. We did not find our material in the main body
                  of their works but rather in their introductions and in their notes in the back of
                  their books, indicating they were unable to relax their modernist theories enough
                  to appreciate the diversity, beauty and significance of the original makers of
                  collage. Many of these ancestors were women who were ignored by the politics of
                  art.</p>
               <p>Janis and Blesh put it succinctly: "Collage was once only the simple pleasant fold
                  art or pastime of cutting and pasting bits of paper into pictures or ornamental
                  designs. It was no concern of serious artists. . . . Its origins began so many
                  centuries ago. . . . It is only with this century and the advent of modern art
                  that this quondum delight of schoolgirl and housewife came to the attention of
                  serious artists grappling with revolutionary ideas . . ." <note>4. Harriet Janis
                     and Rudi Blesh, Collage Personalities Concepts Techniques (Philadelphia/New
                     York/London: Chilton Book Co., 1969), p. 3. </note> It is in fact the
                  "schoolgirl" and "housewife" we must look at more carefully to understand the
                  aesthetics of our ancestors and their processes.</p>
               <p>William Seitz includes this information in his work on assemblage: "Valentines,
                  postcards, and folk art of various kinds incorporating pasted elements as well as
                  pictures and objects made of butterfly wings, feathers, shells, etc. were common
                  much earlier. Indeed various stamped letters, passports and official documents can
                  be looked at as a form of unintentional collage." <note>5 Seitz, p. 150, note 5.
                  </note></p>
               <p>Now that we women are beginning to document our culture, redressing our
                  trivialization and adding our information to the recorded male facts and insights,
                  it is necessary to point out the extraordinary works of art by women which despite
                  their beauty are seen as leftovers of history. Aesthetic and technical
                  contributions have simply been overlooked. Here, for example, we are concerned
                  with the authenticity and energy in needlework.</p>

               <div>
                  <byline>Hannah Stockton</byline>
                  <head>LAND AND SEA</head>
                  <p>This unusual quilt does not adhere to any formula for quilt- making. It has no
                     set pattern—block, brick, half drop or dia- mond form; there are no predictable
                     geometric or imagistic formulas here. It appears to be a crazy quilt with a
                     theme.</p>
                  <p>Crazy quilts are made of freely cut pieces of cloth which may seem to be
                     randomly placed. Here the theme is carried out in motifs of land and sea cut
                     from imported English chintz of Oriental design (the technique called <hi
                        rend="italic">broderie perse</hi>).</p>
                  <p>Holstein says, ". . . so popular was this technique that in the early
                     nineteenth century, chintzes were printed with patterns especially designed to
                     be cut out and used for the centers and corners of applique quilts. <note>9.
                        Jonathan Holstein The Pieced Quilt an American Design Tradition, (Greenwich,
                        Conn.: New York Graphics Society, Ltd., 1973), p. 21. </note></p>
                  <p>A 103 inch by 91 inch quilt is a large work. Visual control is as impressive in
                     this work as it is on the small devotional pieces.</p>
               </div>
            </div>

            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_071.jpg"
               n="71" xml:id="img_0071"/>

            <div>
               <p>When it becomes possible to appreciate a sewn object like a quilt (even though it
                  was created for utilitarian pur poses) because it employs thirty stitches to the
                  inch, and uses color which by all standards is rich and evocative, con tains
                  silhouetted forms which are skillfully drawn and connects perfectly measured
                  geometrical units of fabric, then it will be clear that woman’s art invites a
                  methodology of its own.</p>
               <p>Women have always collected things and saved and recycled them because leftovers
                  yielded nourishment in new forms. The decorative functional objects women made
                  often spoke in a secret language, bore a covert imagery. When we read these images
                  in needlework, in paintings, in quilts, rugs and scrapbooks, we sometimes find a
                  cry for help. sometimes an allusion to a secret political alignment, sometimes a
                  moving symbol about the relationships between men and women. We base our
                  interpretations of the layered meanings in these works on what we know of our own
                  lives—a sort of archeological reconstruction and deciphering. We ask ourselves,
                  have we ever used a secret language in our works? Patricia Mainardi, in her essay,
                  says: "Women not only made beautiful and functional objects but expressed their
                  own conviction on a wide variety of subjects in a language for the most part
                  comprehensible only te other women . . . There was more than one man of Tory
                  persuasion who slept unknowingly under his wife’s " Rose Quilt" . . . women named
                  quilts for their political belief . . . at a time when they were not allowed to
                  vote. <note>6. Patricia Mainardi, "Quilts: The Great American Art." Feminist Art
                     Journal, Winter 1973, p. 19.</note></p>
               <p>Collected, saved and combined materials represented for such women acts of pride,
                  desperation and necessity Spiritual survival depended on the harboring of
                  memories. Each cherished scrap of percale, muslin or chintz, each bead, each
                  letter, each photograph, was a reminder of its place in a woman’s life, similar to
                  an entry in a journal or diary. Cynthia Ozick says, . .. a diary is a shoring-up
                  of the ephemeral, evidence that the writer (we substitute artist-maker takes up
                  real space in the world." <note>7. Cynthia Ozick, The Loose Drifting Material of
                     Life," New York Times Book Review, Oct. 2. 1977, p. 41. </note></p>
               <p>Women’s culture is the framework for femmage, and makes it possible for us to
                  understand "combining" as th simultaneous reading of moosehair and beads, cut
                  paper and paint or open-work and stitches. Our female culture also makes it
                  possible to see these traditional aesthetic elements for what they are—the natural
                  materials needed for spiritual, and often physical, survival.</p>
               <p>In the past an important characteristic of femmage was that women worked for an
                  audience of intimates. A woman artist-maker always had the assurance that her work
                  was destined to be appreciated and admired. She worked for her relatives and
                  friends and unless she exhibited in church bazaars and county fairs, her viewers
                  were almost always people she knew. In their book, Joel and Kate Kopp tell about
                  Mrs. Eleanor Blackstone of Lacon, Il linois, who in the years between 1880 and
                  1890 hooked six large rugs, all recording events in the history of her family
                  These rugs show her six children, their pastimes and their pets including actual
                  strands of the children’s hair worked into the individual portraits. <note>8. Joel
                     and Kate Kopp, American Hooked and Sewn Rugs, Folk Art Underfoot, (New York: E.
                     P. Dutton, 1975), p. 72. </note></p>
               <div>
                  <byline>Anonymous Nun</byline>
                  <head>S. JOANNES EV.</head>
                  <p>Works like this paper femmage were made to be carried in a prayer book This
                     devotional work, approximately five inches by two inches, was an homage to a
                     saint that the artist-maker, a nun, wished to honor. In this case St. John the
                     Evangelist sits in his oval surrounded by ornate cut paper simulating lace. The
                     whiteness of the lace is offset by an illusionistic rendering of the saint
                     himself. The cutting exhibits an astonishing capability in the use of knives
                     and scissors as tools. The paper lace is pasted around the painting of the
                     saint and part of it is painted as well.</p>
                  <p>The appeal of these works is their deli cacy and the tour de force of the cut
                     ting. The artist’s process echoes her purpose. The love lavished by this nun on
                     the little object is visible.</p>
               </div>
            </div>

            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_072.jpg"
               n="72" xml:id="img_0072"/>
            <div>
               <p> We feel that several criteria determine whether a work can be called femmage. Not
                  all of them appear in a single object. However, the presence of at least half of
                  them should allow the work to be appreciated as <hi rend="italic"
                  >femmage</hi>.</p>
               <p><hi rend="bold">1.</hi> It is a work by a woman. <hi rend="bold">2.</hi> The
                  activities of saving and collecting are important ingredients. <hi rend="bold"
                     >3.</hi> Scraps are essential to the process and are recycled in the work. <hi
                     rend="bold">4.</hi> The theme has a woman-life context. <hi rend="bold">5.</hi>
                  The work has elements of covert imagery. <hi rend="bold">6.</hi> The theme of the
                  work addresses itself to an audience of intimates. <hi rend="bold">7.</hi> It
                  celebrates a private or public event. <hi rend="bold">8.</hi> A diarist's point of
                  view is reflected in the work. <hi rend="bold">9.</hi> There is drawing and/or
                  handwriting sewn in the work. <hi rend="bold">10.</hi> It contains silhouetted
                  images which are fixed on other material. <hi rend="bold">11.</hi> Recognizable
                  images appear in narrative sequence. <hi rend="bold">12.</hi> Abstract forms
                  create a pattern. <hi rend="bold">13.</hi> The work contains photographs or other
                  printed matter <hi rend="bold">14.</hi> The work has a functional as well as an
                  aesthetic life.</p>
               <p> These criteria are based on visual observation of many works made by women in the
                  past. We have already said that this art has been excluded from mainstream, but
                  why is that so? What is mainstream? How may such an omis sion be corrected?</p>
               <p>The works themselves were without status because the artists who made them were
                  considered inferior by the his torians who wrote about art and culture. Since the
                  works were intimate and had no data or criticism attached to them and were often
                  anonymous, how could these writers identify them as valid, mainstream history!</p>
               <p>Mainstream is the codification of ideas for the illumination of history and the
                  teaching of the young. What a shame that the young remain ignorant of the vitality
                  of women’s art. Yet the culture of women will remain unrecognized un- til women
                  themselves regard their own past with fresh insight. To correct this situation,
                  must we try to insert women’s traditional art into mainstream? How will the
                  authorities be convinced that what they consider low art is worth representing in
                  history? The answer does not lie in mainstream at all, but in sharing women’s
                  information with women.</p>
               <p>Toward this end we have evaluated a selection of women’s art and looked for
                  similar elements which appeared most frequently. As we recorded them, we
                  discovered with pleasure that they presented a form in many guises—a form we call
                  femmage.</p>

               <div>
                  <byline>Lady Filmer</byline>
                  <head>PRINCE OF WALES SHOOTING PARTY</head>
                  <p>Lady Mary Filmer was an early practitioner of photography, a contemporary of
                     the more celebrated Julia Margaret Cameron. But Lady Filmer took photography to
                     another place. She cut, rearranged and pasted her pictures on to album pages,
                     sometimes adding watercolor. Her work pre-dated the papier collé of Picasso and
                     Braque and the photomontages of Hannah Hoch and Raoul Hausmann. In Lady Mary’s
                     circle, most women did fancywork.</p>
                  <p> Today this term is used disparagingly by cultural historians whose aesthetic
                     remains uninformed by wom- en’s culture. In their hierarchical sympathies, they
                     elevate the camera above the crochet needle. Although we believe Lady Filmer’s
                     photocollages were admirable achievements, the other wom en of her time were
                     accomplishing equally interesting work.</p>
               </div>

            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <p>Melissa Meyer is a painter living in NeW York</p>
         <p>Miriam Schapiro is a femmagist from New York.</p>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
