<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TITLE</title>
            <author>AUTHOR</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <pb n="129" facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/refs/heads/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_132.jpg"/>
         <head>The next issues of Heresies:</head>
         
         
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>5</cell>
               <cell>6</cell>
               <cell>7</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>The Great Goddess/Women’s spirituality: Common bondings in the new
                  mythology; ritual and the collective woman; avoiding limitations in our
                  self-defining process; recipes and wisdom from country “spirit women”; the
                  Goddess vs. the patriarchy; the Goddess movement abroad; hostility against
                  and fear of the goddess; original researches; locating the Goddes-temples,
                  museums, digs, bibliographies, maps; the new/old holydays; healing;
                  political implications of the goddess; psychological impact on women of
                  female-centered spirituality. Available May 1978. </cell>
               <cell>Women and Violence: Cultural: violence against women in mass media,
                  literature and art; women’s self-usage ... Family: wife beating; child
                  abuse; sex-violence among lovers and friends...Institutionalized:
                  incarceration in prisons and mental hospitals; repression in traditional
                  religions; racism; imperialism and economic deprivation; torture of
                  political prisoners; sterilization abuse; homophobia; rape... Rebellion:
                  feminism as an act of self-defense; revolutionary struggles; art which
                  expiores violence; art-making as anbringing act... <lb/>Deadline: April 15,
                  1978.</cell>
               <cell>Working together: ‘True Confessions’: An issue to be edited by the
                  HERESIES Publishing Collective, with an emphasis on examining collectivity,
                  work and individuals; an examination of different collective, past and
                  present, white, Third World, lesbian, female/male; women working with women;
                  an explanation of feminist networks, structure and process; the development
                  of feminist criticism; the trial and tribulations of going public; our own
                  view of HERESIES&apos; working process and substantive radical response to
                  the first four issues of HERESIES. Deadline: July 15, 1978. </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         
         <p>Guidelines for Prospective Contributors: Manuscripts should be typewritten,
            double-spaced, on 8 1/2“ x 11“ paper and submitted in duplicate with footnotes and
            illustrative material, if any, fully captioned. We welcome for consideration either
            outlines or description of proposed articles. These are due no later than one month
            prior to the deadline for manuscripts. If you are submitting visual material, please
            send a photograph, xerox or description—not the original. HERESIES will not take
            responsibility for unsolicited original material. Only manuscripts and visual
            material aecompanied by a stamped, self-addresed envelope will be returned. HERESIES
            will pay a fee between $5 and $50, as our budget allows, for published material.
            There will be no commissioned articles and we cannot guarantee acceptance of
            submitted material. We will not include reviews or monographs on contemporary
            women.</p>
         <p> Dear Lesbian issue Collective: <lb/>We appreciate all of the work the Lesbian Arts
            and Artists issue of HERESIES represents. We find it appalling, however, that a
            hundred years from now it will be possible for women to conclude that in 1977 there
            were no practicing Black and other Third World lesbian artists. It is not sufficient
            to explain such grievous omissions merely by stating: “.. yet biases which informed
            our choices of material were certainly conditioned by the fact that we are all
            lesbians, white, college-educated, and mostly middle-class women who live in New
            York and have a background in the arts.” Feminist and lesbian politics and creative
            are not the exclusive property of white women.</p>
         <p>We would like to know if any of the hundreds of contributors you had to choose from
            were Third World women and if so to know more specifically the basis on which their
            work was rejected. <lb/>We look forward to your response. </p>
         <p>Dear Combahee River Collective:
            <lb/> Although we did not systematically exclude Third world women from the Lesbian
            issue of HERESIES, we did participate in a kind of passive exclusion. The editorial
            collective that formed was all white. Our knowledge of the Third World artist or
            lesbian community was limited. By not making a concerted effort to contact Third
            World Lesbian artists we became an only too typical all-White group operating in a
            racist society.</p>
         <p>The inclusion of Third World contributions was based on the same criteria applied to
            all work submitted to the issue. We don’t know exactly how many Black and other
            Third World women submitted work, but we received nothing that specifically dealt
            with being a non-white lesbian artist or which spoke from an identifiably non-White
            position. As far as we know, the work of only one Third World woman was included in
            the issue. It is probable that we didn’t receive much work from Third World
            women.</p>
         <p>HERESIES has had a similar problem with every issue. Most of the editors and
            contributors have been white women. As you may know, each issue of HERESIES is
            edited by a different group of women. Each issue is thematic and any women with an
            interest in that particular topic is welcome to work on the issue. We hope that,
            increasingly, Third World women will want to participate in issues of their
            choice.</p>
         <p>Also, though we haven’t done this yet, if a group of women approaches us with a
            proposal for an issue they want to put out themselves, we will consider giving an
            entire issue to them to produce. A group of women who are already organized, such as
            the Combahee Collective, might want to do an issue devoted to Black and other Third
            World artists. In this way we can begin to extend our publication to speak for many
            feminists who have not been well represented so far.</p>
         <p>As you pointed out, however, it is HERESIES&apos; responsibility to continue to print
            work by and about minority women (including Third World women, lesbian women, etc.)
            in each issue to avoid tokenism.</p>
         <p>We hope this information and your letter will encourage a greater effort on the part
            of both HERESIES editorial collectives and Third World women to enter into an
            exchange. </p>
         <p>HERESIES is planning to publish an issue on Black, Spanish-American, American Indian
            and other Third World women to be edited by Third World women. As with all HERESIES
            issues, the concept, content and design are to be decided solely by its editors. The
            issue, No. 8, is to be published in January 1979. Any Third World woman in the New
            York area who is interested in working on this should contact HERESIES immediately
            so that the core editorial group can form. White us or call (212) 431-9060. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
