<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_046.jpg" n="46" xml:id="img_0046"/>
            <head><title>Excerpts from Women and the Decorative Arts</title></head>
            <byline>Linda Nochlin</byline>
            <p>
               The feminine presence in the field of the decorative arts, more
               specifically, those related to textiles—weaving, embroidery, stitch-
               ery—is a time-honored one.' Indeed, women have continued to
               make significant contributions in this area through the nineteenth
               and twentieth centuries. For example, exhibits—rather conven-
               tional ones, to be sure—of lace, embroidery, tapestry and needle-
               work were prominent among the works illustrated in the official
               publication of Art and Handicraft in the Woman’s Building of the
               World’s Columbian Exposition in Chicago in 1893. Later, the
               leading weavers and tapestry makers at the Bauhaus—Anni Albers,
               Ruth Consemüller, Gunta Stölzl, Otti Berger, Benita Koch-Otte-
               were women.? Nevertheless, this traditional relation, or perhaps
               relegation, of women to the decorative arts was complicated by a
               variety of social and economic as well as ideological factors at the
               turn of this century. One complicating factor was the ambiguous
               status and prestige accorded to the decorative arts themselves,
               especially in relation to the so-called high arts of painting and sculp-
               ture. Another was the complex relationship of the decorative arts to
               the evolution of abstract painting and the subsequent development
               of an abstruse mystique to differentiate the latter from the former.
               Still another factor was the social, political and moral implications
               associated with the promotion of the handicrafts and with education
               in design, especially in Great Britain during the latter part of the
               nineteenth century.</p>
               <p>Have women simply been shunted off into the so-called minor or
               decorative arts because these were considered less demanding and
               were certainly less prestigious? It is undeniable that English womer
               were admitted to the Schools of Design, both the Branch Schools
               and their own Female School in London, long before they were ad-
               mitted, in any significant numbers, to the teaching facilities of the
               Royal Academy. The ranks of these schools were swelled not merely
               by the working-class girls for whom this sort of training, aimed
               primarily at industrial design, was originally intended, but by vast
               crowds of impoverished young ladies who were in desperate straits
               trying to find employment in the arts, primarily as governesses."
               Even earlier, in France, Mme. Frere de Montyon, a student of Res-
               tout’s, had founded the Ecole Gratuite de Dessin pour les Jeunes
               Personnes, a school established in 1805 to help penniless voung
               women become self-supporting, an enterprise perhaps intended as
               much to aid public morals as to encourage artistic ability. The Ecole
               Gratuite de Dessin was brought under government jurisdiction in
               1810.4</p>
               <p>The democratizing effort to extend knowledge of the applied arts
               to the lower classes—and to women—was carried further in subse
               quent attempts to break down completely the barriers between high
               art and the decorative arts. The attempt reached a climax in Great
               Britain during the late nineteenth century with the program of social
               transformation proposed by John Ruskin and, especially, by
               William Morris. Interestingly enough, women seem to have served
               little more than a purely inspirational function for Morris and his
               followers, although both Janey and May Morris produced em-
               broidery for the cause of arts and crafts. Women in late nineteenth-
               century England certainly made contributions to porcelain painting
               textiles, embroidery, and, often anonymously, to patchwork and
               other forms of stitchery, and of course Kate Greenaway was active
               as an illustrator and tile-designer, influencing Gauguin and many
               other painters. Nevertheless, women as a group were not prominent
               in the English Arts and Crafts Movement. In Scotland, however
               two unusually gifted and productive sisters, Frances Macdonald
               (1874-1921) and Margaret Macdonald (1865-1933) made majoi
               contributions in design. Margaret later married the innovative
               architect and designer Charles Rennie Mackintosh, and as mem-
               bers of his circle both sisters created imaginative curvilinear designs
               for architectural ornaments, metalwork, embroideries and stained
               glass, as well as watercolors that often hover on the brink of
               abstraction.</p>
            <p>
               Although the effort to overthrow the hegemony of “high art” by
               merging it with the “minor” arts, an effort that has characterized
               one current of vanguard ideology from Synthetism to Constructiv-
               ism, is by no means a feminine invention, the extent to which the
               decorative arts, especially those involving textiles, have played a role
               in the careers of advanced women artists is striking. Yet even
               though their achievements in these realms are often brilliant, the
               fact that painters like Nataliia Goncharova, Alexandra Exter.
               Liubov Popova and Varvara Stepanova, Sophie Taeuber-Arp and
               Vanessa Bell, Marguerite Zorach and Sonia Delaunay were in-
               volved in textile design, weaving, tapestry making and costume
               design nevertheless has equivocal implications. On the one hand, for
               a woman artist to “return, as it were, to her traditional role in the
               minor arts, generally less conducive to fame and fortune than a ca-
               reer in painting or sculpture, can be viewed as a retrograde step. Yet
               from another vantage point, we can say that advanced women art-
               ists involved in the decorative arts in the early twentieth century
               were contributing to the most revolutionary directions—both social
               and aesthetic—of their times.</p>
              <p> Marguerite Zorach may indeed have turned from painting to em-
               broidering tapestries after the birth of her second child, when she
               "no longer had the hours of uninterrupted concentration that she re
               quired to work out her personal views on canvas,”5 and Sonia De-
               launay may have moved from monumental Orphist canvases to fab-
               ric and dress design in order to support her husband and herself
               after the loss of her private income following the Russian Revolu-
               tion. Nevertheless it is also true that Zorach’s needlework, in many
               ways more original and interesting than her paintings, received
               more exposure and critical attention than her canvases during the
               1920s and ’30s,° and that Delaunay had had considerable success in
               the applied arts before the loss of her income’ and continued to
               make some of her most original contributions in this area through-
               out her career. Certainly the experiences of Sophie Taeuber-Arp
               and Vanessa Bell in the decorative arts exerted a progressive influ
               ence on their “high art” creations. Taeuber-Arp, who began as a
               textile specialist and taught weaving and embroidery at the Arts and
               Crafts School in Zurich, may well have influenced her husband
               Jean Arp, in the direction of greater abstraction as a result of the
               embroidery and weaving they did together at the time of the First
               World War. Indeed, it was probably precisely because of her back-
               ground in the decorative arts that Taeuber-Arp was one of the first
               artists to think of abstraction as a natural point of departure rather
               than the end of a long process of evolution from representation.
               Vanessa Bell’s participation from 1913 to 1919 in Roger Fry’s
               Omega Workshops, for which she designed screens, textiles and mo-
               saics, seems to have intensified her penchant for abstract colorism
               and bold surface treatment which had already been stimulated by
               contact with the Fauves and Cubists.9</p>
               <p>In attempting to evaluate women artists’ contributions to the
               decorative arts, much depends on one’s attitude toward the relative
               importance of the “high versus the “applied” arts. If we consider
               painting the ultimate form of aesthetic expression, then it will be a
               foregone conclusion that Sonia Delaunay made a sacrifice by ne-
               glecting her monumental abstract canvases to produce fabrics and
               fashions, while her husband, Robert Delaunay, was permitted to
               continue his calling as a painter and, perhaps even more important,
               as a theorist of abstract art. If, however, we take a less conventiona
               view of what constitutes value in the avant-garde production of the
               twentieth century, we can see that women artists, by remaining
               faithful to their time-honored role as decorative artists, have ad-
               vanced the cause of abstraction and, at the same time, spread its
               message beyond the walls of the studio, museum and gallery into the
               realm of daily life—a goal devoutly sought by artists—whether
               high” or “applied, male or female—from the time of Ruskin and
               Morris to the Russian Revolution, the Bauhaus and afterwards.</p>
               <p>From Ann Sutherland Harris and Linda Nochlin, Women Artists: 1550-1950. Reprint-
               ed by permission from the Los Angeles County Museum of Art and Alfred A. Knopf.</p>
               <p>1. See Women Artists, pp. 15-17<lb/>
               2. Although women may have traditionally been involved in handweaving and art
               weaving, this is by no means true as far as industrial or mass-production of cloth is
               concerned.<lb/>
               3. Q. Bell, The Schools of Design, London, 1963, pp. 135-137.<lb/>
               4. Rosa Bonheur’s father took over the directorship in 1848, and his daughter, the
               following year. The school was headed by Mlle. Nelly Marandon de Montyel after
               1860. I am grateful to Professor Albert Boime for much of this information.<lb/>
               5. National Collection of Fine Arts, Marguerite Zorach: The Early Years, 1908-1920,
               1973, p. 50. The artist was joined briefly in her tapestry work by her husband, William
               Zorach<lb/>
               6. Ibid., p. 5<lb/>
               7. A. A. Cohen, Sonia Delaunay, New York, 1975, p. 77.<lb/>
               8. See Taeuber-Arp bibliography in Women Artists.<lb/>
               9. See Bell bibliography in Women Artists.</p>
            <p>
               Linda Nochlin is Professor of Art History at Vassar Gollege.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
