<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Afro Carolinian “Gullah” Baskets</title>
            <author>Howardena Pindell</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <pb n="22" facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/refs/heads/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_025.jpg"/>
         
         <head>Afro Carolinian “Gullah” Baskets</head>
         <div>
            <p>Each black family has its oral history passed down / written door remembering the
               cruelties and atrocities under slavery, reconstruction, on through the present.
               My father tells me of my great grandmother, a slave in Maryland who was blinded
               in one eye by the lash of a whip. I include the adjacent eyewitness accounts
               because I feel there is amnesia concerning the day-to-day fine point of the more
               unpleasant aspects of America history. I find it difficult to imagine any group
               of people having the positive motivation to create under the conditions of
               slavery. Black men were apprenticed in male gender related crafts such as
               cabinetmaking, blacksmithing, silversmithing although laws were passed to
               prevent them from outnumbering whites. I say were frequently not allowed to sign
               their work nor were written accounts in their name generally made of their
               transactions. The &quot;Gullah&quot; people lived in the 17 and 1800&apos;s
               between Mt. Pleasant, Sea Islands, and Sullivan&apos;s Island, South Carolina.
               (The word &quot;gullah&quot; is derived from Angola, Africa.) People from the
               Senegambia region and the Congo-Angola region made up 70% the area&apos;s
               population, slipped from Africa between 1752 and 1808. The women brought from
               the Sene-gambia region of Africa (Gambia to Sierra Leone) continued the
               traditionally female gender related craft of basketweaving usng West African
               coiling techniques incorporating indigenous materials such as marshgrass,
               palmetto leaves, and long leaf pine. Replicas of these baskets are sold today at
               the Old Slave Mart in Charleston. South Carolina.</p>
            <p>African traditional crafts were, unfortunately, lost in my family and replaced by
               Anglo-American crafts.... Aunts, my mothers sisters, crochet and my father
               taught me how to knit. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p>&quot;An honorable friend, who stands high in the state and in the nation,” was
               present at the burial of a female slave in Mississippi, who had been whipped to
               death at the stake by her master, because she was gone longer of an errand to
               the neighboring town than her master thought necessary. Under the lash she
               protested that she was ill, and was obliged to rest in the fields. To complete
               the climax of horror, she was delivered of a dead infant while undergoing the
               punishment.&quot;</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p>Mr. GIDDINGS, member of Congress from Ohio, his speech in the House of
               Representatives, Feb. 13, 1839, made the following statement: &quot;On the
               beautiful avenue in front of the Capitol, members of Congress, during this
               session have compelled to turn aside from their path, to permit a coftle of
               slaves, males and females, chained to each other by their necks, to pass on
               their way to this national slave market.&quot; </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> Rev. JAMES NOURSE, a Presbyterian clergyman of Mifflin co. Penn., whose father
               is, we believe, a slaveholder in Washington City, says, “The Rev. Mr. M—, now of
               the Hunting- don Presbytery, after an absence of many months, was about visiting
               his old friends on what is com- monly called the Eastern Shore.&apos; Late in
               the afternoon, on his journey, he called at the house of Rev. A. C. of P —town,
               Md. With this bro- ther he had been long acquainted. Just at that juncture Mr.
               C. was about preceeding to whip a colored female, who was his slave. She wa
               firmly tied to a post in FRONT of his dwelling house. The arrival of a clerical
               Visitor at such time, occasioned a temporary delay in the execut- tion of Mr.
               C.&apos;s purpose. But the delay was only temporary; for not even the presence
               of such a guest could destroy the bloody design. &apos;The guest interceded with
               all the mildness yet earnestness of a brother and new visitor. But all in vain,
               &quot;the woman had been SAUCY and must be punish- ed.&apos; The cowhide was
               accordingly produced, and the Rev. Mr. C, a large and very slout man, ap- plied
               it &apos;manfully&apos;on &apos;woman&apos;s&apos; bare and &apos;shrink- ing
               flesh.&apos; I say bare, because you know that the slave women generally have
               but three or four inches of the arm near the shoulder covered, and the neck is
               left entirely exposed. As the cow- hide moved back and forward, striking right
               and left, on the head, neck and arms, at every few strokes the sympathizing
               guest would exclaim, &apos;O, brother C. desist.&apos; But brother C. pursued
               his brutal work, till, after inflicting about sixty lashes, the woman was found
               to be suffused with blood on the hinder part of her neck, and under her frock
               between the shoulders. Yet this Rev. gentleman is well esteemed in the
               church—was, three or four years since, moderator of the synod of Philadelphia,
               and yet walks abroad, feeling himself unrebuked by law or gospel. Ah, sir </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> The following letter was sent by Capt. JACOB DUNHAM, of New York City, to a
               slaveholder in Georgetown, D.C. more than twenty years since: &quot;Georgetown,
               June 13, 1815. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> &quot;Dear sir—Passing your house yesterday, I beheld a scene of cruelty seldom
               witnessed; that was the brutal chantisement of your negro girl, lasked to a
               ladder and beaten in an inhuman man¬ ner, too bad to describ. My blood chills
               while I contemplate the subject. This has led me to in¬ vestigate your character
               from your neighbons who inform me that you have caused the death o one negro
               man, whom you struck with a sledge for some trivial fault—that you have beaten
               ano¬ ther black girl with such severity that the splint ers remained in her back
               for some weeks after you sold her—and many other acts of barbarity, too lengthy
               to enumerate. And to my great sur¬ prise, I find you are a professor of the
               Christian religion!</p>
            <p>“You will naturally inquire, why I middle with your family affairs. My answer is,
               the cause of humanity and a sense of my duty requires it.— With these hosty
               remarks I leave you to reflect on the subject; but wish you to remember, that
               there is an all-soeing eye who knows all our fault and will reward us according
               to our deeds. I remain, sir, yours, &amp;c. JACOB DUNHAM Master of the brig
               Cyrus, of N. Y. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> The preceding are but a few of a large num- ber of similar cases contained in
               the foregoing tes- timonies. The slaveholder mentioned by Mr Ladd, p. 86, who
               knocked down a slave and af- terwards piled brush upon his body, and consum- ed
               it, held the hand of a female slave in the fire till it was burned so as to be
               useless for life, and confessed to Mr. Ladd, that he had killed four slaves, had
               been a member of the Senate of Geor- gia and a clergyman. “A non-professor of
               religion, in Campbell county, Ky. sold a female and two children to a Methodist
               professor, with the proviso that they should not leave that region of country.
               The slave-drivers came, and offered $50 more for the woman than he had given,
               and he sold her. She is now in the lower country, and her orphan babes are in
               Kentucky. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> From the &quot;Macon (Georgia) Messenger,&quot; Jan. 16, 1839. &quot;Ranaway
               from the subscriber, two negroes, Davis, a man about 45 years old ; also Peggy,
               his wife, near the same age. Said negroes will probably make their way to
               Columbia county, as they have children living in that county. I will liberally
               reward any person who may deliver them to me. NEHEMIAH KING.” From
               the“Petersburg (Va.) Constellation, June 27, 1837. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> &quot;Ranaway, a negra man, named Peter. He has a wife at the plantation of Mr.
               C. Haws, near Suffolk, where it is supposed he is still lurking. JOHN L. DUNN
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> The two following facts are stated upon the authority of the Rev. Joseph G.
               Wilson, pastor of the Presbyterian Church in Salem, Washington co., Indiana.</p>
            <p>“In Bath co., Kentucky, Mr. L., in the year &apos;32 or &apos;33, while
               intoxicated, in a fit of rage whip- ped a female slave until she fainted and
               fell on the fioor. Then he whipped her to get up; then with red hot tongs he
               burned off her ears, and whipped her again! but all in vain. He then or- dered
               his negro men to carry her to the cabinet There she was found dead next morning.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> &quot;I cannot,&quot; says the doctor, &quot;forget my feel- ings on visiting a
               hospital belonging to the plant- ation of a gentleman highly esteemed for his
               vir- tues, and whose manners and conversation ex- pressed much benevolence and
               conscientiousness. When I entered with him the hospital, the first object on
               which my eye fell was a young woman very ill, probably approaching death. She
               was stretched on the floor. Her head restored on some- thing like a pillow, but
               her body and limbs were extended on the hard hoards. The owner, I doubt not,
               had, at least, as much kindness as myself; but he was so used to see the slaves
               living with- out common comforts, that the idea of unkind- ness in the present
               instance did not enter his mind.’ </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> Howardena Pindell 1974, N.Y. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> "Rev. Joseph Hough, a Baptist minister, formerly of Springfield, Mass, now of
               Plainfield, N.H. while traveling the south, a few years ago, put up one night
               with a Methodist family, and spent the Sabbath with them. While there, one of
               the female slaves did something which displeased her mistress. She took a chisel
               and mallet, and very deliberately cut off on eof her toes." </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p> "Rev. Dr. Staughton, formerly of Philadelphia, often stated, that while he lived
               at Georgetown, S.C. he could tell the doings of one of the slaveholders of the
               Baptist church there by his pyrayers, at the prayer meeting. 'If,' said he,
               'that man was upon good terms wiht his slaves, his words were cold and heartless
               as frost; if he had been whipping a man, he would pray with life; but if he had
               left a woman whom he had been flogging, tied to a post in his cellar, with a
               determination to go back and torture again, O! how he would pray!' The Rev.
               Cyrus P. Grosvenor of Massachusetts can confirm the above statement by Dr.
               Staughton.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <p> Howardena Pindell is an artist and a founding member of A.I.R. Gallery in New York
            City </p>
      </back>
      
   </text>
</TEI>
