<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TITLE</title>
            <author>AUTHOR</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_031.jpg"
               n="31" xml:id="img_0031"/>

            <head><title>Political Fabrications: Women’s Textiles in 5 Cultures</title></head>
            <byline>
               <persName>Jean Feinberg</persName>
               <persName>Lenore Goldberg</persName>
               <persName>Julie Gross</persName>
               <persName>Bella Lieberman</persName>
               <persName>Elizabeth Sacre</persName>
            </byline>
            <p> We have been meeting collectively for many months, exploring the political
               dimensions of women’s traditional artmaking. Our focus was on textiles and the women
               who made them from five cultures – Navajo, Northwest Coast Chilkat Indian, New
               Zealand Maori, pre-conquest Peruvian and Western European. We wanted to clarify
               relationships between the social/political position of women and the status of their
               textile making in these societies.</p>

            <p> Our notion of collectivity began vaguely and was gradually clarified. We wanted to
               tolerate tensions and individual voices. Even though each of us has contributed
               individually to this effort, what we wrote was the outcome of collective debate. This
               form has had everything to do with our content. Women’s history has been
               characterized by the systematic denial of access to analytic modes of exploring
               situations. We joined a long tradition of women who worked together offering each
               other support and intimacy. What we intensified was a critical and intellectual
               dimension which became, in time, indistinguishable from the emotional dimension.</p>
            <p>The first part of this piece describes our filters—our articulation of the political
               dimensions of art and aesthetics and our reasons for exploring women’s traditional
               arts. Our individual explications of women and textiles in five cultures follow. We
               conclude with several theoretical speculations prompted by our research and our
               collective process.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>Toward a definition of the politics of art and aesthetics</head>
            <p>Women’s traditional art has been defined as craft or “low” art. This ascribed status
               of women’s art is political. To understand why women’s art has been considered in
               this way is a vital political act.</p>
            <p>Aesthetics, theory making about art, has been given to us as though it were
               value-free, objective and not grounded in a particular historical moment. According
               to us, art and art theories are mediated by those groups who dominate the social
               sphere and have greater access to power. In general, when Westem theorists have
               reported on traditional societies, their cultural and sexist biases have interfered.
               Thus, in order to understand what traditional art is, we are forced to state what it
               is not. It is not the work of a formative period of culture, not a late or stagnant
               phase of development, not the work of children, naives or mentally ill people. It is
               not technologically crude or inept. Traditional arts have been considered all of
               these.</p>
            <p>The Western notion of “primitivism” should not be confused with the artistic
               expression of fully developed cultures of the pretechnological world. Within these
               cultures, although women’s art is skillfully made and present in all aspects of life,
               it has largely been ignored by Westem theorists. Its artistic qualities have not been
               recognized and its possible meanings have not been explored.</p>
            <p>Through our research we discovered another bias to be explored. Males within
               traditional cultures have, because of their political and social power, tended to
               define what is valuable in art. By becoming aware of how biases shape the formulation
               of aesthetic theories, we can reveal the political nature of aesthetics.</p>
         </div>

         <pb
            facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_032.jpg"
            n="32" xml:id="img_0032"/>
         <div>
            <head>Personal sources for our exploration</head>
            
               <p>My interest in women’s traditional arts originated in a need to connect personally
                  and historically with women who had the desire to enrich utilitarian objects.
                  Although relegated to forms of expression bounded by their homes and bodies, women
                  engendered works informed by an analytic and intuitive but not a High Art
                  sensibility. I wanted to understand why the creative expression of women was
                  usually channeled into crafts. Because I felt so connected to these works of art,
                  I questioned that designation altogether. In particular, I wanted to look behind
                  the ephemeral appearance of lace to see what answers and paradoxes would be
                  there. <persName>B.L.</persName></p>               
            
               <p> Because I am still struggling with the myth of male superiority in art, 1 was
                  instinctively drawn to a women’s art form which embodied a sensual, visual beauty.
                  My incentive to investigate these textiles was generated by the barrenness which
                  characterizes the dehumanized products of modern technology. I questioned the
                  place assigned to these domestic, utilitarian objects by male- politicized
                  aesthetics. If I could not find validation, I sought at least more factual
                  information regarding their origins and the context in which they were made and
                  seen. I came to feel it was necessary to find female antecedents in art and that
                  the lack of a woman’s history cuts us off from our own dreams and aspirations.
                  Without a knowledge of our own history, whether in this culture or others, we are
                  limited in the extent to which we may excel. <persName>J.F.</persName></p>
                           
               <p> As an artist in this eclectic age, my interest in women’s traditional arts is
                  filtered through exotic, romantic notions of other cultures. I am interested in
                  how cultural frameworks affect art and aesthetics. Primitive artists have been
                  described as reflecting the style of their culture rather than having an
                  individual style. I wanted to explore that idea with particular reference to
                  women. I wondered how women’s distance from the power centers of traditional
                  cultures related to their styles of artmaking and choices of materials. I
                  questioned whether women artists had as their purpose the expression of their
                  culture’s basic conservatism or if they sought to change it. <persName>L.G.</persName></p>
                           
               <p>My earliest responses to the traditional art of women were contradictory. I wanted
                  to celebrate women who, despite natural and man-made constraints, have been
                  creative in the transformation of various media. 1 also wanted to understand the
                  historical forces that have tried to colonize women’s fantasies, limiting them in
                  their choice of media, iconography and access to an audience, and how these
                  limitations have related to restrictions in other spheres of their lives. A
                  historical understanding of women and art is prerequisite to a meaningful
                  encounter with the contemporary culture of women. <persName>E.S.</persName></p>
                          
               <p>Studying women’s artmaking in traditional societies, I had a sense that certain
                  core needs were fulfilled by many kinds of activities, whether or not the product
                  of these activities was called art or craft. Both categories seem to embody these
                  needs – manual/tactile, conceptual, creative/transformative—in the making as well
                  as the experiencing of these objects. “Icing” a canvas or icing a cake, shaping a
                  bowl or painting flesh, weaving a blanket or looking to that blanket as
                  inspiration, can all be seen as examples of these needs in practice. <persName>J.G.</persName></p>               
         
         <div>

            <head> Peru</head>
            <p>In Peru textiles were produced as early as 2500 B.C. They served as the major vehicle
               for abstract social and religious expression until the end of the Inca state in 1532
               A.D. Textile styles developed throughout the successive Peruvian cultures of Paracas,
               Chavin, Nazca, Tiahuanaco-Wari, Chimu and Inca, and continue today. For almost 5,000
               years, until the Spanish conquest, Peruvian textiles enjoyed an uninterrupted freedom
               from foreign influence. Thus a clear, strong indigenous style evolved.</p>
            <p>Most accounts attribute this activity to women by implicit assumption, not stating it
               as actual fact, which suggests that to formally attribute to women a cultural legacy
               of such artistry and expertise is to go out on a limb and to risk being dismissed as
               biased and unscholarly. One prominent authority, in a classic essay on Peruvian
               textiles, indicates the weaver’s sex only once by using the pronoun “she” to clarify
               a sentence at the end of the article’s seventeen pages. However, reports and
               excavated artifacts exist 

            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_033.jpg"
               n="33" xml:id="img_0033"/>

            which confirm that Peruvian spinning and weaving was predominantly a woman’s art.
               Spindles, pottery and cloth dolls portraying women weavers (sometimes with a male
               overseer) have been found at gravesites. Early Spanish chronicles and contemporary
               accounts also describe women’s prevalent role as weavers.</p>
            <p>The sandy soil and dry climate of coastal Peru have preserved ancient textiles well.
               Despite extremely simple technology the level of manufacture was very high, with
               variations impossible to duplicate today on machine-powered looms. Peruvian spinners
               could produce yarn of great fineness and consistency, measuring 1/250th of an inch in
               diameter, thus enabling the weaver to produce a textile as tightly woven as 250
               threads per inch. These women dealt with more than a simple grid structure. Technical
               ingenuity was shown in the variety of twined, embroidered and knitted threads
               creating rich surfaces and detailed motifs. Patterning began about 1800 B.C. with the
               techniques of brocade, tapestry, double-cloth and pattern weave being invented and
               often brilliantly combined. Subtle and varied color combinations from vegetable and
               mineral dyes existed from Paracas times onward.</p>
            <p>Early cotton fabrics made by weft-twining were replaced when a loom with heddles was
               introduced which expanded an annual production to tens of thousands of square meters
               of textile and implemented the use of llama, alpaca and vicuna wool. Despite their
               basic rectilinear shape, weavings were put to uses as varied as ponchos, mantles,
               wall hangings and mummy wrappings. As much as 200 pounds of textiles, depending on
               the person’s wealth, were accumulated for burials. In life as well as in death,
               possession of fine textiles symbolized status. Sex, age, marital status and
               occupation were also signified by wearing textiles of a certain color, size, material
               or motif.</p>
            <p>Accounts after the Incan empire was conquered chronicled textiles’ social
               significance. A wife’s desirability was measured by the quality of her weaving. Wives
               of one household would compete as to who embroidered the best blanket. At Incan
               weddings husbands gave brides a fine cloth to indicate their joint control of the new
               household. Incan initiations required four clothing changes, to be woven in a single
               day by the initiate’s mother and sisters.</p>
            <p>A textile’s sacred quality was heightened by the compression and “density” of energy
               in the garments being transferred to the wearer. Incan shrines of venerated female
               ancestors included their spindles, handfuls of cotton and unfinished webs of tapestry
               as offerings or for keeping fingers busy in the next world. These tools were
               protected in case of an eclipse, when it was thought a comet would destroy the moon,
               a female sybol. The spindles would then be in danger of turning into snakes, the
               looms into bears and jaguars.</p>
            <p>Throughout Peru’s history, the distinguished quality of tapestry tunics, mantles and
               diaphanous gauzes made part-time weaving unlikely for those engaged in multiple
               household duties. This indicates the existence of a class of specialist spinners,
               dyers and weavers. All peasants under the Incan empire were required to work and
               weave for state needs during two-thirds of the year. At first both men and women spun
               and wove to satisfy their obligation to the state. Houses were organized for
               specialized guilds called the aklla, weaving or “chosen” women. Aged or infirm men,
               exempted from mitta, labor services, made ropes, slings, nets or sacks.</p>
            <p>Under Spanish colonialism any artisan manufacture competing with goods of the mother
               country was initially suppressed. The Spanish introduced a new weaving technology.
               Today men still use medieval Spanish looms, while Andean women hand spin and weave on
               indigenous looms and follow original patterns, although their weavings lack the
               earlier intricacy and subtlety. Factory-produced textiles are also manufactured. A
               strong textile workers’ federation in the 1940s defended the rights of women, despite
               the fact that female suffrage was not legal until 1955. This union caused Peru to be
               the only country with a large textile industry to legally prohibit sex discrimination
               in wages. The history of Peru documents a long tradition of superlative textile art
               made by women. These works emerged as the product of traditional cultural values.
               Peruvian weavers were ingenious and dexterous; they utilized natural materials
               sensitively in what now seems a simpler and temporally slower reality. Within a
               society with rigidly defined sex roles, women lacked many options. Weaving
               paradoxically served to focus their vision and allowed their inner resources to be
               realized. Complexity and beauty glow in the work, which resists grandiosity as false
               and alien. These works, in which women wrapped and shaped the history of Peru, are
               true to themselves.</p>
            <byline>J.G.</byline>
         </div>

         <pb
            facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_034.jpg"
            n="34" xml:id="img_0034"/>
         <div>
            <head>New Zealand Maori</head>
            <p>In the beginning, Rangi-nui (sky father) and Papa-tua-nuku (earth mother) embraced.
               Their love produced 70 supernatural beings who, embodied in natural phenomena, were
               everyday deities. Tane, the oldest child, convinced his brothers and sisters to force
               their parents apart so that the earth could have light. In this way he became the god
               of light and took the form of the sun. Tane wanted to create a race of mortals for
               the earth, and he began a wide search for uha, the female element. In his wandering,
               he reached the twelfth heaven where he sought the aid of 1o, supreme god. lo’s
               attendants sent him to Kurawaka, the pubic region of his mother Papa. There he
               created a woman from mud and earth, breathing on the inanimate figure until she came
               to life.</p>
            <p>Such myths simultaneously reflected and created the status and treatment of women in
               New Zealand Maori society. Man was considered the sacred provider of life-giving
               elements while woman was regarded as his profane, passive receptacle; men were
               associated with life and strength, women with death and destruction. Female
               reproductive organs were called the “house of misfortune and disaster.” Distinctions
               between men and women colored every aspect of life in Maori society: the right side
               of the body was male and vital, the left female and degraded. These designations had
               tactical implications in battle and were used to explain good and bad fortune. Women
               were excluded from access to esoteric knowledge and ceremonial rituals because they
               were not tapu (sacred). Only highborn men could become tohunga (priests) and only
               tohunga knew Io. Women knew only lo’s familiar manifestations. Nevertheless, women
               had their own rituals: they greeted the reappearance of certain
               constellations—Pleiades (Maori new year) and Canopus (first frost)—with song and
               dance. The moon, regarded by women as their true husband, was similarly welcomed.</p>
            <p>A distinct sexual division of labor began after birth when children were dedicated to
               masculine and feminine roles. When the sacredness of an activity might be destroyed
               by the presence of women, these tasks were done by men. When the sacredness of men
               might be degraded by doing certain tasks, these were done by women. In practice, this
               meant that men’s tasks were physically dangerous and seen as challenging: hunting,
               open-sea fishing, tattooing and carving wood and greenstone. Women’s tasks followed
               the rhythm of domesticity: collecting food, water and firewood, cultivating and
               preparing flax, weaving and offering hospitality through singing and dancing.</p>
            <p>Women’s decorative impulse found form in the taniko designed borders of the cloaks
               they wove. Weaving was the last stage in a complicated, arduous, even painful process
               which began with the cultivation of flax and continued through the scraping,
               plaiting, pounding and rolling of flax fibers into twine. Girl children learned early
               that they were destined to become weavers. As babies, their first thumb joint was
               bent outwards in anticipation of certain tasks. As children, they played to the
               accompaniment of ditties like: “The woman with nimble hands and feet, marry her; The
               woman who chatters, cast her out” and “Who will marry a woman too lazy to weave
               garments?</p>
            <p>By the age of nine or ten, girls began complex and ritualized training. They were
               made <hi rend="italic">tapu</hi> through a ritual, sitting inactive while a male
               instructor recited a charm. They were then instructed to bite into the upper part of
               the right weaving stick which was tapu (masculine). Until their first sampler was
               finished, they were not allowed to communicate with anyone other than the priest or
               instructor. Eating sow thistle removed the <hi rend="italic">tapu</hi>.</p>
            <p>Flax was woven on primitive looms consisting of two sticks in the ground. Taniko
               elements included triangles, chevrons, diamonds and hourglass shapes; the predominant
               colors were red, black, white and yellow. Feathers were used decoratively in the
               weaving of garments, kiwi feathers being highly valued, parrot feathers adding bright
               color. Since they were inserted as the garment was woven, the overall pattern had to
               be kept in mind. Sometimes, hard strips of flax were curled into tubular forms and
               hung from a band. This produced a rattling sound during dancing, serving as the
               unique percussive instrument in Maori culture.</p>
            <p>Carving was forbidden to women; weaving was open to men. Women used only the taniko
               patterns in their decoration. Men used the taniko patterns in carving a single
               wallboard (heke tipi) high above the house porch, but typical male iconography
               directly represented feared or revered aspects of their environment: stylized human
               figures, mythic long-tongued sea monsters, lizards and ancestors. Even the more
               abstract male patterns were related to such elements in their surroundings as sea
               waves, hammerhead sharks, ferns and sand flounder.</p>

            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_035.jpg"
               n="35" xml:id="img_0035"/>
            <p> Both male and female designs were subject to strict rules; although there were
               accepted evaluative criteria such as symmetry, rhythm and dramatic use of color,
               designs were not copied and within formal constraints originality was expected.
               Although choices of material and iconography were socially defined for both sexes,
               men enjoyed more latitude. If art is that which approximates the autonomous, then
               there was a curious freedom in the restricted iconography of women, since the
               abstract elements of taniko were not reality dictated. But men could use taniko too.
               Since they also had access to schools of weaving, even if they rarely exercised the
               option, role flexibility was greater for them. Men’s political and religious power
               enabled them to structure language and assign values in Maori society. The actual
               reciprocity on which the society was based was not acknowledged. Maori mythology
               reinforced the ideology of male superiority which devalued the tasks and art produced
               by women.</p>
            <byline>E.S.</byline>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>The Chilkat</head>
            <p>North of Oregon, south of Alaska, is a coastal area abundant with game, fish and
               vegetation. Here in the late 18th and 19th centuries lived a subgroup of the Tlingit
               tribe—the Chilkats. Their neighbors were the Tshimshian, Kwakiutl and Haida, with
               whom they traded, fought and intermarried.</p>
            <p>Basic survival needs could be met with relative ease among the Chilkats because of
               the lush environment. The Chilkat society was a chiefdom, based economically on the
               redistribution of goods within a network of family groups linked through matrilineal
               descent. Resources were owned communally, while special highly decorated objects were
               accumulated to give prestige to heads of the individual clans. Among these objects
               was a type of shawl or robe, popularly referred to as a “blanket.</p>
            <p>The story is told that a Chilkat bride of a Tshimshian chief learned the art of
               making cedarbark dance aprons and leggings. When she died, a dance apron was sent
               home to her relatives, who unraveled it in order to understand how it was made. They
               began then to make blankets in the same fashion, although eventually they became far
               better-known as weavers than the Tshimshian.</p>
            <p>Blankets were woven with yarn spun from mountain-goat wool with a core of yellow
               cedarbark twine. Men hunted the goats and made the half-loom ; Women spun and dyed
               the yarn black, blue, yellow and white from hemlock, copper and vegetable dyes. In
               all instances women were the weavers. They set up the loom and tied off the warp
               bundles to form a shallow curve along the lower edge of the blanket. While in certain
               cases they copied patterns painted on boards by men, in others they designed their
               own weaving patterns. There were two distinct styles of Chilkat blankets. The first
               was abstract with chevrons, stripes, enclosing borders and squares. This was the
               women’s style. The second, the men s'style, was representational using signs or
               symbols for man, animals and water life.</p>
            <p>The abstract and representational styles shared many characteristics. In addition to
               the unique curved shape of the lower edge, the visual field in both is highly active
               and extremely dense, although the mode of expression looks dissimilar.</p>
            <p>The male-style blankets reflected men’s foraging activities through bilateral
               symmetry and x-ray and transparent portrayals of animal motifs. The blanket,
               organized by a central panel and two flanking sides, was itself like a flayed animal
               skin. Because of the Chilkat’s desire for design density, the overlay of motifs
               sometimes made interpretation of the blankets difficult, if not impossible. The
               animal characteristics portrayed were often determined by a dream that the male
               artist or the patron had. As designers of the representational blankets, men brought
               their dreamlife into the waking world as a record of their encounters with the
               supernatural. We have no such record of the women’s dreams.</p>
            <p>Women were prohibited from creating designs involving life forms, so that while
               simultaneously producing men’s blankets, women wove their own using a purely abstract
               design system. Variation of visual elements, contrast of yarn color and variety of
               texture created blankets with strong graphic and sensual impact. The geometric
               patterns with alternating areas of linear density created a rhythmic variation which
               broke the uniformity of the field. Design in the women’s style was even denser than
               in the men’s. By filling the space from edge to edge, the weavers virtually
               eliminated any illusion of shallow planar recession. Instead, they created an
               advancing plane by the addition of wool and bark fringes protruding from the body of
               the robes which emphasized the flatness and frontality of the surface conception.
               Instead of the dreamlike meditations implied in the men’s blankets, the female style
               was at once more accessible and more reserved: accessible through the emphasis on the
               physicality of the textile, reserved because of the impenetrability <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_036.jpg"
                  n="36" xml:id="img_0036"/> of the design. Because of the limited number of design
               elements, the variation of combinations gave richness to the weavings. Just as the
               women were not at the center of the power hierarchy of the Chilkat clans, their art
               did not rely on signs central to the culture. The limited motifs available to women
               were indicative of the women’s position in relation to the status quo, the fabric out
               of which the blankets were created.</p>
            <p>Both men’s and women’s blankets were highly valued and were used in a variety of
               ceremonies. Given as dowry, along with songs, dances and titles, they were commonly
               made for the potlatch. Potlatch was integral to Chilkat life. These were competitive
               ceremonies involving the distribution and destruction of wealth. Blankets were often
               cut up and handed round or burned in vast quantities of salmon oil. Guests sometimes
               collected pieces of blankets they received as gifts and later reassembled them into
               new blankets, shirts or dance aprons. In this way they created collage motifs and
               symbols. The recipient was obliged to pay back the gift, preferably with interest.
               Blankets therefore were a currency of obligation. The Chilkats based their
               interpersonal relations on desire for power and control, intense competition coupled
               with a philosophy of conspicuous consumption. The many social ceremonies in which the
               Chilkats demonstrated these characteristics created an unending demand for
               prestigious art objects, like the blankets. At some point in their history the
               Chilkats began to support professional artists to meet these needs. Partly as a
               result of the desire to consume or destroy costly items, the Chilkats valued objects
               that were very difficult to produce. The intricacy of the men’s style blanket
               patterns made them more highly valued than the women’s style; these considerations
               were central to the Chilkat ideas of aesthetic appreciation.</p>
            <p>Men’s concerns were at the center of their society’s power structure – represented in
               blankets by hunting and mythological motifs. However, even though the women’s style
               did not demonstrate the same access to the culture’s core concerns, their blankets
               were highly regarded. The competitive give-aways which commissioned the
               prestige-laden blankets of both styles raised the weavers’ status. As European
               contact increased, European standards infiltrated the Chilkat community and affected
               the production of female-style blankets. The increased demand for representational
               blankets, sought after for their unique yet recognizable images, limited the time the
               weavers had to produce their own type of textile. It is partly as a result of this
               influence that the female-style Chilkat blankets have received so little
               attention.</p>
            <byline>L.G.</byline>
         </div>
         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_037.jpg"
               n="37" xml:id="img_0037"/>
            <head>The Navajo</head>
            <p> Spider Woman instructed the Navajo women how to weave on a loom. The warp was of
               spider web. There were crosspoles of sky and earth cords, warp sticks of sun rays,
               and healds of rock crystal and sheet lightning. The batten was sun halo, and white
               shell made the comb. The four spindles were of flash lightning with a whorl of
               turquoise, lightning with a whorl of abalone, a rain streamer with a whorl of white
               shell and zigzag lightning with a whorl of coal. <seg>—A Navajo Legend</seg></p>
            <p> The Navajos explained the origins of weaving through the myth of Spider Woman. As an
               art form weaving reflected a changing Navajo culture and therefore serves as a
               valuable and permanent record. Through their vigorous design and color, and the
               technical skill involved, Navajo blankets expressed women’s vision and artistry.</p>
            <p>Blankets were woven for many needs, but were essentially used for clothing and
               warmth. Their other uses were as bedding, saddle blankets and floor coverings for
               sitting. They were also used as doorways to Navajo homes, called hogans. The blankets
               were secular, not ceremonial, textiles through which the women expressed a strong
               personal connection to the people using them. Blankets represented, and perhaps
               symbolized through their design, the life of the wearer. When worn, the blanket's
               linear design emphasized the verticality of a standing person. The wearing of
               blankets enlivened the environment, not only visually, but also through the symbolic
               meanings of color. To the Navajo red meant Blessed Sunshine, white the East or
               Morning Light, blue the South which was cloudless, yellow the West or the Sunset and
               black the North where dark clouds originated. Combinations evoked naturalistic
               images. For example, black vertical lines might represent rain, and on a yellow
               background, the rain in the evening sky. Women followed certain traditional forms,
               but each weaver made her own interpretation and wove the blanket herself.
               Individuality of the blankets was highly regarded; each weaver’s ideas and feelings
               could be expressed in unique designs which were never repeated.</p>
            <p>In Navajo society women historically have been greatly respected and thought the
               equal of men. Deep religiosity and mythology permeated daily life, explaining natural
               phenomena and daily tasks, and creating their history. Woman was deified in Navajo
               mythology as Changing Woman, a central figure who designed the hogans. By hanging her
               blankets as a doorway and designat ing their colors as those of “Dawn, Sky Blue,
               Evening Twilight, and Darkness,” women connected the domestic, natural and religious
               spheres, a synthesis typical of Navajo life structure. Women headed the separate
               family units and managed thei economic affairs. In this matrilineal society women’s
               participation in rituals and in political activities was considered essential. Their
               chores included cooking, sewing, caring for the house and children, gathering wood,
               hauling water, butchering livestock and herding the sheep from which they prepared
               the wool for their weaving. This preparation included shearing the wool and <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_038.jpg"
                  n="38" xml:id="img_0038"/> carding, spinning and dyeing it. Frequently women built
               their own looms, which were set up outside in summer and inside the hogan in winter.
               Looms were made of logs placed vertically and could be dismantled for transport from
               summer to winter grazing grounds. The women designed and wove their blankets, without
               prior drawings, as their time and chores allowed. The earliest-known examples of the
               Navajo blanket date from 1805. However, the first Navajos who migrated to the
               Southwest United States in 1000 A.D. probably used tree and bark fibers. It was not
               until the fifteenth century, when Spanish livestock was brought to the neighboring
               Pueblo Indians, that Navajo weaving changed significantly. Through trade and raids
               the Navajo got sheep which provided the women with softer threads and the varying
               colors of natural fleece. Exposure to the weaving techniques of the Pueblos in the
               late seventeenth century influenced Navajo weavers to experiment with new techniques
               and develop a style of alternating bands of natural wool colors.</p>
            <p>As dyes and yarns were obtained through trade, new colors began to be used. One of
               the earliest colors was a red whose source was the unraveled, respun and rewoven
               threads of an English fabric called “bayeta,” imported by the Spaniards and traded to
               the Pueblos. Because of their complexity and technical skill these “bayeta” blankets
               were reknowned among the Spanish and other tribes. To own a Navajo blanket was
               considered a sign of honor.</p>
            <p>Stylistic changes also occurred after contact with North American culture. In the
               1860s the Navajos fought with and finally surrendered to Kit Carson at Fort Sumner,
               where they were imprisoned for four years. Although conditions there were not good,
               the Navajos assimilated many new influences. One of the dominant and most startling
               styles to come out of this period was the “Eye-Dazzler,” so called for its interplay
               of expressive pattern and vivid color. This style, as well as others, showed the
               weaver’s mastery in its finely spun wool, even and tightly woven texture, boldness
               and energy of design and subtlety in its skillful handling and control. In relation
               to this highly developed artistic decísion-making Gladys Reichard, in Weaving a
               Navajo Blanket, speaks of the weaver Atlnaba who “spends hours experimenting with the
               colors at her command . . . She may discard a dozen greens and yellows before she
               accepts one.</p>
            <p>Men and women in Navajo society used different aesthetic systems to filter and
               express their perceptions. Men’s art, unlike the women’s, was religious. Sand
               paintings, whose powers were guarded in secret and destroyed after the ritual, used
               figurative imagery to summon the spirits and gain vicarious control over nature.
               Women’s art, however, was visible in everyday use. Women employed a nonfigurative and
               abstract imagery, powerfully reflecting the desert landscape in which the Navajo
               lived, a landscape of horizontality, expansiveness, drama and vivid color. The
               strength of their aesthetic language and the power of its expressiveness reveal the
               great pride Navajo women felt in their social and economic importance and the value
               of their activities.</p>
            <byline>J.F.</byline>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Lacemakers of Western Europe</head>
            <p>Wearing and making lace was important in Europe from the sixteenth through the
               nineteenth centuries. Lace appears to us today as a delicate and innocent fabric. The
               world in which it existed was fai from innocent, and despite its appearance, lace and
               its history illustrate this Like other luxuries, most lace could be had only by the
               wealthy. The womer who made it rarely benefited from it While their products were
               coveted, they worked under poor and sometimes hazardous conditions. As symbols of
               status, laces left the humble homes of lacemakers to enter a world removed from their
               lives.</p>

            <p>The two most highly prized laces were “needlepoint, which depended entirely on the
               buttonhole stitch, and “bobbin, in which thread was woven, twisted and braided around
               bobbins. These laces were made by women of all classes. Wealthier women made it for
               recreation and because it befitted their roles as “cultivated ladies.” Poorer women
               made it to sell. Lace made for personal use contained any design of the woman’s
               imagination and cultural heritage. Motifs included fantastical animals, birds, human
               figures or religious scenes or symbols. Designs for commerce were more limited. They
               were usually created by male patternmakers according to prevailing fashion, although
               commercial lacemakers’ own interpretations were also highly valued. Each country and
               region had indigenous designs, but if lacemakers moved to new areas, they took their
               patterns and drawings with them. Many towns were financially dependent on this female
               industry despite the low wages paid.</p>
            <p>The process of making lace was painstaking and required close scrutiny. The thread
               was so fine that complicated means were necessary to magnify it. Many lacemakers went
               blind by the time they were thirty. Every effort was made to keep the lace clean and
               delicate, mostly at the expense of the lacemaker’s health. Often thread spinning and
               lacemaking were done in damp cellars to prevent the thread from becoming brit tle and
               breaking. In winter lacemakers worked in lofts above cowsheds for warmth so that the
               lace was kept away from smokey fireplaces. Its production was time-consuming; a woman
               could spend a whole year on a single piece of Valenciennes. In 1855 Napoleon III
               ordered a dress for Princess Eugenie which took 36 women 18 months to complete. Even
               when not involved in such ambitious projects, women might spend 12 to 15 hours each
               day making lace.</p>
            <p>Lace was produced in whole pieces or in parts depending on the design. Making
               separate parts entailed a division of labor determined by specialization and skill.
               Some women were better at making the ground net, others at filling in the flowers,
               etc. The most skilled worker assembled the entire piece.</p>
            <p>To sell their work, lacemakers were immersed in a cumbersome commercial process,
               called the “facteur” or middleman system. A commercial house (manufacturer) was
               represented by a facteur who, acting as its agent, supplied lacemakers with patterns
               and raw materials on credit. Finished pieces were then sold to the facteur who in
               turn resold them to the manufacturer. There was little or no contact between
               lacemakers and manufacturers. Facteurs were usually women—former lacemakers who could
               supervise other lacemakers and who were counted on to drive a hard bargain for the
               manufacturer. Since lacemakers were totally dependent on facteurs for their work and
               raw material, they were unable to bargain for better pay or working conditions. Their
               only other option was to become facteurs. The contradiction of this system is that
               through personal advancement the women who became facteurs helped to perpetuate the
               exploitation of their former peers.</p>
            <p>For artistocratic women instruction in lacemaking prepared them for futures as “noble
               ladies.” Poor girls were taught at home, in convents or in charitable institutions.
               Convents established apprenticeships where girls began their training at five and by
               ten were able to earn their keep. They were taught lacemaking not to master an art
               but to make a living. Women of both classes were denied the opportunity to direct
               their own lives. The notion that women were suited to <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_039.jpg"
                  n="39" xml:id="img_0039"/> work which required patience and perseverance directly
               resulted from the constraints imposed upon them by society.</p>
            <p>Ironically most lacemakers did not benefit from the beauty and romance of lace. In
               addition, their products became symbols in a world in which they did not participate.
               Lace was highly valued by the rich because it represented their position in society.
               Men boasted about how much land their lace was worth; they appeared in ballrooms
               wearing as much of it as they could. Women wore it as a reflection of their husbands’
               or fathers’ wealth. Lace became a nationalistic emblem. Countries were highly
               competitive in its display and production. Monarchs decreed that only their favorite
               native laces could appear in court. Edicts were proclaimed banning the use of foreign
               laces to protect home industries and black markets involving smuggling and kidnapping
               developed to undermine these laws. When lace designs were traded, they were secretly
               guarded. When Belgium tried to prevent the theft of lace imported from France, these
               designs were so cut up when distributed to lacemakers that their entirety was unknown
               to any individual woman. It was feared that a lace- maker would attempt to smuggle or
               to sell the design.</p>
            <p>Lace made by women for personal use was often kept by their families which also
               preserved the memory of the lacemakers. Lace made to sell was and is perceived as
               anonymous. Although most lacemakers remain unknown to us, their art is silent witness
               to the arduous and creative work which was their tradition.</p>
            <byline>B.L.</byline>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>Speculations</head>
            <p>Because art, its creation and the theories surrounding it are political, we have
               placed the textile art made by women in traditional societies into a cultural
               context, instead of simply considering the artifacts. We have explored aspects of
               women s art in each of five cultures, relating them to women’s broader social
               identities. Our assumption that art dialectically reflects and contributes to the
               creation of society was basic to our study and revealed in our research.</p>
            <p>Peruvian textiles were viewed as sacred; as such, women making them performed this
               task as a ceremonial act of creation. Textiles reflected status within Peruvian
               culture, making the weavers responsible for visibly defining differences of rank.</p>
            <p>In Maori society women were considered nonsacred and socially inferior. Activities
               like wood and greenstone carving were forbidden to them. It was possible for men, on
               the other hand, to weave and use women’s designs, although they usually undertook
               women’s tasks only as instructors in weaving schools where they initiated girls into
               the ritual, technique and aesthetics of weaving.</p>
            <p>In Chilkat society, rank and privilege were inherited matrilineally, but women did
               not really own the titles passed down to them by birthright. Instead, titles were
               given by women’s fathers to their husbands at the time of marriage The distinctions
               of female/male status can also be seen in relation to blanket making. While men
               designed the representational blankets, women executed their designs. Despite a
               certain lack of legitimate power, women exerted covert power as weavers by inserting
               disruptive motifs into the spaces on and between male mythological designs. More
               importantly, women designed and wove blankets which were also highly valued by their
               culture, although not representational in style.</p>
            <p>Women in Navajo society were well respected. Their responsibilities and powers were
               equal to those of men. Though it was possible for women to participate in the making
               of religious art, they rarely did so, preferring to maintain the female tradition of
               weaving. Their weaving used strong abstract imagery. Their textiles were highly
               valued both inside and outside the tribe.</p>
            <p>Class differences in Western Europe affected the production of lace. Wealthy women
               made it as part of their required repertoire of ladylike leisure accomplishments.
               Poor women made it for a living. Paradoxically, this afforded them a certain autonomy
               that richer women did not achieve, but this autonomy did not extend to conceptual
               control over commercial lace design. Because our research has focused on particular
               aspects of five cultures, we are not making universal claims. Rather we have explored
               alternative ways of looking at and trying to understand women and their products.
               These have included:</p>
            <list>
               <item>working collectively in our research, discussions and writing;</item>
               <item>questioning our information sources, particularly in terms of their andro- and
                  ethnocentrism;</item>
               <item>articulating our own filters, consistent with our conten- tion that objectivity
                  in research or interpretation is neither possible nor even desirable.</item>
            </list>
            <p>We came to our project curious, confused, angry that even within the already
               denigrated category of “traditional art, women’s objects had often been overlooked or
               misrepresented. We were ready to be sympathetic to the women whose objects had
               attracted us to this research in the first place.</p>
            <p>But we wanted to avoid merely replacing one set of distorting biases for another. We
               wanted to understand our curiosity, clarify our confusion, find the sources of our
               anger without anachronistically using contemporary Western notions like oppression of
               women to explain sex hierarchies. We were wary of our sympathy for the objects and
               their makers and did not wish to impose a simple translation of Western definitions
               of art on to societies where art had a very different meaning. All the speculations
               that follow should be read in the context of these qualifications.</p>
            <p>There is a contradictory freedom in the abstract style of women s art in some of
               these cultures (Maori, Chilkat, Navajo). Women’s iconography did not directly
               function in the service of male religion and therefore was not subservient to male
               mythology. The abstractness” of women’s art has to be questioned. Men, investigating
               New Zealand Maori male design, have taken great pains to discover that, though
               abstract, this iconography is an exaggerated stylization of natural objects in the
               Maori environment. Yet the literature <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_040.jpg"
                  n="40" xml:id="img_0040"/> on women’s styles denies that their abstractions also
               have meaning. Chilkat men designed their dreams into the blankets woven by their
               women. Because their symbols have been interpreted more than the designs of the women
               does not negate the possibility that female abstractions have symbolic meaning too.
               That the making of Navajo blankets was embedded in the myth of Spider Woman and that
               their colors and designs call to mind so evocatively the atmosphere of the Navajo
               environment suggest the possibility of a latent symbolism.</p>
            <p> Even the claim that men have often tended to be the designers and women the makers
               (of Chilkat blankets, of lace) cannot be accepted at face value. In the Chilkat
               society women challenged the constraints imposed by male designers by inserting their
               own motifs. By the time lacemaking had become an industry men were the acknowledged
               designers, although the industry drew on the long tradition of cottage lacemaking.
               Women had been sovereign over the whole process, and undoubtedly many designs had
               their origins in what women had been creating for centuries.</p>
            <p>Though our focus has been on the female/male contradiction, other forms of
               stratification existed in Peruvian, Maori, Chilkat and European society. Status
               distinctions separated women from each other as well as women from men. Lace was made
               in the context of early capitalism in which old feudal distinctions between the high
               and low born were giving way to class structures. As lace was produced for commerce,
               the opportunity for some poor women to become facteurs developed. This created
               additional inequalities in income and status between lacemakers. In Maori society the
               advantages of being a puhi or woman aristocrat (more elaborate clothing,
               ornamentation, responsibilities for organizing entertainment) were tempered by
               restrictions, particularly on her sexual freedom, her choice of husband and lovers.
               The Chilkat social structure was stratified into chiefs, commoners and slaves; women
               occupied all three ranks. As has been discussed, though rank was matrilineally
               inherited, the women who owned titles tended, in turn, to be the property of men. The
               Navajo society, where women enjoyed equality with men and there was mutual respect
               between the sexes, was not hierarchical. Apparently the more stratified a society is
               and the more its production depends on the existence of castes and classes, the more
               likely it is that women in general, and women in less prestigious groups in
               particular, will be designated inferior in practice, ideology and myth.</p>
            <p>What strikes us is that despite the potential of traditional social structures to
               muffle and distort the artistic expression of women, the effect on women’s artmaking
               was contradictory. Conceptualizaton was separated from execution of design in Chilkat
               and Peruvian societies and, most extremely. among employed lacemakers in Westemn
               Europe. The range of media and motifs available to women was restricted in Maori and
               Chilkat societies, and women’s art was designated as nonreligious in societies such
               as the Navajo and Maori where religion was valued. Despite these limitations, women s
               textiles asserted themselves as beautiful art objects. Out of this contradiction
               women invented a varied abstract visual language. We are not attempting to resolve
               that contradiction, which is a real one. It is not our point that the objects women
               made were, or need to be, judged qualitatively as equal, inferior or superior to
               those of men. What we are saying is that we do not subscribe to these
               categorizations.</p>
            <p>We cannot neglect the contexts, both real and ideological, in which women s art has
               been made. Our critique questions the social and political structures which created
               and perpetuated discriminating hierarchies. By looking at traditional societies
               through our Western, female eyes, we can acknowledge the biased quality of our
               interpretations. We can also see how contemporary biases were anticipated by the
               discriminatory attitudes toward women characteristic of the cultures we have
               investigated.</p>
            <p>We take for granted that women’s self-expression in textiles was artistic expression.
               Social structures and supporting mythologies did have the potential to thwart
               creative needs of women. What was important was women’s ability to break codes, to
               play with format and to transcend limitations. Women often had to subvert societal
               dictates in order to gain access to a fundamental human need—that of artistic
               self-expression. Any attempt to deny this need is a painful form of oppression. That
               women in traditional societies have been resourceful and spirited in challenging this
               must be celebrated.</p>
         </div>
<div>
            <biblStruct>               
               <monogr>
                  <author>Anderson, Johannes C.</author>
               <title>Maori Life in Ao-Tea.</title>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>Christchurch, Wellington and Dunnedin</publisher>
               <pubPlace>New Zealand</pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>Melbourne and London</pubPlace> <publisher>Whitcombe and Tombs</publisher>             
               <date>1907</date></imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Averkieva, Julia</author> 
                  <title>“The Tlingit Indians,” in Eleanor Leacock and O. Lurie, eds.,
               North American Indians in Historical Perspective.</title> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Random House,</publisher> <date>1971</date> 
                     <biblScope unit="page">pp. 317-342.</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Benedict, Ruth,</author> 
               <title>Patterns of Culture (with a new introduction).</title> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace> <publisher>Houghton Mifflin,</publisher> <date>1959</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Bird, J.,</author> 
                  <title>“Textile Designing and Samplers in Peru," in S. K. Lothrop. Essays in
               Pre- Columbian Art and Archaeology.</title> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge:</pubPlace> <publisher>Harvard University Press,</publisher> <date>1961</date> 
                     <biblScope unit="page">pp. 299-316.</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Bird, J. and L. Bellinger, Paracas</author> 
                  <title>Fabrics and Nazca Needlework, Third Century B.C.# A.D. Third Century.</title> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.:</pubPlace> <publisher>Washington, D.C. Textile Museum.</publisher>
               <date>1954.</date></imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Boas, Franz.</author> 
                  <title>Primitive Art.</title> 
                  <imprint>
                    <pubPlace> New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Dover,</publisher> <span>reprint,</span> <date>1955.</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
                     <monogr>
                        <author>Burnham, Jack,</author> 
                        <title>The Structure of Art,</title> 
                        <imprint>
                           <pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Braziller,</publisher> <date>1971.</date></imprint>
                     </monogr>
            </biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Chaplin, D.,</author> 
                  <title>The Peruvian Industrial Labor Force.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>Princeton:</pubPlace> <publisher>Princeton University
               Press.</publisher> <date>1967.</date></imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Cowan, James,</author> 
                  <title>The Maoris of New Zealand.</title> 
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Christchurch, Wellington and Dunnedin,</publisher>
               <pubPlace>New Zealand, Melbourne and London:</pubPlace> <publisher>Whitcombe and Tombs,</publisher> <date>1910.</date></imprint> </monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Cowan, James,</author> 
                  <title>The Maori People of New Zealand.</title> 
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>New Zealand Government Publicity
               Production, </publisher>
                     <date>1928.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Denney G., and C. Osborne, eds.,</author> 
                  <title>Textiles of Ancient Peru and Their Techniques.</title>
               <imprint><pubPlace>Seattle:</pubPlace> 
                  <pubPlace>University of Washington Press,</pubPlace> <date>1962.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Dockstadter, Frederick J.,</author> 
                  <title>“Indian Art in the Southwest.” in American Indian Art:
               Form and Tradition.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>Minneapolis:</pubPlace> <publisher>Walker Center and Minneapolic Institute of Arts,</publisher>
               <date>1972</date><biblScope>, pp. 63-69.</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Drucker, Philip.</author> 
                  <title>Indians of the Northwest Coast.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>Garden City, N.Y.:</pubPlace> <publisher>Natural
               History Press, 19.</publisher></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Fiske, P. L., ed.,</author> 
                  <title>Irene Emery Roundtable of Museum Textiles.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>Washington, D.C. Textile Museum,</publisher> <date>1974.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Fraser, Douglas, ed.,</author> 
                  <title>The Columbia University Exhibition of Ancient Textiles from
               Peru, the Central Coast.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Program of Advanced Studies at Graduate Faculties,
               Columbia University,</publisher> <date>1965.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Gayton, A. H.,</author> 
                  <title>“Cultural Significance of Peruvian Textiles, Production, Function.
               Aesthetics, in J. H. Rowe and Menzel, Peruvian Archaeology.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>Berkeley:</pubPlace> <publisher>Peek
               Publications, Mountain View, CA. </publisher><date>1967.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Goldwater, Robert,</author> 
                  <title>Primitives in Modern Art.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace><publisher> Vintage Press.</publisher> <date>1967.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>
            
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>                     
               <author>Harris, Ann Sutherland and Linda Nochlin,</author> 
                     <title>Women Artists 1550-1950.</title> 
                     <imprint><pubPlace>Los Angeles and
               New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Los Angeles County Museum and Alfred A. Knopf,</publisher> <date>1976.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Heuer, Berys,</author> 
                  <title>Maori Women.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>Wellington, Sydney, London:</pubPlace><publisher> A. H. and A. W. Reed.
               James, George Wharton, Indian Blankets and Their Makers. McClurg.</publisher> <date>1914.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Kahlenberg. Mary and Anthony Berlant,</author> 
                  <title>The Navajo Blanket.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Praeger,
               Kellogg. Mrs. Charlotte (Hoffman), The Bobbins of Belgium. New York: Funk and
               Wagnall, </publisher><date>1920.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>King. M. E.,</author> 
                  <title>Textiles and Basketry of the Paracas Period, Ice Valley, Peru.</title> 
                  <imprint>
               <pubPlace>Tuscon:</pubPlace> <publisher>University of Arizona Press,</publisher> <date>1965.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Mead, C.,</author> 
                  <title>Old Civilizations of Incaland.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Museum of Natural History, 1924
               Murra, J.. “Cloth and Its Functions in the Inca State,” American Anthropologist, 64,</publisher>
               <date>1962,</date></imprint><biblScope unit="page" from="710" to="728">pp. 710-728.</biblScope></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Palliser, Mrs. Fanny (Marryat),</author> 
                  <title>The History of Lace.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Scribners Sons,</publisher>
               <date>1902.</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
               
              <biblStruct>
                 <monogr>
                    <author>Paz, Octavio,</author> <title>Essay in In Praise of Hands, Contemporary Crafts of the World.</title>
                    <imprint><pubPlace>Greenwich. Conn.:</pubPlace> <publisher>New York Graphic Society,</publisher> <date>1974,</date></imprint> <biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="24">pp. 17-24.</biblScope></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Phillips, W. J.,</author> 
                  <title>Maori Life and Custom.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>Wellington, Auckland, Sydney:</pubPlace> <publisher>A. H. and A.
               W. Reed,</publisher> <date>1966.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Reichard, Gladys,</author> 
                  <title>Social Life of the Navajo Indians.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Columbia University
               Press,</publisher> <date>1928.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Reichard, Gladys,</author> 
                  <title>Weaving a Navajo Blanket.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace><publisher> Dover, reprint, 1936</publisher></imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            
               <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <author>Schneider, Peggy,</author> <title>“Children of Changing Woman: Myth, Symbol, and Navajo Women."</title>
                     <imprint><publisher>Exhibition at Wheelwright Museum,</publisher> <date from="1977-07-31" to="1977-10-30">July 31-October 30, 1977.</date>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Stafford, C. E.,</author> 
                  <title>Paracas Embroideries.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace> <publisher>Augustin,</publisher> <date>1941.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Vreeland, J.,</author> 
                  <title>“Ancient Andean Textiles, Clothes for the Dead,” Archaeology,</title> 
                  <imprint><biblScope>30
                     (3)</biblScope> <date>1977,</date></imprint><biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="178">pp. 166-178.</biblScope></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Warble, Patricia,</author> 
                  <title>Victorian Lace.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>London:</pubPlace> <publisher>Praeger,</publisher> <date>1968.</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct>

            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Wingert, Paul S.,</author> 
                  <title>Primitive Art: Its Traditions and Style.</title> 
                  <imprint><pubPlace>Cleveland and New York:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>World Publishing,</publisher> <date>1962.</date></imprint> </monogr></biblStruct>
         </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div>
            <p> Jean Feinberg is a painter living in New York City. Lenore Goldberg is a New York
               painter involved with pattern and collage. Julie Gross is an artist living in New
               York who teaches at Pratt New York Phoenix School of Design. Bella Lieberman does art
               and secretarial work in New York City. Elizabeth Sacre, an Australian, is studying
               literature and education at Columbia Uni- versity Teachers College.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
