<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[ESSAY TITLE]</title>
            <author>[ESSAY AUTHOR]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
                     <div>
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_022.jpg" n="22" xml:id="img_0022"/>
            
               <head><title>THE STRAITS OF LITERATURE AND HISTORY</title></head>
                        <byline>Carrie Rickey</byline>
            <p>
               With whom does history empathize? For
               Walter Benjamin, “The answer is inevita-
               ble: with the victor.”1 The reciprocity be-
               tween historian and ruler is tacit: the his-
               torian makes official the ruler’s authority
               and the ruler’s authority gives the histori-
               an’s work validity. This is not to suggest
               that no histories exist that subvert this
               premise. Literature is a “history” which in
               most cases serves the prevailing order
               because its very existence confirms thaf
               order’s cultural richness. But literature is
               privileged because it can employ language’s
               nuance and allusiveness and from the inside
               gently or joltingly criticize that order. Be
               cause literature is by implication a cultural
               artifact of a ruling order, subversive or not
               it is a historical spoil owing as much to the
               anonymous toil that gave the writer time to
               pursue an idea as to the original mind that
               conceived it.</p>
               <p>The connection between a ruling order
               and its cultural artifacts is like a strait sep-
               arating two bodies of water intimately link-
               ed in time and geography. The straits of lit-
               erature and history are evidenced in Jap-
               anese writing of the Heian period (794-1185
               A.D.) which commands interest because of
               its richness of description, its pioneering of
               new forms, and the fact that its leading
               practitioners were women. Many social and
               cultural conditions set the stage for this un-
               precedented predominance of literary
               women. According to Ivan Morris.</p>
               <p>"Though they (peasants, fishermen, forest-
               men and other laborers contributed to the
               vast majority of the (Heian period’s) popula
               tion and were the only economically pro-
               ductive class in the country, we virtually
               have no authentic information about their
               lives.”2 What we today know of Heian life
               has been garnered from the literature of that
               period—especially from Murasaki Shikibu’s
               The Tale of Genji and Sei Shonagon’s The
               Pillow Book—but these literary milestones
               detailing Heian court life treat a population
               of only about one-tenth of one percent of the
               five million population in Japan at that
               time.3 </p>
              <p> Murasaki’s and Sei’s originality of form
               and observation is unparalleled in the
               history of literature. These two women were 
               contemporaries; both were brought to court
               from the provinces because of their talent
               and intelligence. Due to the complications
               of Japan’s clan politics, there was a “court
               with many satellite courts, and it is not
               known whether these two women ever lived
               in the same palace, although they were
               aware of each other’s writings. Their social
               position was substantially different from
               that of the women outside the court who
               “toiled arduously, were subject to harsh
               treatment by their men, bred young, and
               died early.4</p>
               <p>Murasaki and Sei are figures of incalcu-
               lable significance because they were pio-
               neers, because they produced work in a
               period which had articulated for itself a dis
               tinct masculine and feminine aesthetic, and
               because they wrote in Japanese at a time
               when the language for official and theologi-
               cal affairs was Chinese (cf. the European
               use of Latin as an “official” language). Not
               only did they establish traditions of the psy-
               chological novel and the diary, but their
               writings preserved the Japanese language
               for subsequent generations. In their day
               women were restricted to the use of Japan
               ese while men exchanged ideas and conver
               sation in Chinese. Even today the dis-
               tinction between native syllabary and the
               Chinese characters incorporated into the
               language reflects this gender dichotomy.
               The native characters are called onnade, or
               woman’s hand,” while Chinese character
               are known as otokomoji, “man’s letters.”
               Sei’s writings are still studied today for the
               purity of her Japanese diction; she avoidec
               Chinese-isms—an accomplishment compar-
               able to writing in English without using any
               Latinate words.</p>
               <p>In the time of Murasaki and Sei there
               were no narrative literary traditions to
               maintain. Japanese literature before their
               time had been poetry of a calculatedly
               oblique nature; a long prologomena was
               necessary to explain the poem’s meaning.</p>
               <p>What a remarkable achievement to conceive
               a psychological novel—as Murasaki did-
               where a poem appears as an organic expres-
               sion within the context of a narrative and re
               quires no annotation to be understood
               Murasaki fused the traditional poetic form
               
               with her narrative innovation, the intimate
               epic. Sei’s Pillow Book was so called
               because she suggested to the empress that
               notebooks of historical documents could be
               recycled by making them into a pillow (a
               word that referred to a diary as well as a
               head rest); Sei filled her notebook with lists,
               odd facts and observations from the present,
               thereby annotating the leaves of official
               history with her lively opinions.“ For both
               these women, objectivity was the domain of
               the historian and untenable because it neu-
               tralized differing positions. Objects and peo-
               ple, in the writings of Murasaki and Sei.
               have innumerable facets. They intimated
               the spirit of an object or a person by bom-
               barding the reader with dense description:
               lists, textures, physical and natural detail.
               Collectively their historical truth is compel
               ling because they replace “objectivity” with
               opinionation.</p>
               <p>But these two contemporaries reflected
               different attitudes about their culture. Sei
               begins a chapter of her book with: “When I
               make myself imagine what it is like to be one
               of those women who live at home, faithfully
               serving their husbands—women who have
               not a single exciting prospect in life yet be-
               lieve they are perfectly happy—I am filled
               with scorn.”7 In a passage where Murasaki
               describes Genji’s (and by implication her
               own) view of the novel, Genji observes,
               “Without it what should we know of how
               people lived in the past from the age of the
               Gods down to the present day? For history
               books . . . show us only one corner of life;
               whereas these diaries and romances which I
               see piled around you contain, 1 am sure, the
               most minute information about people's
               private affairs.”° Sei and Murasaki charted
               divergent routes in their writing: Sei was an
               empiricist recording impressions of contem-
               porary Heian manners; she lacked the self-
               consciousness of Murasaki, who fashioned a
               world in the indeterminate past in order to
               best intuitively comment on life in her im-
               mediate present. Sei’s literary concerns were
               the refined tastes of the nobility and the
               freshness of nature. Murasaki was less im-
               pressionistic and more analytic in her eval-
               uation of Heian society. She continuously
               tells us that it was best to be born a man of</p>
            
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_023.jpg" n="23" xml:id="img_0023"/>
            <p>
               imperial blood and live at the court. But she
               was keenly aware of the hierarchies within
               the aristocracy and observed the tension
               between provincials and the court clique, as
               well as sensitively articulating the social
               restrictions limiting the mobility of the lower
               ranks within the court.</p>
               <p>A number of factors informed the atti-
               tudes Sei and Murasaki expressed. The
               birth of a woman was a happy event because
               in the marriage politics of Heian society a
               woman might grow up to marry the emper-
               or. It was much easier in their day for a
               woman of “inferior” birth to marry a man of
               noble rank than vice versa. The professions
               which brought a lower-rank man to the cap-
               ital—scholar or priest, say—would not auto-
               matically give him ingress to the imperial
               circle, while it seems likely that Sei and
               Murasaki were brought to the court because
               of their reputations as women of wit and
               sensibility. In Heian Japan a woman was
               allowed both to inherit and own property.
               The civil codes expressly forbade wife-beat-
               ing, although the punishment for this was
               two degrees less than assaulting other
               people.”° But these facts don’t pinpoint the
               complex and inbred quality of Heian life,
               which is best described by the Chinese prov-
               erb: “The people are as far from the Emper
               or as from heaven. Japanese appropriation
               of China s governmental centralization pro-
               duced a bureaucracy so awkward in this
               land of decentralized clans that the delega-
               tion of authority was carried to extreme
               lengths; the source of authority was, accord-
               ingly, far removed from the functionary who
               directly wielded it. Because the real power
               was exercised by ministers and other imperi-
               al subalterns, the emperor was left with two
               functions: to encourage new art forms and
               fashion rituals of piety from the religious hy-
               brid of Shinto and Buddhist beliefs. Women
               were excluded from public affairs, but they
               played a tremendous role in the Heian
               court. A well-born woman had leisure and
               imperial encouragement for creation and
               contemplation denied to male counterparts
               busy with official duties and polygamous
               pursuits (the man at the Heian court was ex-
               pected to have a wife and a few mistresses).</p>
            <p>
               If Murasaki’s and Sei’s writings are an in-
               dex to female sexual options during the
               Heian period, aristocratic women enjoyed a
               multiplicity of partners as well. Later ages
               would revile Sei and Murasaki for their
               foully licentious”1° descriptions, but prom-
               iscuity was a vital element of their culture
               The largely endogamous Heian court was
               energized by the covert alliances of pro-
               vincials with sovereigns and their
               subalterns. The ruling clan of the Heian
               period—the Fujiwaras—never commanded
               significant military strength but established
               power by marrying their daughters to sover-
               eigns. The famous Fujiwara Michinaga was
               father-in-law of two emperors, grandfather
               of a third, grandfather and greatgrandfather
               of a fourth, grandfather and father-in-law of
               a fifth." This kind of inbreeding was the
               substructure of the court clique. The
               nominal source of power, this clique was at-
               tractive because it nurtured the creation of
               art. But it needed the vitality of provincials
               like Sei and Murasaki to regenerate its in-
               cestuous ranks.</p>
               <p>Once at court, Sei and Murasaki became
               insiders who made observations on the
               social arts at a time when manners were
               politics and politics culture. Murasaki wrote
               of a picture competition designed by Genji
               to rechannel court enmities to less des-
               tructive ends: “It was indeed a moment in
               the history of our country when the whole
               energy of the nation seemed to be concen-
               trated upon the search for the prettiest
               method of mounting paper scrolls.”12</p>
               <p>Murasaki’s and Sei’s importance is that
               while they operated in a culture that re-
               garded women as inferior to men, they never
               believed that of themselves. Although in her
               diary Murasaki repeatedly alluded to her
               father’s regret that because of her great in-
               telligence she had not been born male, she
               characterized the richness of both male and
               female experiences in Genji. Although it is
               clear in Genji that men have more options
               available to them, women are equal in wit,
               intelligence and style. Sei, perhaps because
               of her position as the empress’ favorite, is
               much more interested in the doings of im-
               perial ladies than those of gentlemen. Mur-
               
               
               asaki’s and Sei’s writing was expressly
               power-identified at a time when power was
               not so much a link with male dominance as
               it was one expression in a complex social
               milieu in which women participated. Mura-
               saki and Sei dealt with emotions that are
               universally intelligible and exist cross-
               culturally—unlike the objective specificities
               of the official histories and philosophies in
               which the men of their day engaged. Edu-
               cated women were able to act and write less
               conventionally than were men of com-
               parable status.</p>
               <p>Could a Heian man have created work
               like Murasaki and Sei? The self-conscious
               Heian court was totally aware of the sexual
               division of speech and the exclusion of
               women from the public sphere. Only at
               court could women circulate and not be
               expected to hide behind fans and screens,
               the way propriety demanded women do out-
               side the court. The masculine style,
               identified by scholars of Japanese literature
               as well as by Murasaki and Sei in various
               appreciations of male qualities, was “the di-
               rectness of utterance and concern with
               society.”1 The “feminine preference was
               taken to be the interest in suggestion and in-
               tuition—which was the style imitated by
               men when they wrote to women or expressed
               themselves in affairs of the heart. A man
               could have written in the style of Murasaki
               and Sei, and, indeed, some men assumed
               the feminine voice and pretended to be
               women authors. But the incisiveness and
               sensibility of these female impersonators is
               inferior to the work of Murasaki and Sei.
               The inference that women sensed nuance in
               affairs of state while men were consigned
               blindly to conduct these affairs leads to a
               simplistic women feel/men think conclu-
               sion that fails to cut through psychology or
               historicism. Men couldn’t create work like
               Murasaki and Sei, even though they tried.
               These women were successful in capturing
               the range of experience and feeling of both
               sexes.</p>
              <p> Why were they successful? They glorified
               a shining nobility. They catalogued and or-
               dered a courtly etiquette rich in gestural nu-
               ance, which inspired contemporary court</p>
           
            <pb facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_024.jpg" n="24" xml:id="img_0024"/>
            <p>
               behavior. They articulated a feminine posi-
               tion to which men could respond. Both pro-
               vincials, they described a life outside the
               court that seemed raw and exotic to the in-
               bred Heian court. Murasaki characterized
               the province/capital dichotomy when she
               wrote about Genji’s scrolls made during his
               exile on the Suma coast: “Amid intense ex-
               citement . . . (they) produced a roll con-
               taining Genji’s sketches at Suma .
               masterly a hand working at complete leisure
               and far from the distracting influences
               which beset an artist in town. They saw so
               vividly presented both the stem manner of
               his life there and in some sort the feelings
               which this rustic life had aroused in
               everyone used to every luxury and in-
               dulgence.”" Soon after The Tale of Genji
               appeared at court, Genji was adopted as a
               Shinto deity.15</p>
               <p>Sei’s open competition with men—even
               with those of a higher rank—gave the Heian
               court a model of an openly combative
               woman who refused to acquiesce to the pre-
               vailing notions of female propriety. She
               writes with glee how she embarrassed the
               minister Nobutsune (who was Murasaki's
               cousin): “One day when Nobutsune was
               serving as Intendant in the Office of Palace
               Works he sent a sketch to one of the crafts-
               men explaining how a certain piece of work
               should be done. Kindly execute in this
               fashion,’ he added in Chinese characters. I
               happened to notice the piece of paper and it
               was the most preposterous writing 1 had
               ever seen. Next to his message I wrote, 'If
               you do the work in this style, it will certainly
               turn out strangely.” The document found its
               way to the imperial apartment, and every-
               one who saw it was greatly amused—except,
               of course, Nobutsune, who was furious and
               after this held a grudge against me." 16</p>
               <p>Murasaki acidly noted in her diary, “Some-
               one [Sei who makes such an effort to be dif-
               ferent from others is bound to fall in
               people’s esteem and 1 can only think her
               future will be a hard one. She is a gifted
               woman, to be sure . . . how can things turn
               out well for such a woman?”17</p>
               <p>Sei and Murasaki challenged the religious
               as well as social assumptions of their society.
               They shaped as well as recorded their civ-
               ilization; there are few other instances of
               such literary power and evocativeness.
               History regards Heian Japan as a golden
               age whose achievements rank with those of
               Byzantium, Athens, and Renaissance Italy.
               T’he work of these two women recorded that
               period with greater depth and insight than
               any other contemporary cultural products,
               so much so that virtually all that is known
               about the period has been learned from their
               writings.</p>
               <p>Two questions remain: What is the
               deeper meaning of a golden age”? What
               was Murasaki’s and Sei’s relationship to the
               golden age they so consummately character-
               ized? An age is golden” in contrast to the
               generations of dross preceding and suc-
               ceeding it. An age is golden” because cul-
               tural achievements complement political
               strength and together give the impression of
               an ideal social harmony. Cultural achieve-
               ments in Heian were enjoyed, as is so often
               the case, by a few at the expense of many.
               Like two facing mirrors, the literature re-
               flected the glory of the ruling class and vice
               versa. But there were some distortions. In
               reading these works—as literature or as his-
               torical documents—there is a striking
               double edge to each. Murasaki’s choice to
               place her tale in the indeterminate past sug-
               gests two contradictory readings: Did the
               paucity of excitement and intelligence at the
               court encourage her to invent a perfect and
               brilliant hero, or was court life so thrilling
               she was inspired to glorify it? Whichever,
               there is throughout Murasaki’s novel a wist-
               fulness of “wouldn’t it be nice if it were this
               way which suggests dissatisfaction with the
               way it was, and the characters still alive at
               the close of the novel are so morally and in-
               tellectually inferior to Genji that her conclu-
               sion has a hopeless tone. Sei’s devotion to
               the imperial family and her contempt for the
               lower orders (an attitude that prompted a
               Japanese scholar to call her a “spiritual
               cripple”18) reveals a mindset that for the
               Heian court was good breeding but for the
               modern reader is patronizing and blind.
               Sei’s circumscribed vision and partisanship
               today says more about the exclusion of the
               lower classes from Heian society by omission
               than do the scanty histories from the period.</p>
               <p>Sei’s and Murasaki’s historical reflections
               are powerful and moving, simultaneously
               evocative of Heian pageantry and of the
               sadness of a society where leisure and
               culture was reserved for a chosen few. No
               culture, no golden age wants to be tar-
               nished by an enumeration of its prejudices
               and oppressions. Murasaki’s and Sei’s lit-
               erature both criticized and apotheosized
               their era and, in doing so, exemplifies the
               straits of literature and history.</p>
            <p>
               1. Walter Benjamin, Illuminations (New York:
               Schocken Books, 1969). From “Theses on the
               Philosophy of History, p. 256.<lb/>
               2. Ivan Morris, The World of the Shining
               Prince (New York: Alfred Knopf, 1964), p. 83<lb/>
               3. Ibid.<lb/>
               4. Morris, p. 199.<lb/>
               5. Morris, p. 195.<lb/>
               6. Sei Shonagon, The Pillow Book of Sei Shon-
               agon (Harmondsworth, England: Penguin
               Books, 1967). Translated and edited by Ivan
               Morris.<lb/>
               7. Sei Shonagon, p. 39.<lb/>
               8. Marasaki Shikibu, The Tale of Genji (New
               York: Alfred Knopf, 1977). Translated by
               Edward Seidensticker.<lb/>
               9. Morris, p. 90.<lb/>
               10. Quoted in Morris, p. 45.<lb/>
               11. Morris, p. 44.<lb/>
               12. Murasaki Shikibu.<lb/>
               13. Donald Keene, in Half the World, edited by
               Arnold Toynbee (New York: Holt, Rinehart
               and Winston, 1973), p. 255.<lb/>
               14. Murasaki Shikibu.<lb/>
               15. Parker Tyler, “Prince Genji: The Hero and
               His Culture, Art News, Nov., 1958, p. 180.<lb/>
               16. Sei Shonagon.<lb/>
               17. Murasaki quoted in introduction to Shon-
               agon by Morris.<lb/>
               18. Morris, introduction to Shonagon.<lb/>
            </p>
               <p>References</p>
               <p>Hall, J. W., Japan. New York: Delta, 1970.
               Keene, D., Japanese Literature. New York:
               Grove Press, 1955.</p>
               <p>Sansom, G. B., The Western World and Japan.
               New York: Random House. 1973.</p>
            <p>
               Carrie Rickey writes about movies and lives in New
               York.</p>
            </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
