<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Apron ... </title>
            <author>Elli Siskind</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_074.jpg"
               n="74" xml:id="img_0074"/>
            <head><title>The Apron... Status Symbol ... or Stitchery Sample?</title></head>
            <byline>Elli Siskind</byline>
            <p>The earliest aprons wove a shield of magical strength about the women who wore them,
               sym bolizing fertility. A Great Moth er figurine, the “Venus of Les pugne,” 14,000
               B.C., wears an apron beneath her voluptuous buttocks. She is carved of ivory though
               the apron proclaiming her fecundity was probably wo- ven of pierced cowrie shells.
               (1)</p>
            <p>Among Celts and other early English and European tribes aprons vied with body paint
               as ceremonial costume and decora tion. On every continent triba women wove aprons of
               feathers, bark and leaves, and patternec them with natural dyes. Aborig- ine virgins
               in Australia still wea aprons of leaves. (2) The fig lea worn by the mythological Eve
               was probably a fertility apron rather than a modesty panel. Missionaries, acting upon
               the body-is-bad principle, replaced these natural materials with cheap cotton
               pinafores, called in Polynesia the Pina Foa, and sub- stituted Victorian needlework
               foi traditional “pagan” designs. (3)</p>
            <p>European peasant women cre- ated brilliantly colored and em- broidered aprons. In
               Italy long strips of plaid wool or silk edged with embroidered borders were worked in
               stitchery and worn wrapped around the waist, over- lapping in front. The Koteny made
               by Hungarian women was highly prized and passed down ir the family. The Indianapolis
               Children’s Museum owns a Hun- garian apron exuberantly worked with billowing scarlet
               and red violet poppies and finished with hand-knotted fringe on an em broidered blue
               and green ground. In Rumania style called for nar row rectangles of gold, black and
               red horizontal stripes, worn back and front. A Czech apron in rainbow silks displays
               the jac- quard brocade weaving tech nique. Swedish and Swiss aprons were gaily
               striped, identifying the parish of the wearer (4)</p>
            <p>A gypsy woman can ostracize a male member of the tribe by touching or covering him
               with her apron or katrinsa which sym bolizes to the tribe the marime or unclean
               status of the lower half of a woman’s body. (5) In the American folk song “Careles
               Love” the apron is a baromete of virginity lost and the woman’ loss of esteem among
               males seek ing wives.</p>
            <quote>Once 1 wore my apron low . . and you came by my door . . Now I wear my apron
               high. . and you come to my door and pass on by . ..</quote>
            <p>In Elizabethan England aprons came into fashion. Wealthy, ti- tled women created a
               frivolous parody of the working apron, stitched in white lawn and ex pensive Franch
               lace. During the reign of Queen Anne, wedding gowns were not complete without a
               lace-point apron secured with a jeweled pin. (6)</p>
            <p>In Victorian England the wife and mother role became separ- ated from household
               chores for affluent women. A checked ging ham apron was worn by the cook. Kitchen
               servants and par lormaids wore floor-length white aprons with huge skirts and bibs
               Ladies sat at their needlework with dainty aprons, announcing their privileged class
               by the apron’s impracticality. (7)</p>
            <p>Personal decoration was dis- couraged as vanity by early American settlers. Pilgrim
               wom en wore snowy-white, full-length aprons set against plain green brown and dull
               purple homespur skirts.(8) Pioneer women’s apron were tucked many times dowr the
               front. This enabled the hems, which burnt as they swept the hearth, to be turned up
               again and again.(9) Aprons of a century ago still carry stains that bear witness to
               the enduring nature of woman’s work. Middle-class American women in the early
               nineteenth century wore aprons with their fine Sunday gowns. Those over 30 and/or
               married were expected to wear black or white, and as a woman grew old- er, black was
               her only option Silk or satin or other fine ma- terials such as dimity and chiffon
               could be used to make Sunday aprons and hand-decorating demonstrated a woman’s wifely
               skills.(10)</p>
            <p>Aprons dwindled in size as in- dustrialization freed women from the making of dyes,
               soap, condiments and jellies—not to mention the killing of chickens. Although
               contemporary women have neither the practical nor the institutionalized need for
               apron- wearing, by rediscovering the apron in the history of the decor- ative arts,
               we add to the rich fab- ric of the emerging history of women’s art.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1.Hilaire Hiler, From Nudity to Raiment (Paris: Librairie de France, 1929), p.
                  36.</item>
               <item>2.Ibid., p. 80.</item>
               <item>3.Ibid.</item>
               <item>4.Mary Evans, Costume Throughout the Ages (Phila- delphia: J. B. Lippincott
                  Co., 1930), pp. 202-245.</item>
               <item>5.Anne Sutherland, Gypsies: The Hidden Americans (New York: Free Press, 1975),
                  p. 103.</item>
               <item>6.Lucy Barton, Historic Cos tume for the Stage (Boston: Baker Co., 1935), p.
                  230.</item>
               <item>7.Ibid., p. 320.</item>
               <item>8.Alice Morse Earle, Two Cen- turies of Costume in America (New York: The
                  Macmillan Co., 1910), p. 172.</item>
               <item>9.Told to me by Dixie Clark Connor Prairie Farms, In- dianapolis,
                  Indiana.</item>
               <item>10.Told to me by Mary Jane Teeter, Curator of Victorian Art, Children’s Museum
                  of Indianapolis, Indianapolis. Indiana.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <p>Elli Siskind, originally from Kansas and points West, lives in Indianapolis. She does
            acrylic paintings, including a recent series of laundromat pieces about women's
            work.</p>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
