<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Apron ... Status Symbol ... or Stitchery Sample?</title>
            <author>Elli Siskind</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb
            facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_074.jpg"
            n="74" xml:id="img_0074"/>

         <div>
            <head><title>The Apron... Status Symbol ... or Stitchery Sample?</title></head>
            <byline>Elli Siskind</byline>
            <p>The earliest aprons wove a shield of magical strength about the women who wore them,
               symbolizing fertility. A Great Mother figurine, the "Venus of Lespugne," 14,000 B.C.,
               wears an apron beneath her voluptuous buttocks. She is carved of ivory though the
               apron proclaiming her fecundity was probably woven of pierced cowrie shells.
                  <note>1.Hilaire Hiler, <title>From Nudity to Raiment</title> (Paris: Librairie de
                  France, 1929), p. 36.</note></p>
            <p>Among Celts and other early English and European tribes aprons vied with body paint
               as ceremonial costume and decoration. On every continent tribal women wove aprons of
               feathers, bark and leaves, and patterned them with natural dyes. Aborigine virgins in
               Australia still wear aprons of leaves. <note>2.Ibid., p. 80.</note> The fig leaf worn
               by the mythological Eve was probably a fertility apron rather than a modesty panel.
               Missionaries, acting upon the body-is-bad principle, replaced these natural materials
               with cheap cotton pinafores, called in Polynesia the Pina Foa, and substituted
               Victorian needlework for traditional "pagan" designs. <note>3.Ibid.</note></p>
            <p>European peasant women created brilliantly colored and embroidered aprons. In Italy
               long strips of plaid wool or silk edged with embroidered borders were worked in
               stitchery and worn wrapped around the waist, overlapping in front. The <hi
                  rend="italic">Koteny</hi> made by Hungarian women was highly prized and passed
               down in the family. The Indianapolis Children's Museum owns a Hungarian apron
               exuberantly worked with billowing scarlet and red violet poppies and finished with
               hand-knotted fringe on an embroidered blue and green ground. In Rumania style called
               for narrow rectangles of gold, black and red horizontal stripes, worn back and front.
               A Czech apron in rainbow silks displays the jacquard brocade weaving technique.
               Swedish and Swiss aprons were gaily striped, identifying the parish of the wearer.
                  <note>4. Mary Evans, <title>Costume Throughout the Ages</title> (Philadelphia: J.
                  B. Lippincott Co., 1930), pp. 202-245.</note></p>
            <p>A gypsy woman can ostracize a male member of the tribe by touching or covering him
               with her apron or katrinsa which symbolizes to the tribe the marime or unclean status
               of the lower half of a woman's body. <note>5.Anne Sutherland, <title>Gypsies: The
                     Hidden Americans</title> (New York: Free Press, 1975), p. 103.</note> In the
               American folk song "Careles Love" the apron is a barometer of virginity lost and the
               woman's loss of esteem among males seek ing wives.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Once I wore my apron low . .</l>
               <l>and you came by my door . .</l>
               <l>Now I wear my apron high. .</l>
               <l>and you come to my door and</l>
               <l>pass on by . ..</l>
            </lg>
            <p>In Elizabethan England aprons came into fashion. Wealthy, titled women created a
               frivolous parody of the working apron, stitched in white lawn and expensive Franch
               lace. During the reign of Queen Anne, wedding gowns were not complete without a
               lace-point apron secured with a jeweled pin. <note>6. Lucy Barton, <title>Historic
                     Costume for the Stage</title> (Boston: Baker Co., 1935), p. 230.</note></p>
            <p>In Victorian England the wife and mother role became separated from household chores
               for affluent women. A checked gingham apron was worn by the cook. Kitchen servants
               and parlormaids wore floor-length white aprons with huge skirts and bibs. Ladies sat
               at their needlework with dainty aprons, announcing their privileged class by the
               apron's impracticality. <note>7. Ibid., p. 320.</note></p>
            <p>Personal decoration was discouraged as vanity by early American settlers. Pilgrim
               women wore snowy-white, full-length aprons set against plain green brown and dull
               purple homespun skirts. <note>8.Alice Morse Earle, Two Centuries of Costume in
                  America (New York: The Macmillan Co., 1910), p. 172.</note> Pioneer women's apron
               were tucked many times down the front. This enabled the hems, which burnt as they
               swept the hearth, to be turned up again and again.<note>9.Told to me by Dixie Clark,
                  Connor Prairie Farms, Indianapolis, Indiana.</note> Aprons of a century ago still
               carry stains that bear witness to the enduring nature of woman's work. Middle-class
               American women in the early nineteenth century wore aprons with their fine Sunday
               gowns. Those over 30 and/or married were expected to wear black or white, and as a
               woman grew older, black was her only option. Silk or satin or other fine materials
               such as dimity and chiffon could be used to make Sunday aprons and hand-decorating
               demonstrated a woman's wifely skills. <note>10. Told to me by Mary Jane Teeter,
                  Curator of Victorian Art, Children's Museum of Indianapolis, Indianapolis.
                  Indiana.</note></p>
            <p>Aprons dwindled in size as industrialization freed women from the making of dyes,
               soap, condiments and jellies—not to mention the killing of chickens. Although
               contemporary women have neither the practical nor the institutionalized need for
               apron-wearing, by rediscovering the apron in the history of the decorative arts, we
               add to the rich fabric of the emerging history of women's art.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <p>Elli Siskind, originally from Kansas and points West, lives in Indianapolis. She does
            acrylic paintings, including a recent series of laundromat pieces about women's
            work.</p>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
