<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TITLE</title>
            <author>AUTHOR</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021- Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-23)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>[ISSUE TITLE]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_106.jpg"
               n="103" xml:id="img_0106"/>
            <head><title>Women's Art in Village India</title></head>
            <p> In discussing the articles we received on different aspects of women and their art
               in village India, we noticed a recurring theme: artmaking in India is in a state of
               flux. Colonization, industrialization and the impingement of the world market have in
               fluenced choices of material, means of production, the meaning of ritual content, the
               relationship between artist and consumer and the status of the artist in society.
               Women’s traditional arts such as embroidery and ritual painting on walls and ground,
               themselves often affected by such changes, co-exist with nontraditional forms such as
               painting on paper produced specifically for the market. Nontraditional paintings by
               women from Mithila have received recent attention through articles, a book and ex-
               hibitions in India and Europe.</p>
            <p>As we discussed the articles submitted to us, a dilemma became apparent since two
               distinct interpretations of the meaning of Mithila paintings in terms of ritual
               content and social significance emerged. It seemed to us that we were seeing a
               demonstration of ways in which feminist analyses develop and some of the problems in
               making an accurate woman-centered description. Véquaud and Stendhall <note>Yves
                  Véquaud, Women Artists of Mithila (London: Thames and Hudson, 1977); Renate
                  Stendhal, “Ein Volk von Malerinnen” (“A Nation of Women Artists”), Emma, No. 6
                  (June 1977), pp. 50-53. Thanks to Tobe Levin for her translation of this
                  article.</note> connected the Maithil<note>2Maithil is the adjective form of
                  Mithila. ”Personal communication, Tamara Wasserman—E. W.</note> women to a
               tradition of independent women artists who perpetuated ancient matriarchal customs.
               We were attracted to their picture of Maithil women as “a nation of women artists.”
               But as editors we felt that this analysis, in the light of fieldwork observations by
               feminist sociologists, did not adequately reflect the extremely circum- scribed life
               typical of women in village India. We noted, moreover, that the traditional painters
               of Mithila were women of the upper caste, the caste which most strictly requires
               seclusion of women and absolute obedience to men.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, the sociological writers tended not to emphasize some of the
               strengths of women, even in this extremely segregated (sex and caste) society. Women
               developed their creativity, forming women’s art traditions outside of male control.
               Most prized by the women themselves is the work derived from weaving raffia or
               embroidering cloth. Paintings exist in a category other than art; they are sacred
               acts in themselves. But they are exclusively women’s work—and there lies their
               interest to us, as we search for examples of traditional women’s art, their designs,
               materials and techniques.</p>
            <p>Why a connection was made to matriarchal traditions becomes clearer if we note that
               in southern India, at least, the ritual wall and ground paintings are made in honor
               of the goddess Lakshmi, who is throughout Hindu India a patron goddess of women.?
               Thus the paintings reinforce female concerns and a sense of female community.
               However, this is the sense of communi- ty that occurs when one group is
               systematically oppressed. A visually rich and religiously meaningful woman’s art
               exists. But this does not deny, to our dismay, the real exclusion of women of
               Mithila, as of other areas of India, from full control of their lives. —The
               Editors</p>
         </div>
         <pb
            facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_107.jpg"
            n="104" xml:id="img_0107"/>
         <div>

            <head>WOMEN OF INDIA</head>
            <byline>Sharon Wood</byline>
            <p> Despite the complex and heterogeneous nature of Indian society, there are certain
               consistent attitudes and values. Such is the case with the status of women: their
               positions relative to men and to other women, and the practical effects of prevailing
               atti tudes on their lives.</p>
            <p>The following description of the roles open to the majority of women is based on my
               own observations and written sources, Four-fifths of the population are caste Hindus,
               and unless otherwise indicated, 1 am referring to caste Hindu women. The family, not
               the individual, is the primary economic and social unit in India. A joint family,
               where married sons, their wives, unmarried daughters and parents live together, is
               the Indian ideal. Most women’s lives are spent within the family court yard while men
               circulate between home, fields, markets, villages and cities. Home is where children
               first learn to perpetuate the subordination of women.</p>
            <p>Inferior status is more evident in North India where many women still practice a
               modified form of Purdah, seclusion at home and covering one’s face in the presence of
               most men. Purdah became popular during the Muslim rule (approximatel 1200-1700) and
               was practiced among royal and upper-class women. Centuries of foreign invaders
               attacked the North, but prior to the British, few penetrated to the South, so it was
               not necessary to “protect” women by hiding them.</p>

            <div>
               <head>TOO BAD IT’S A GIRL</head>
               <p>Parents welcome the birth of their first daughter as a manifestation of the
                  goddess of wealth. It is considered pious to give away a daughter in marriage, but
                  with each daughter a dowry must be given, and succeeding daughters mean
                  substantial, perhaps ruinous expense. Dowries, the only property traditionally
                  allowed to women, supposedly guarantee their maintenance in their husband’s family
                  and serve as a tangible measure of economic strength to the community at large.
                  There is considerable social pressure to continue the dowry system despite its
                  illegality. Dowries are given by some families who know that the law is
                  unenforceable, and by many more who do not know of the law’s existence.</p>
               <p>Sons are preferred because they will remain to contribute financial and physical
                  support, perpetuate the family line and per- form necessary funeral rites for
                  their parents.</p>
               <p>Considered temporary residents, daughters are frequently reminded that they will
                  marry and go to live with their in-laws. Their share of household work depends on
                  the economic standing and jati (lineage group within broad caste categories) of
                  their family. Regardless of caste, all women are expected to know how to cook,
                  clean and care for children.</p>
               <p>Traditional education, memorization of religious texts, was denied to women and
                  the lower castes. Modern education, though prestigious, is an economic luxury for
                  women.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>THE ARRANGEMENT</head>
               <p>The major event in most people’s lives is marriage. Families select potential
                  spouses to strengthen or improve their social posi- tion. In North India this
                  takes the form of affiliation between families in distant villages, and in South
                  India consolidation within a local setting. Thus, a North Indian bride faces total
                  strangers, perhaps a new language, while a South Indian bride may marry someone as
                  familiar as a cousin. The transition from parents’ to in-laws’ home is rarely as
                  traumatic for her.</p>
               <p>There are a few socially acceptable alternatives to marriage for upper- or
                  middle-caste women. One is to secure employment in a “proper” profession,
                     <note>The ideal profession is medicine. Doctors may defy almost all domestic
                     and societal restrictions and still are highly respected. Nursing, however, is
                     undesirable because it is associated with traditional midwifery, a low-caste
                     profession.</note> such as teaching, and continue to live with their parents,
                  celibate, in a social limbo, their public behavior subject to scrutiny and
                  criticism by’neighbors. A more drastic but traditional choice, available to
                  malcontents and nonconform- ists of both sexes, is to leave society and become a
                  religious devotee: a hard and often solitary life. Most women get married.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>DEVOTION, DUTY AND SACRIFICE</head>
               <p>By adolescence, young people have witnessed many marriages and know their
                  obligations and expectations. A bride should serve her mother-in-law, respectfully
                  avoid older men, show symbolic and real deference to her husband and have babies.
                  She expects to be ill- treated by her mother-in-law, to have little in common with
                  her husband except sex and to be allowed occasional visits to her parents home
                  where she is a privileged guest.</p>
               <p>During menstruation women are considered unclean and not allowed to cook. Instead
                  of resting indoors, they frequently work harder than usual outdoors. As protectors
                  of domestic purity, they are expected to be more ritually strict than men. Defy-
                  ing such restrictions is one way women express their anger.</p>
               <p>Childbirth is ritually unclean. Low-caste midwives, otherwise shunned, enter homes
                  of all castes and assist. Their freedom of movement is envied by upper-caste women
                  who haven’t fully rationalized and internalized their own sequestered lives.</p>
               <p>On almost every social level, a wife’s status improves with the birth of a child,
                  especially a son. Children are wives’ social insur- ance and the most acceptable
                  focus of their attention and affection. If women do not produce sons, husbands who
                  can afford it take another wife. Divorce is an unspeakable disgrace, so the first
                  wife stays on, adjusting to her lowered status as a barren woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>THE LATER YEARS</head>
               <p>Maintenance of a joint family demonstrates stability, reliability and strength to
                  the community, which rewards the family with prestige and economic opportunities.
                  But many forces work against its continuance: difficulties of integrating brides
                  into the household, rivalries between nuclear units and possible conflict between
                  brothers over family property. These find expres- sion in battles between mothers-
                  and daughters-in-law and among brothers’ wives. Quarrels among women are an
                  acceptable release of tension. It is believed that women drive apart families
                  which would otherwise remain peaceably united.</p>
               <p>In matters beyond the domestic sphere, women are expected to indirectly wield what
                  power they have through the men in their family. A wife’s status depends on her
                  husband’s position in the household: after his mother, the oldest son’s wife has
                  the most authority. Some widowed mothers have considerable influence over their
                  sons, much to the displeasure of the sons’ wives.</p>


               <pb
                  facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_108.jpg"
                  n="105" xml:id="img_0108"/>
               <p> Antagonism between mothers- and daughters-in-law keeps them divided, competing
                  for their son/husband’s support, and diverts them from more fundamental sources of
                  discontent inherent in the repressive hierarchy of family relations.</p>
               <p>Age is respected, and unless widowed, women can attain a secure and powerful
                  position in their later years.</p>
               <p>Treatment of widows varies widely depending on their age, relations with their
                  children and family resources. Young, childless widows dependent on their in-laws
                  are undoubtedly treated the worst. Widows’ heads are shaved, their glass jewelry
                  broken and their saris replaced by permanent mourning clothes. Widows are not
                  allowed to remarry. A proper widow should devote herself to religion and quietly
                  pine away. Those with the means, interest and determination become involved in
                  com- munity social services or charity work.</p>
               <p>In later life, people are encouraged to turn to religion, the selection and
                  practice of which provide more personal choice than any other aspect of Indian
                  life. Continued participation in family and social activities is frowned upon.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>ANOTHER WORLD</head>
               <p>Low-caste, Harijan (untouchable) and tribal women are more independent
                  economically, socially and ritually. Poverty forces them to work, and although
                  they receive lower salaries than men, the result is freedom unknown to their
                  upper-caste sisters. They choose their husbands, leave or divorce them and remarry
                  if widowed. This is possible because these people are so poor that a woman’s
                  wage-earning ability is of great value. But Harijan and tribal women must contend
                  with real and threatened vio- lence, insults and humiliation due to their caste
                  ranking.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>HOW MUCH CONTROL DO WOMEN HAVE OVER THEIR OWN LIVES?</head>
               <p>In one lifetime, women fulfill a number of assigned roles, each with its own
                  privileges and constraints. Transitions between roles are often abrupt, making it
                  very difficult to retain and consolidate power or authority.</p>
               <p>Upper-caste women have more economic security and community respect, accompanied
                  by physical and social confinement.</p>
               <p>Lower-caste women have the possibility of choice in their domestic relations, but
                  live and die in crushing poverty.</p>
               <p>A U.N. report notes that on a worldwide basis</p>
               <p>.. .even where women have made major gains in acquiring access to knowledge,
                  training and economic independence, their share in decision-making in both the
                  family and in public life—that is, their share of political power—appears to lag
                  behind their share in other resources. <note>2U.N. Department of Economic and
                     Social Affairs, Status of Women and Family Planning.</note></p>
            </div>

            <div>
               <list>
                  <item>Beteille, Andre and Madan, T.N., Encounter and Experience: Personal Accounts
                     of Fieldwork. Delhi: Vikas Publishing House, 1975.</item>
                  <item> Cormack, Margaret, The Hindu Woman. New York: Teachers College, Columbia
                     University, 1953.</item>
                  <item>Das, Frieda Hauswirth, Purdah: The Status of Indian Women. New York: Vangard
                     Press, 1932. Mandelbaum, D. G., Society in India. Berkeley: University of
                     California Press, 1970, vol. 1 and 2.</item>
                  <item>Masani, Mehra, “Indian Women: Second Class Citizens,” Illustrated Weekly of
                     India, Vol. XCVI, No. 9, March 2, 1975, p. 4</item>
                  <item>Mies, Maria, “Indian Women and Leadership,” Bulletin of Concerned Asian
                     Scholars, Vol. 7, No. 1, January-March 1975, p. 56.</item>
                  <item>Minturn, L. and Hitchcock, J., The Rajputs of Khalapur, India. New York:
                     John Wiley and Sons, 1966.</item>
                  <item>Mody, Susan and Mhatre, Sharayu, “Sexual Class in India,” Bulletin of
                     Concerned Asian Scholars, Vol. 7, No. 1, January-March 1975, p. 49.</item>
                  <item>Omvedt, Gail, “Caste, Class, and Women’s Liberation in India,” Bulletin of
                     Concerned Asian Scholars, Vol. 7, No. 1, January-March 1975, p. 43.</item>
                  <item>U.N. Department of Economic and Social Affairs, Status of Women and Family
                     Planning. New York: U.N. Publications, 1975.</item>
               </list>
            </div>

            <div>
               <head>On The Status of Women in India</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Contrary to demographic averages, the ratio of men to women in India is
                     100:93. This is attributed to the neglect of females.</item>
                  <item>90% of abandoned babies in Delhi, the Indian capital, are female.§</item>
                  <item>The Indian Constitution proposed universal, free, compulsory edu- cation but
                     postponed it to 1965, then to 1981. In 1971, 97% of boys and 62% of girls aged
                     6 to 11 years were enrolled in school. Actual attendance figures were not
                     available.</item>
                  <item>60% of all children drop out of school before the fifth grade.†</item>
                  <item>39% of the male and 18.7% of the female population were literate in 1974;
                     40% of the “literate” women can only sign their names.</item>
                  <item>4/5 of the population is rural; 13.2% of rural women are literate. Women
                     formed 18% of the work force in 1971, a decrease from 27 in 1961. The official
                     explanation was “economic stagnation,” but employers use protective labor laws
                     as excuses to not hire women.7</item>
                  <item>80% of working women are agricultural laborers, 15% work in fac- tories or
                     plantations, or as unorganized laborers such as bidi (cig- arette) makers,
                     hawkers, and domestic servants. 90% of working women are illiterate.7</item>
                  <item>5% of urban women who matriculated and 20% of university grad- uates find
                     work; only 0.4% of Indian women hold degrees.</item>
                  <item>50% of employed, educated women teach primary school, 15% are clerks or
                     typists, 15% teach secondary school, 7% are nurses and 10% are doctors,
                     lawyers, college teachers, artists, administrators, etc.†</item>
                  <item>15% of all rural women are married before 14 years of age.</item>
                  <item>71% of women aged 15 to 19 were married, widowed or divorced in
                     1961.§</item>
                  <item>100,000 women, mostly widows, aged 20 to 45, become destitute every year due
                     to lack of work.</item>
                  <item>Life expectancy for men is 51.3 years, and 49.6 for women.</item>
                  <item>§U.N. Department of Economic and Social Affairs, Status of Wom- en and
                     Family Planning (New York: U.N. Publications, 1975).</item>
                  <item>Masani, Mehra, “Indian Women: Second Class Citizens,” Illus- trated Weekly
                     of India, Vol. XCVI, No. 9 (March 2, 1975), p. 4.</item>
                  <item>tTimes of India, sec. 1. p. 1 (June 7. 19751.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_109.jpg"
               n="106" xml:id="img_0109"/>

            <head>Embroidery from the Northwest</head>
            <byline>Zette Emmons</byline>
            <p>In the 700,000 villages of India, the peasant woman is born into a set of prescribed
               rituals which she is responsible for maintaining and transmitting. Traditional art is
               one form these rituals take; in Northwestern India, an area historically rich in all
               kinds of textiles, peasant women embroider. A classification of textiles made in
               India for domestic use includes “skilled work of weavers and dyers, who work close to
               large market towns; articles of luxury made under court patronage or in the court
               tradition; folk embroidery; and fabrics of the aborigina tribes.”<note>John Irwin,
                  Textiles and Ornaments of India (New York: The Museum of Modern Art, 1956), p.
                  29</note> The first two forms of production are dominated by male weavers and
               craftsmen working in a commercial structure. The fourth is outside the mainstream of
               Indian village life, though folk embroidery draws upon many aboriginal antecedents
               which have become tangled with Islamic and Hindu influences.</p>
            <p>The depth of religious feeling and devotion that permeates Indian village life does
               not exist in the West in any comparable way, and it is fron this regard for the
               deities that the impulse to create something beautiful and worthy seems to come.
               Outer and inner worlds are merged in a relationship kept flowing and harmonious by
               the constant application of visible symbols and signs. Everything is part of
               everything else; there is none of the “disconnectedness” that is so much a part of
               life in the West. When the woman embroiders, she is conscious of the decorativenes of
               what she does, but she also has the satisfaction of honoring the world of the spirits
               residing in the plants and animals which she imitates in thread. Even the poorest
               village woman is capable of making her life more bearable and secure by the
               application of decoration to her house on herself. A Krishna proverb which applies to
               village women at work is—“I take the form desired by my worshippers.” <note>Anand,
                  Mulk Raj, “The Hand and the Heart,” MARG (Bombay: Marg Publications, 1969), p.
                  6.</note></p>
            <p>Women wear blouses, full skirts and shawls, all heavily embroidered. They spend their
               spare time embroidering not only their own clothing or trousseaus for their
               daughters, but also natis (children s headdresses), toranas (wall hangings), animal
               trappings and small bags for carrying jewelry and other small items. To wear someone
               else’s clothing would be unthinkable. When the wearer dies or when a garment is worn
               out, the old garment is cast off.</p>
            <p>Patterns to be embroidered are drawn onto cloth, which is worked in flat sections and
               sewn together when finished. Chain, cross and but- tonhole stitches cover the surface
               with patterns; satin stitching fills large areas with color. Small mirrors or pieces
               of mica are used extensively, interspersed fancifully with the embroidery. Mirrors
               also decorate walls, furniture and even chicken coops. They are not only attractive.
               flashing in the sun, but also frighten away demons.</p>
            <p>In the designs of peasant women in all parts of India, the essences of the animals,
               flowers and gods are revealed, emphasized by repetition. Dots, triangles and lines
               are arranged in panels surrounding abstracted symbols and objects. Even buses,
               bicycles and airplanes may be incor- porated into the work. The sense of color is
               more pronounced in the Northwest than in any other part of India. Traditional dyes
               have been derived from indigo, cochineal (red made from crushed insect bodies), iron
               filings (black), saffron and various other plants yielding yellows and oranges. Pupul
               Jayaker of the All-India Handicrafts Board describes the emotional content for
               peasant women of the colors they use.</p>
            <quote>Red was the color of Chunari, a tie-dyed sari, and was the symbol of sohog, the
               first days of marriage and love-play. It was the garment worn by the Abhisarika, the
               young woman seeking in the darkness of night her waiting beloved. Saffron or gerua
               was the color of Vasant, of spring, of young mango blossoms, of swarms of bees, of
               southern winds and the passionate cry of mating birds. Maroon and black were the
               colors of mourning. Blue or nil, the color of indigo, was also the color of Krishna,
               the cowherd child-god who bore the name of Navjaldhar—he who is of that color, that
               of the newly formed cloud, dormant with the darkness that is rain. But there was
               another blue, Hari nil, or the color of water which is reflecting a clear spring sky.
                  <note>Irwin, p. 20.</note></quote>
            <p>Daughters learn embroidery from their mothers who teach not only the techniques but
               the mythology that provides much of the subject mat ter for their images. Styles in
               the village gradually change according to the inclination of successive generations
               of artists and the impact of cultures. Islamic influence is seen in the geometric
               mazes and flower patterns; the bright colors and looser flowing lines are Hindu in
               origin.</p>
            <p>In the twentieth century industrialization has made inroads on every Indian village,
               no matter how remote. The survival of women’s arts, especially embroidery is being
               threatened by the adoption of bright, mill-made cloth. Synthetic dyes have largely
               replaced traditional ones. Im- itation printed or machine-sewn embroidery also
               appears now in place of the real thing. In recognition of this the All-India
               Handicrafts Board has provided incentives for maintaining quality by turning some
               previously noncommercial arts into quality-controlled commodities. This often has the
               opposite effect of the one intended, because the spark of life may go out of work
               produced for an unknown market whose needs are irrelevant to the rural craftsperson.
               Gandhi believed that it was possible and desirable for India to return to a
               village-centered economy in which the machine would be relegated to a minor role and
               the villager dictate the pace of life. Although his ideas are out of favor in
               present-day India, there is still a sentimental longing for that kind of simplicity
               in which the drive to create and survive comes out of the soil. The peasant woman
               holds on to the old ways for the time being, but there is no doubt that even she will
               become a victim, willing or not, of the changes that have afflicted the West since
               the industrial revolution.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <pb
               facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/issue04/images/Heresies_04_110.jpg"
               n="107" xml:id="img_0110"/>

            <head> Mithila Paintings</head>
            <byline>Erika Mosei</byline>

            <p>Mithila is a large region in North Bihar with an ancient high culture which is
               represented in the Sanskrit written tradition of the Brahman caste. The “painting
               women of Mithila” who belong to this elite sociocultural stratum are a numerical
               minority. They have more leisure time to practice their art skills than do women of
               lower castes.</p>
            <p>What is specific to the art of these Maithil women? To answer this question it is
               necessary to understand the traditional hierarchy of arts and artisans. As in our own
               culture, manual labor and handmade art such as sculpture or painting have, in spite
               of highly developed techniques and theories, been considered less prestigious
               professions than mental labor and intellectual art like poetry. In a male-dominated
               hierarchica society like India’s, the latter sphere is traditionally occupied, with
               few exceptions, by men of high rank. Tasks requiring skilled hands ar- relegated to
               low-caste occupational specialists</p>
            <p>In addition to the arts and crafts of specialists, nonprofessional domestic art is
               produced by women as part of their household duties. Orna mental decoration with
               symbolic meaning is made on festive occasions to beautify the home, household
               utensils, and those who live in the house. The numerous festivities of the life and
               calendar cycles, especially marriages, are functional occasions for the art of women.
               The most eye-catching of the domestic arts are the wall and floor drawings, two
               aspects of the total range of women’s traditional arts which use many media, styles
               and contents. Wall murals feature motifs of gods and goddesses, epic scenes, brides
               and grooms and fertility symbols. Floor designs are made with rice flour dissolved in
               water and drawn with the fingers to mark a kind of ground altar for household
               rituals. What is considered the ritual center of the drawing is covered very
               carefully with earth after ritual use so that no one will accidentally step on it.
               The other ornamental forms, however, remain exposed to the sun and rain.</p>
            <p>Objects of high aesthetic quality are created as gifts for friends and relatives and
               as donations to the gods. Such domestic art done by women is usually not highly
               esteemed. In fact the concept of art is usually not applied to it though its creative
               qualities equal those of classical art There are various explanations for the low
               prestige of women’s traditional domestic arts:</p>
            <p>The objects are primarily functional, having an everyday household use rather than
               being representative monuments of social prestige. In addition, symbolic items are
               prepared for one time use only in a specific ritual context</p>
            <p>The raw material out of which the art is made is usually regarded as being of little
               value because it is freely available, e.g., grass, mud. flowers and other organic
               material, self-prepared colors. Also, the materials tend not to be durable so that
               objects become unattractive within a short time. The objects are predominantly
               hand-worked. Highly developed tools and technologies are rarely used in their
               production. Thi kind of art is available without cost, a feature which tends to
               undermine its appreciation</p>
            <p>High-caste Brahman males may become defiled by doing manual labor; thus domestic work
               is left to low-caste servants and housewives. In this context, how was it possible
               that out of the mass of women in India a few could break out of the rigid traditional
               value system to become famous as a group in the world market of naive and folk art,
               producing paintings which sell as “Mithila paintings”?</p>
            <p>A clue to the answer lies in the word “market.” In 1967-1968, after a famine, the
               government of India carried out a relief program in North Bihar. At that time,
               various handicrafts were bought and women were encouraged to prepare sikki grass work
               and other traditional folk arts on payment. Pupul Jayakar, the woman who headed the
               Handicrafts and Handlooms Exports Corporation at that time in Delhi, introduced the
               idea of distributing handmade paper among village women so that they could transfer
               their traditional motifs from murals and floor designs or to paper and create
               marketable products. The All-India Handicrafts Board promoted this project. In
               response to a Western demand for naive and folk art with ritual and oriental themes,
               the Mithila paintings became commercially successful. Unlike the ritual traditional
               art forms, the paintings on paper are not symbolic forms of meditation and prayer,
               but are made explicitly in order to eamn money. (When the demand is there, they are
               produced daily.) This, at least, is the way the women themselves view their artistic
               achievements</p>
            <p>About 500 women in the region paint for the market. For most women painting is not
               the main source of family income. The money earned through painting is rarely
               available for personal use. In most cases, male members of the family collect and
               spend the money the women earn. But even though the earnings are not theirs to keep,
               most benefit from their work either psychologically or by eliciting what has rarely
               beer possible for them—social prestige and respect from male family members. (Three
               of the women received the highest prize, the “Nationa Award of Master-Craftsmen” from
               the All-India Handicrafts Board.) Together, the women painters of Mithila have
               achieved collective acclaim for their region</p>
            <p>The concepts of art and creativity in our Westem sense do not exist at all in this
               context. What we mean by traditional art is for these women a part of domestic ritual
               decoration, which extends far beyond the area of drawing and painting. Painting has
               been selected for promotion from the whole complex of domestic art skills because
               critical criteria have been brought in from the outside. These criteria, deduced from
               Western traditional art academic categories, value painting as highly-esteemed
               bourgeois art. Typical female skills like embroidery do not have much worth on such
               scales. The women of Mithila in fact value textile art skills and, above all, the
               fine weaving of sikki, higher than painting Interestingly, when formerly disregarded
               female work succeeds commercially, males join the ranks, and, in this case, even
               Brahman mer have acted as helpers, publicity agents or even as painters.</p>
            <p>The art of the women of Mithila is exemplary of an indigenous woman’s art as opposed
               to women’s art in the West which still, in the realm of "fine” arts, may be regarded
               as imitative of dominating male art styles. The ideology that male artists have been
               the major creative geniuses and that women have been the followers is usually
               accepted without question on the simple basis that there have been more famous male
               artists in the history of art. Only in some seemingly insignificant corners of the
               world has female creativity had the chance to develop without male competition,
               mainly in the domestic sphere</p>
         </div>

      </body>
      <back>
         <p>Sharon Wood is a student of film at San Francisco State. She traveled in India in 1974
            and plans to return to do further film work. 105</p>
         <p> Zete Emmons vas born in San Francisco and studied at the University of California at
            Berkeley. She spent 1971-1972 in India documenting folk art on a grant from Berkeley and
            presently lives in Kingston, R.I</p>
         <p> Erika Moser is a lecturer of visual anthropology at the South Asia Institute,
            University of Heidelberg, Germany. She is the Vice-President of the Society for Folk
            Arts Preservation, Inc.</p>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
