<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lucy Lippard</title>
            <author>3 Short Fictions</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
			<pb n='45'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_1_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>CORRESPONDENCE
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_1_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>BETWEEN
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_1_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>JACKI APPLE AND MARTHA WILSON
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_1_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>1973-1974
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>August 6, 1973
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>Dear Jacki Apple —... When I read the c. 7,500 catalogue I was
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>overjoyed to find that I am working alongside of a great many
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>other women, especially you. I am enclosing a resume, a descrip
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>tive list of works to date, and transcriptions of videotapes for you
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>to peruse. Also a photograph of me invading homosexual con
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>sciousness...
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>Recently I have been working on a piece called &quot;Male Imper
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>sonator” and on method acting concerns. I find that in front of
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>the camera I don’t feel particularly male or homosexual or what
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>ever; the identity shock comes when I look at the photographs of
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>myself in those roles. I am considering an actual invasion of
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>another identity: being picked up on Halifax waterfront as a
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>prostitute. That would involve real risk. I don’t think I would be
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>able to forget who I am, though, in spite of the immersion. To
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>lose myself was my original intent, I think, in December of 1971.
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>Also I used to worry about audience verification of my success a
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>good deal more than I do now. In the method acting exercise, I
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>wanted to track the images that would cause me to, say, cry
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>using a tape recorder, and I found that the intellectual process of
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>talking about emotion prohibited me from experiencing it.
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>Who are the &quot;four people” in a relationship? Do you distin
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>guish between real self and perception of self? How do you docu-
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>ment your interchanges, exchanges and redefinitions?...
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>Hope to meet you someday. If you’re ever in Halifax (ha)
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>you can sleep in my studio. Martha Wilson
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>August 26,1973
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_28' n='N028'/>Martha Wilson came to see me last Thursday. She is in the c.
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_29' n='N029'/>7,500 show with me, and after receiving her pieces and talking on
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_30' n='N030'/>the phone, I was excited about meeting her. We talked witl
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_31' n='N031'/>familiarity, not as strangers. Yet there wasn’t enough time — little
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_32' n='N032'/>more than an hour—allowing us to barely do anything more than
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_33' n='N033'/>become aware of each other’s positions.... We jumped from sub
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_34' n='N034'/>ject to subject like two people sampling a feast of appetizers,
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_35' n='N035'/>wanting to taste everything. She is full of curiosity and hunger,
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_36' n='N036'/>and buoyancy, asking questions, taking in information, talking
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_37' n='N037'/>rapidly, never resting
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_38' n='N038'/>She has an open face, quick to smile with her eyes as well as
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_39' n='N039'/>her mouth, a gamine quality with a sense of camp. Short shaggy
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_40' n='N040'/>yellow hair, plucked out, bleached eyebrows, fair skin. She wore
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_41' n='N041'/>pants and a short-sleeved printed shirt. She laughs easily, and has
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_42' n='N042'/>a natural extroverted sense of theater. Yet there is nothing theatri
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_43' n='N043'/>cal about her appearance.
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_44' n='N044'/>I liked her immensely. I also recognize something of myself
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_45' n='N045'/>in her, younger. The energy, independence, restlessness; the
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_46' n='N046'/>quickness of response, so direct yet somehow elusive, testing, try
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_47' n='N047'/>ing out life. I liked her optimism. She has a quality of motion and
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_48' n='N048'/>sunshine, and underneath a vulnerability. I hope we will be able
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_49' n='N049'/>to expand the relationship, write to each other, even make the
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_2_1_tl_50' n='N050'/>correspondence a piece in the future.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>August 26, 1973
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>Met Jacki Apple today, big surprise. A professional woman,
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>I expected a stringbean like myself. Jolted me to realize women
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>from different circumstances are doing similar experiments with
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>identity. She runs her own design room, draws a pair of pants,
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>chooses a fabric, a pattern cutter cuts it, two Hispanic women
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>sew it up. Her designs on Macy’s third floor, Sportswear. Any
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>way, I was shocked when I saw her: She looked professional all
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>over, eye makeup to high heels. I thought artists weren’t sup
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>posed to look like that. A sexist belief, something inherited from
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>Gertrude Stein, a woman has to be un-pretty to be taken as seri
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>ously as a man. I&quot;believe” this, questioned Jacki’s intelligence on
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>the basis of her appearance, even though I had read her work,
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>yikes.
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>September 18, 1973
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>Jacki —I xeroxed all the &quot;Selfportrait&quot; notes and am waiting for
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>an 8x10 enlargement to come back from the drugstore. Now
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>working on an idea sparked by Yvonne Rainer: images of my
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>perfection/deformity. Also a piece about the chemistry of camera
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>presence which came out of our conversation. Drop me a card.
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_3_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>Martha
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>October 14, 1973
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>Dear Martha—l’ve been trying to write you for weeks, no—
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>months, and this is the second letter l’ve started. I came away
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>from the hour we spent together feeling it was much too brief,
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>that we were like two people at a banquet wanting to taste every-
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>thing, with only enough time for a first bite. So the hour left me
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>stimulated and looking forward to corresponding. Part of my
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>excitement was in discovering another artist, a woman artist,
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>working with concepts similar to my own, and with the attitude
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>of experimentation which is so important to me. Another part of
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>it was your own personal openness and energy and curiosity.
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>The day your postcard arrived I had gone to the c. 7,500
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>opeñling at Moore College in Philadelphia. I have a number of
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>mixed feelings about the show, and it was an interesting experi
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>ence for me. One thing which I was surprised about (and prob
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>ably shouldn’t have been) was the discovery of how far from the
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>mainstream both of us are. Your perception of that from the cata
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>logue was more astute than mine. In the final analysis the work
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>that was most interesting to me, the work that was not “conven
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>tional&quot; or &quot;acceptable&quot; in its approach, its intent, the work that
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>seemed to attempt to present a different perception — a female
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>perception through female experience — was less prevalent than I
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>had hoped. I suppose that my personal criticism was that much of
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>the work, like much of conceptual art, was boring. It is amazing
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>how quickly a &quot;Movement&quot; becomes academic. How easy it
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>becomes to fit into the formula, to make bland ideas appear
				<lb facs='#facs_45_r_4_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>important, to inflate them through fancy presentation. So much
			</p>
			<pb n='46'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>conceptual art has become slick documentation without real sub
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>stance. It is a difficult problem, very much related to commercial
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>ism and egoism (fortune and fame). How ironic that “dematerial
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>ized&quot; art has become almost more “material&quot; than painting and
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>sculpture, without the compensation of pure sensual pleasure.
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>I think that what really disappointed me was not the art but
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>seeing other women fall into the male-role prison, women falling
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>into the forms and patterns of male-defined concept art, and
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>wanting acceptance within that framework; women not com
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>municating through their knowledge and experience of them
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>selves as women. Worst of all was seeing women behaving
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>towards each other very much like male artists I see each week in
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>Soho—guarded, competitive, assessing each other, vying for
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>position, not interacting. When we have a chance to do things
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>differently, because we’ve never been in this position before, I
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>hate to see us blow it.
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>Right now I am working on some new pieces and I am con
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>cerned about pushing myself to the next stage, not doing thinge
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>which are repetitive. Yet I also think it is important to work
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>things through, not be precious, risk losing it, experiment on
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>several levels at one time.
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>I am interested in how a person changes his/her perception
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>of him/herself through both self redefinition and definition by
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>others. Right now I am considering a piece which will involve a
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>person, then a group, experiencing then reexperiencing them
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>selves through their color aura, their self-color, and then their
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>alien color...
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_28' n='N028'/>I would like to hear more about the piece you are doing
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_29' n='N029'/>about the “chemistry of camera presence&quot; as it is something that
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_30' n='N030'/>has been both a concern and a conflict for me. Do you plan to do
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_31' n='N031'/>the same piece twice, with and without a camera, and see how
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_32' n='N032'/>they differ?...
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_33' n='N033'/>Would you be interested in doing a piece with me? Some
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_34' n='N034'/>thoughts, possibilities: I Both of us doing the same piece sepa
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_35' n='N035'/>rately. (2) Exchanging pieces and carrying out each other’s pieces,
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_36' n='N036'/>then doing our own. Showing the four interpretations. (3)
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_37' n='N037'/>Perhaps doing my &quot;Identity Exchange” piece together as we are of
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_38' n='N038'/>similar coloring, size, and sign. I have never performed this piece
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_39' n='N039'/>myself. It was enacted by Geoff Hendricks in February 1972 at
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_40' n='N040'/>Rutgers University. If you plan to be in NY we could do it as a
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_41' n='N041'/>one-day event. (Like a Saturday in Soho—unofficial use of
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_42' n='N042'/>galleries!)
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_43' n='N043'/>l’ve been taking ballet classes twice a week now since the
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_44' n='N044'/>beginning of July, and it is changing my body awareness. It
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_45' n='N045'/>makes me think about movement pieces. It would be good to
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_46' n='N046'/>work with a dance group.
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_47' n='N047'/>Write and let me know what you are doing and thinking. I
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_48' n='N048'/>am looking forward to hearing more about the pieces you men
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_49' n='N049'/>tioned in your card, and everything else going on in your life. Let
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_50' n='N050'/>me know when you plan to be in New York again, and hopefully
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_51' n='N051'/>we will be able to spend more time together. I will take a day off.
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_52' n='N052'/>Jacki
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_53' n='N053'/>October 23, 1973
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_54' n='N054'/>Dear Jacki — Your letter put adrenalin back into my blood. Actu
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_55' n='N055'/>ally, l’m an avid letter writer, but I hesitate to write copious
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_56' n='N056'/>letters to non-writers or post-carders; now I have an excuse.
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_57' n='N057'/>Did I tell you about my &quot;value scale,&quot; composed of colors
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_58' n='N058'/>that have emotional value for me? When I read the part of your
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_59' n='N059'/>letter about &quot;color aura” I started glumping around my empty
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_60' n='N060'/>kitchen making soft exclamatory noises. Friday l’m going to a
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_61' n='N061'/>paper company downtown to get a sheet each of high-intensity
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_62' n='N062'/>orange, blue, red and green, the colors that represent the four
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_1_1_tl_63' n='N063'/>points on my emotional compass. I was thinking of making call
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>ing-card-sized chips of color to place before me as I confront a
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>(stranger? Haven’t worked this out yet) during a ten-minute inter
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>val. The number and combination of chips would suggest the
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>tone of the confrontation (for me). As I explained in New York, I
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>used to worry about the content of my subjects&apos; consciousness,
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>but it’s too hard to document it. On the other hand, for the
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>&quot;Chemistry of Camera-Presence” piece, l’ve decided the only way
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>to keep the element of surprise is for me to surprise other people
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>with a camera; since I am going to set up the piece, I would
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>always be aware of the possibility of being filmed. I want to blow
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>up the adjustment process as an individual realizes s/he is being
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>filmed. Also I want to do a piece next week on videotape record
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>ing the time it takes me to act out an emotion. Method actors
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>recall certain images to make themselves cry, etc. l’m not as inter
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>ested in the tears as I am in the images. These will be written and
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>read silently while l’m on camera (?). l’ve discovered that reading
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>out loud does not produce tears or whatever, and neither does
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>description into a mike; the intellectual process cancels the
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>emotional experience. Silent fantasy is necessary. l’m wondering
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>what the camera will do to me, since l’m not an experienced
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>actor....
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>Ihave been taking Graphoanalysis by correspondence, and I
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>am happy to inform you that you are highly intelligent, have
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>initiative, spurts of enthusiasm and determination, don&apos;t hold
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>grudges, are sympathetic, not too precise, but were pessimistic
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>when you wrote the letter. Oh, yes, very original, as indicated by
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>figure-8 &quot;g&quot; formations. I am typing because when I get excited,
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_28' n='N028'/>my handwriting becomes code.
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_29' n='N029'/>Now for the facts: I plan to cut first term a week short and
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_30' n='N030'/>come to NYC. If I came on, say, Monday the 3 of December,
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_31' n='N031'/>could I stay with you through Saturday the 8th? We could use the
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_32' n='N032'/>week to get together a performance in 420 West Broadway such
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_33' n='N033'/>as &quot;Identity Exchange” or we could do our color pieces simul
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_34' n='N034'/>taneously and trade off. I could do a reading of &quot;Routine Per
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_35' n='N035'/>formance&quot; et al. in front of an audience instead of a video
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_36' n='N036'/>camera; also l’ve been wanting to try out &quot;Body Images” on a live
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_37' n='N037'/>audience. I hadn’t thought about it before, but perhaps I could do
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_38' n='N038'/>&quot;Composure,&quot; the piece which was in the c. 7,500 show, in front
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_39' n='N039'/>of an audience with the aid of a mirror.
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_40' n='N040'/>I have been thinking about &quot;Identity Exchange&quot; and (don&apos;t
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_41' n='N041'/>worry, I won’t tell you) I can’t help associating New York with
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_42' n='N042'/>you. In your case, I think it is valid to associate place with char
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_43' n='N043'/>acter; I just hope I don’t make you think of Mackerel....
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_44' n='N044'/>l’d like to attend a women’s meeting in NYC; a group has
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_45' n='N045'/>finally started meeting here, but for some reason I don’t feel close
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_46' n='N046'/>to anyone as yet. l’m not trying to prove myself as strenuously as
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_47' n='N047'/>I used to through my appearance, as they do. Appearance is stil
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_48' n='N048'/>critical to me, but l’m settled now and they aren’t. Many of them
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_49' n='N049'/>see me as a teacher (which of course I am to some of them) with
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_50' n='N050'/>all the connotations of that position attached: wise, old, re
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_51' n='N051'/>served, yuk.
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_52' n='N052'/>Thanks again for your letter. Martha
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_53' n='N053'/>January 3, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_54' n='N054'/>Dear Jacki—Richards met me at the airport; he and Marcia
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_55' n='N055'/>arrived the day before. He guessed that I might sue him, and said
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_56' n='N056'/>I would have to do it, but we reached an amicable peace even
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_57' n='N057'/>tually. We sat in the car for an hour talking, and he ended up
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_58' n='N058'/>saying that he couldn’t believe how strong I was. Last night I
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_59' n='N059'/>didn’t sleep at all and consequently felt rotten all day today, but
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_60' n='N060'/>today I got an apartment which I can move into January 12th. I
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_61' n='N061'/>am envious of the way Richards looks at Marcia, but that&apos;s all. I
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_62' n='N062'/>don’t think Marcia is any shakes. She has this defense mecha
				<lb facs='#facs_46_r_2_1_tl_63' n='N063'/>nism, looking wide-eyed, that really annoys me.
			</p>
			<pb n='47'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>Enough of that. I am depressed but doing rather well....
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>I wrote a movie on the plane. l’II show it to you. Love, M.
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>January 13, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>Dear Martha — Chin up and smile. We are all with you all the
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>way. You are going to make it, beautifully too. Whenever you
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>begin to feel the depression closing in, think of the whole world
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>waiting for you here.
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>l’m exhausted. Can’t wait till you get here. For some reason
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>l’ve had trouble getting my fire going since the piece. It’s as if so
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>much power was used, such intense concentration, that I need
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>refueling. Talk about an energy crisis! l’ve also discovered how
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>jealous people can get when you get yourself together, have any
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>power, and can affect others. The threatened ones work very
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>hard at undermining you, searching out your vulnerabilities. No
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>wonder the alchemists banded together in secret societies
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>I worked today, wrote the second half of the piece up (down-
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>town part). Anne has really come out since the piece. She just
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>told her shrink about it this week. He was so turned on that he
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>asked to see me. He can hardly believe it, thought it was the most
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>extraordinary thing he’d ever heard. Should I charge him 540 an
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>hour to talk to me? If he wants to write a paper about it, it will
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>have to be with our final approval and permission before release.
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>After all, we have “all rights reserved.&quot;...
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>Have a lot of things to talk to you about. I hope we can share
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>our strengths and weaknesses and balance each other, and sup
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>port each other. I need your opinion on a few things...
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>Stay strong and don’t let R. screw you out of what’s legally
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_28' n='N028'/>yours by doing a number on your emotions.... See you Friday
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_29' n='N029'/>night the 25th. l’II make a lovely leisurely dinner, and we can sit
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_30' n='N030'/>and relax and talk.
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_31' n='N031'/>Take care of yourself. Love, Jacki
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_32' n='N032'/>January 30, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_33' n='N033'/>I noticed after the Bar Mitzvah that when I stood on the
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_34' n='N034'/>corner of 57th and 6th Avenue in my braless red dress that lots of
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_35' n='N035'/>people looked at me as though I was a call girl, even though it
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_36' n='N036'/>was 3:00 in the afternoon. Definition by circumstantial evidence.
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_37' n='N037'/>Photographs of me in the same outfit on various corners in NYC:
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_38' n='N038'/>57th and 6th; West Bway and Spring; Ist Ave and 69th; Wall
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_39' n='N039'/>Street; Bway and 125th. Costume acts as a mirror; bluejeans
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_40' n='N040'/>could do the same?
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_41' n='N041'/>February 15, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_42' n='N042'/>Two letters from Martha Wilson. She has become inter
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_43' n='N043'/>twined in my life since December, and I ought to examine the
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_44' n='N044'/>events, and the complexities of feelings that have come out of
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_45' n='N045'/>them. I am slightly antagonistic towards her today. Somewhat
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_46' n='N046'/>resentful of her carelessness, her total self-absorption, the com
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_47' n='N047'/>plete subjectivity of her way of dealing with things, always seeing
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_48' n='N048'/>through her needs, never beyond them or around them. Perhaps
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_49' n='N049'/>it is her youth, her limited experience. No matter. Combined with
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_50' n='N050'/>all that intense hungry ambition and that fine sharp intellect, it
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_51' n='N051'/>fills me with a vague sense of annoyance. I have been very gener
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_52' n='N052'/>ous with her, given of myself — my friends, my home, my
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_53' n='N053'/>clothes, my time, my ideas, experiences, knowledge, my food,
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_54' n='N054'/>my energy, and finally advice when asked for. I find her to be less
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_55' n='N055'/>sharing. At first her sunshine smile, her eagerness, seemed so
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_56' n='N056'/>unassuming. But her apologies are aggressive, and her assump
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_57' n='N057'/>tions border on arrogance. Yet underneath there are still the self-
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_58' n='N058'/>degrading gestures, the feelings of inadequacy, the fear. She is ful.
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_59' n='N059'/>of contradictions, inconsistencies. Overriding everything is the
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_60' n='N060'/>impressive professionalism of her art.... Our relationship seems
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_61' n='N061'/>to have gone around in a full circle. I think we will have to talk
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_1_1_tl_62' n='N062'/>about these things.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>February 28-March 2, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>Dear Martha —... Rereading your letter I get the feeling R. and
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>M. are really bugging you underneath the bravado. That is very
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>real, a painful fact you have to deal with daily. It’s understand
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>able. Hard to avoid them. Glad your friends are supportive.
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>Don’t worry. As you’ve begun to discover, facades become reali
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>ties, and it takes about six months and distance for a lover to
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>become a stranger in your mind. Love, Jacki
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>March 8, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>Jacki —... I got an assurance that our piece could be shown in
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>the Mezzanine Gallery here at NSCAD, so I will take installation
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>photos when it’s up...
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>I don’t talk to Richards anymore; we speak if we bump into
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>each other, but don’t seek each other out. l’m speaking to a
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>female lawyer on Tuesday and I may sue Richards if l’m legally
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>capable because he really did step on me. Otherwise l’m dating a
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>concert pianist who lives out in Hubbards. He now plays only to
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>amuse himself and directs plays in experimental theatres and
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>prisons for his living. He knows l’m leaving in May. He says he
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>was first attracted by my independence. Men like that are hard to
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>come by....
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>I keep my social life full as possible so I don’t have to think
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>about being in Halifax near Richards, etc. l’m going to a shrink
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>who is sending me to relaxation therapy because I don’t know
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>how to relax.... III let you know how the layout progresses.
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_2_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>Love, Martha
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>Wilson and Apple, March 1976. JJudith Vivell.)
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>March 31, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>Dear Martha —... There are a lot of things I want to get into in
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>relation to the really extraordinary experience that we’ve been
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>through. I don’t think either of us realized just how far we had
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>gone. We placed ourselves in the most vulnerable of positions. As
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>two strangers we entered into immediate and intense intimacy
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>with total trust. We took an enormous gamble. It was very
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>daring of us. And I think we both suffered from aftereffects not
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>anticipated and not immediately perceived or understood. I don’t
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>have the time right now to explore this and I think in another
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>sense it is kind of another piece. Certainly the subject of another
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>part of our piece and worth investigating....
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>This weekend I worked up my “Brunette” piece. It’s turned
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>up some interesting surprises for me. Perhaps a subconscious
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>equation — Blonde-Female, Brunette-Male (hmmm......) in
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>relation to identity/image projection (mine).
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>Reading books on Archaeology for the Digging piece in
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>May. Fascinating. Also, l’m enjoying my privacy. Like being
				<lb facs='#facs_47_r_4_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>alone.
			</p>
			<pb n='48'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>l’m very glad you called me that day as it cleared a lot of
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>conflicts and questions and complex mixed-up feelings all collid
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>ing in my head. It relieved a few tensions, and I felt a release of
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>certain anxieties after talking. It was also good to talk with you as
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>the extra dimension in voice clarifies the meaning in words so
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>often misread in print....
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>Take care. Love, Jacki
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>April 5, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>Dear Jacki —... It’s wonderful to hear about L’s interest in the
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>piece. It is so bleak up here, and New York gets more and more
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>frightening to contemplate from this distance. I keep questioning
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>whether I can survive as an artist and get worry wrinkles thinking
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>about it.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>Your letter was tremendously supportive. Today I do a
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>videotape of making myself up first as beautiful and then as ugly
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>as I can. I have been thinking a lot about &quot;vomiting&quot; on people; I
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>see this as playing a joke on myself.... Love, Martha
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>April 28, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>Dear Martha —I wanted to write to you immediately, as soon as I
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>got back from London, as I am bursting with things to tell you.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>That was two weeks ago, and my life has been in turmoil, so I am
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>beyond apologies....
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>First I want to tell you about the c. 7,500 show in London. I
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>called Tony Stokes (at Garage Arts) when I arrived and he
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>seemed very relieved that I was there. On Saturday morning I
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>went down to Garage and then with the help of a terrific group of
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>London women artists I installed the show in the Warehouse next
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_28' n='N028'/>door. It was a perfect space for the show. Very New York raw! I
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_29' n='N029'/>must say I did a fantastic job. Did two terrific walls for us, put
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_30' n='N030'/>ting our work next to each other’s. Added the B&amp;W contact sheet
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_31' n='N031'/>from “Transformance” with your article in the middle. It really
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_32' n='N032'/>looked good....
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_33' n='N033'/>I have been going through some fairly difficult changes and
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_34' n='N034'/>conflicts. I long for my own psychic space, room to grow in, to
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_35' n='N035'/>experience my art in. The time has run out for me to continue in
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_36' n='N036'/>the double life of full-time work (job) and full-time art. I am
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_37' n='N037'/>exhausted, overstrained, and colliding with myself, struggling
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_38' n='N038'/>with hostilities and overextension emotionally. I don’t have
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_39' n='N039'/>enough time and I feel like l’m suffocating from spinning too
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_40' n='N040'/>quickly and not being able to slow down to breathe deeply...
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_41' n='N041'/>Not having money is as paralyzing as not having time. They
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_42' n='N042'/>equalize and neutralize each other. Besides, earning one’s own
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_43' n='N043'/>money is part of both the real and psychological independence
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_44' n='N044'/>and liberation from the role of the woman-child. So I have to
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_45' n='N045'/>search for alternative possibilities. This is especially difficult now
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_46' n='N046'/>because the economy is a disaster area. There are no jobs any
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_47' n='N047'/>where.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_48' n='N048'/>I am at a point of change in my life, trying to create new
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_49' n='N049'/>structures. The piece we did together was a culmination point for
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_50' n='N050'/>me, the end of a cycle.... I find myself looking into another
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_51' n='N051'/>mirror, seeing a different image.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_52' n='N052'/>The DIGGING piece has become very complex and multi
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_53' n='N053'/>layered. It is just a beginning now, and it might take months to
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_54' n='N054'/>complete. The actual &quot;dig&quot; itself will take place in several weeks.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_55' n='N055'/>When I think about it I get very excited, like someone about to
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_56' n='N056'/>take a journey into unknown territory, like going to a foreign city
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_57' n='N057'/>after having read a book about its history.... It will be good to
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_58' n='N058'/>see you and sit and talk for hours.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_59' n='N059'/>Also it will be interesting to do a tape about the other part of
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_60' n='N060'/>TRANSFORMANCE —what we experienced with each other,
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_61' n='N061'/>the risks we took, how far we went, how we reacted later, over-
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_1_1_tl_62' n='N062'/>reacted, then rebalanced; where we are now. We plunged into
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>each other’s lives off a high diving board. We went very deep,
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>very quickly, and perhaps suffered the mild bends coming up for
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>air. It could be a very important tape to go with the piece. Also
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>maybe a photo of us today, six months later. Call me when you
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>get to New Jersey....
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>Love, Jacki
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>May 3, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>Taking diet pills, haven’t slept in 2 nights. Cried on bus w.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>Marcia, talking about Primal Scream and ego-coasting, being
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>alone. She said R was unoriginal, I was the &quot;individual&quot; which
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>shocked me. She sees me as courageous, she said in her letter to
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>me, envies me. I love speed, it relieves the panic, the separation,
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>substitutes euphoria, wholeness? I wish I could stay on it. Have
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>lost some double chin. Dinner tonight with R and Marcia. Sat
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>with R yesterday watching John Watt tapes, didn’t feel much. I
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>admire him from a distance. I plan to break down in the car
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>tonight, tell him I am alone, afraid. He is my father substitute
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>because of his aloofness. I should be doing something all the time,
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>can’t do fruitless activity.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>May 5, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>Kicked and screamed w/ R last night, he said there was no
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>sense pretending he wasn’t happy. I saw that he was. I felt very
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>hurt, cried a lot over loss of children, middle-class life which his
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>marriage to Marcia represents to me. I can’t do that now? Now
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>l’m in the kitchen and I feel lethargic, desperate, speechless,
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>embarrassed, like being at home. I have to be intellectual around
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>him. Isnap at Damian, can’t play, indulge him. Had a dream that
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_28' n='N028'/>I stayed in the room below them. I am a frustrated child and I
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_29' n='N029'/>communicate that frustration to Damian, I frustrate him. I don&apos;t
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_30' n='N030'/>let myself feel. Ate cheesecake out of the fridge this a.m. Rrepre
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_31' n='N031'/>sents home situation which I am trying to resolve. I feel like I
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_32' n='N032'/>have to perform for him. He came in to ask what my plans were
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_33' n='N033'/>and for a split second I felt guilty? Not a barrel of fun to be with.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_34' n='N034'/>Have to learn to love myself, whatever that means. Art about
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_35' n='N035'/>performing for others. Double exposure = &quot;Exposure
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_36' n='N036'/>May 11, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_37' n='N037'/>My emotions are frozen. I am frightened, not attracted to
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_38' n='N038'/>men. Metaphor, describe my parents as luggage. I do what they
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_39' n='N039'/>and authorities say because l am afraid they will not love me.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_40' n='N040'/>May 10, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_41' n='N041'/>Feel generally OK. Felt good to see Jacki last night. Saw
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_42' n='N042'/>Nancy Kitchel show at 112 Greene St. which put me in awe.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_43' n='N043'/>Darkness, “masking,&quot; lit tables, notebooks, folders for papers.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_44' n='N044'/>Her involvement with Vito, a story about tragic encounter, her
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_45' n='N045'/>grandmother’s gestures. Talked w/ (Jane) Kleinberg at Whitney
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_46' n='N046'/>about how women are making art about separation. I fantasize
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_47' n='N047'/>about my loft. I discover who I am as I go along. &quot;Borders
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_48' n='N048'/>occurs to me. I will take photos of rooms during search. l’m tired
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_49' n='N049'/>Art about not knowing how I feel about things. Accept, discard
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_50' n='N050'/>Divide objects. Retouched photos of how I want things to appear.
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_51' n='N051'/>How much are we defined by our surroundings. Deprived of
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_52' n='N052'/>middle-class life. Photograph the fantasy. Marcia and I occupy
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_53' n='N053'/>the same space in relation to R, but opposite sides of a single
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_54' n='N054'/>personality pulled in two directions. Forced into a position. Men
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_55' n='N055'/>= authority figures, never women. Dad wanted me to pity him,
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_56' n='N056'/>told me he was nearly out of a job. Apparently she is ambitious,
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_57' n='N057'/>an egomaniac, a blood-curdling bitch. She uses people, squeezes
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_58' n='N058'/>them dry, dumps them. Actually, she’s sensitive, retiring, sweet-
				<lb facs='#facs_48_r_2_1_tl_59' n='N059'/>tempered.
			</p>
			<pb n='49'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>May 12, 1974
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>I used to feel like women were the &quot;enemy,&quot; men were my
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>best friends. Then I didn’t have any respect for myself, treated
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>them like authorities to please. Now I feel more comfortable with
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>women, even have a distaste for men. I look at attractive men on
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>the subway and experience revulsion. Dad made me afraid of him
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>to cover his weakness. Sylvia Plath got at that real hatred every
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>one feels for his/her parents. For how they have hurt you. Trem
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>bling hands, my own fear of incompetence. Videotape of a simple
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>task, hands hammering nails. Unfamiliar, incompetent, bad
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>craftsman, danger, &quot;hammering.&quot; Stuttering videotape, head w/
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>eyes closed, Mother &amp; Dad dialogue of unsaid phrases.
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>July 26,1974
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>Martha and I have lunch at the Plaza Palm Court. Reprise
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>An attempt to reexamine, redefine “Claudia” (TRANSFOR-
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>MANCE). Same setting, shift in context, intent. We want to see
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>how we feel, how we act. The mystique dissolves. It is, after all,
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>like having lunch any other place. Just a restaurant....
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>Over too expensive spinach salad we pursue the question of
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>female sensibility, questioning whether women artists have
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>become caught in a web of confusion between subject matter and
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>&quot;sensibility. Often they choose objects, acts and symbols associ
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>ated with the stereotypes of the female role in our culture as
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>content, when they are in fact the objects and conditions created
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>by male sensibility and value systems. Do too many women
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>artists perpetuate the &quot;system&quot; by attempting to elevate a certain
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>kind of subject matter out of proportion to its significance? On
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_28' n='N028'/>the other hand, liberation declaring equality continues to enforce
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_29' n='N029'/>the concept of there being no female sensibility. “Anything they
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_1_1_tl_30' n='N030'/>can do we can do as well if not better” thinking. In the struggle to
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_1' n='N001'/>achieve power and position in the art world we charge forth into
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_2' n='N002'/>battle to prove this, and the result, which is often successful, is
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_3' n='N003'/>also often indistinguishable from the acclaimed and established
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_4' n='N004'/>art created by a male sensibility. Again we reenforce their system,
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_5' n='N005'/>their concept of reality. Perhaps the only answer, at least the only
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_6' n='N006'/>one we can come up with, is to work through an internal view
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_7' n='N007'/>coming from our female experience of reality (or lack of it!), and
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_8' n='N008'/>that out of this will come some alternative perspectives that also
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_9' n='N009'/>do not end up putting us all together in yet another box. Still the
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_10' n='N010'/>same old questions go round in a circle. Cultural conditioning
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_11' n='N011'/>and biology. Well, how do we change the patterns of the condi
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_12' n='N012'/>tioning, making our viewpoint carry equal weight? “Claudia
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_13' n='N013'/>was a magnification of role models and stereotypes of power,
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_14' n='N014'/>media images programmed into all of us. The “power” of the
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_15' n='N015'/>beautiful, rich woman. The illusion of power. We exaggerated it,
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_16' n='N016'/>&quot;lived&quot; in order to also shatter it, expose the illusion, blow it up
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_17' n='N017'/>not reenforce it, or validate it. It’s a fine line, a delicate balance of
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_18' n='N018'/>form and content, intent and context. Both Martha and I have all
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_19' n='N019'/>kinds of ambivalences about that work and whether it worked. In
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_20' n='N020'/>two years perhaps we will be able to see it in the right perspective,
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_21' n='N021'/>with the distance to analyze it better, understand it in relation to
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_22' n='N022'/>female sensibility and art.
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_23' n='N023'/>Martha Wilson, performance artist, began executing private performances
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_24' n='N024'/>or “transformations” in 1971. In 1975 and 1976, she performed five chap
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_25' n='N025'/>ters of The Arnotated Alice in which the heroine encounters contemporary
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_26' n='N026'/>conventions —social, sexual, logical and linguistic. Jacki Apple began
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_27' n='N027'/>doing performances in 1971. Since 1975 she has been doing installation
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_28' n='N028'/>works exploring psychological space. She and Martine Aballea are writing
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_29' n='N029'/>a collaborative novel between New York and Paris. Martha is the founder
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_30' n='N030'/>and executive director of The Franklin Furnace Archive for artists’ books
				<lb facs='#facs_49_r_3_1_tl_31' n='N031'/>in New York City, and Jacki is its curator.
			</p>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
