<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Correspondence Between Jacki Apple and Martha Wilson, 1973-1974</title>
				<author>Jacki Apple and Martha Wilson</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
					<resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<pb n="43"
					facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_043.jpg"/>
				<head>Correspondence between Jacki Apple and Martha Wilson 1973-1974</head>
				<div>
					<opener><date>August 6, 1973</date>
						<salute>Dear Jacki Apple —</salute></opener>
					<p>... When I read the c. 7,500 catalogue I was overjoyed to find that I am
						working alongside of a great many other women, especially you. I am
						enclosing a resume, a descriptive list of works to date, and transcriptions
						of videotapes for you to peruse. Also a photograph of me invading homosexual
						consciousness...</p>
					<p>Recently I have been working on a piece called "Male Impersonator" and on
						method acting concerns. I find that in front of the camera I don’t feel
						particularly male or homosexual or what ever; the identity shock comes when
						I look at the photographs of myself in those roles. I am considering an
						actual invasion of another identity: being picked up on Halifax waterfront
						as a prostitute. That would involve real risk. I don’t think I would be able
						to forget who I am, though, in spite of the immersion. To lose myself was my
						original intent, I think, in December of 1971. Also I used to worry about
						audience verification of my success a good deal more than I do now. In the
						method acting exercise, I wanted to track the images that would cause me to,
						say, cry using a tape recorder, and I found that the intellectual process of
						talking about emotion prohibited me from experiencing it.</p>
					<p>Who are the "four people" in a relationship? Do you distinguish between real
						self and perception of self? How do you document your interchanges,
						exchanges and redefinitions?... Hope to meet you someday. If you’re ever in
						Halifax (ha) you can sleep in my studio. </p>
					<closer><signed>Martha Wilson</signed></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>August 26,1973</date></opener>
					<p>Martha Wilson came to see me last Thursday. She is in the c. 7,500 show with
						me, and after receiving her pieces and talking on the phone, I was excited
						about meeting her. We talked with familiarity, not as strangers. Yet there
						wasn’t enough time — little more than an hour—allowing us to barely do
						anything more than become aware of each other’s positions.... We jumped from
						subject to subject like two people sampling a feast of appetizers, wanting
						to taste everything. She is full of curiosity and hunger, and buoyancy,
						asking questions, taking in information, talking rapidly, never resting.</p>
					<p>She has an open face, quick to smile with her eyes as well as her mouth, a
						gamine quality with a sense of camp. Short shaggy yellow hair, plucked out,
						bleached eyebrows, fair skin. She wore pants and a short-sleeved printed
						shirt. She laughs easily, and has a natural extroverted sense of theater.
						Yet there is nothing theatrical about her appearance.</p>
					<p>I liked her immensely. I also recognize something of myself in her, younger.
						The energy, independence, restlessness; the quickness of response, so direct
						yet somehow elusive, testing, try ing out life. I liked her optimism. She
						has a quality of motion and sunshine, and underneath a vulnerability. I hope
						we will be able to expand the relationship, write to each other, even make
						the correspondence a piece in the future. </p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>August 26, 1973</date></opener>
					<p>Met Jacki Apple today, big surprise. A professional woman, I expected a
						stringbean like myself. Jolted me to realize women from different
						circumstances are doing similar experiments with identity. She runs her own
						design room, draws a pair of pants, chooses a fabric, a pattern cutter cuts
						it, two Hispanic women sew it up. Her designs on Macy’s third floor,
						Sportswear. Any way, I was shocked when I saw her: She looked professional
						all over, eye makeup to high heels. I thought artists weren’t supposed to
						look like that. A sexist belief, something inherited from Gertrude Stein, a
						woman has to be un-pretty to be taken as seriously as a man. I"believe"
						this, questioned Jacki’s intelligence on the basis of her appearance, even
						though I had read her work, yikes.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>September 18, 1973</date>
						<salute>Jacki</salute> —</opener>
					<p>I xeroxed all the "Selfportrait" notes and am waiting for an 8x10 enlargement
						to come back from the drugstore. Now working on an idea sparked by Yvonne
						Rainer: images of my perfection/deformity. Also a piece about the chemistry
						of camera presence which came out of our conversation. Drop me a card.</p>
					<closer><signed>Martha</signed></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>October 14, 1973</date>
						<salute>Dear Martha</salute>—</opener>
					<p>I've been trying to write you for weeks, no — months, and this is the second
						letter I've started. I came away from the hour we spent together feeling it
						was much too brief, that we were like two people at a banquet wanting to
						taste everything, with only enough time for a first bite. So the hour left
						me stimulated and looking forward to corresponding. Part of my excitement
						was in discovering another artist, a woman artist, working with concepts
						similar to my own, and with the attitude of experimentation which is so
						important to me. Another part of it was your own personal openness and
						energy and curiosity.</p>
					<p>The day your postcard arrived I had gone to the c. 7,500 opeñling at Moore
						College in Philadelphia. I have a number of mixed feelings about the show,
						and it was an interesting experience for me. One thing which I was surprised
						about (and probably shouldn’t have been) was the discovery of how far from
						the mainstream both of us are. Your perception of that from the catalogue
						was more astute than mine. In the final analysis the work that was most
						interesting to me, the work that was not "conventional" or "acceptable" in
						its approach, its intent, the work that seemed to attempt to present a
						different perception — a female perception through female experience — was
						less prevalent than I had hoped. I suppose that my personal criticism was
						that much of the work, like much of conceptual art, was boring. It is
						amazing how quickly a "Movement" becomes academic. How easy it becomes to
						fit into the formula, to make bland ideas appear important, to inflate them
						through fancy presentation. So much <pb n="44"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_044.jpg"
						/> conceptual art has become slick documentation without real substance. It
						is a difficult problem, very much related to commercialism and egoism
						(fortune and fame). How ironic that "dematerialized" art has become almost
						more "material" than painting and sculpture, without the compensation of
						pure sensual pleasure.</p>
					<p>I think that what really disappointed me was not the art but seeing other
						women fall into the male-role prison, women falling into the forms and
						patterns of male-defined concept art, and wanting acceptance within that
						framework; women not communicating through their knowledge and experience of
						them selves as women. Worst of all was seeing women behaving towards each
						other very much like male artists I see each week in Soho—guarded,
						competitive, assessing each other, vying for position, not interacting. When
						we have a chance to do things differently, because we’ve never been in this
						position before, I hate to see us blow it.</p>
					<p>Right now I am working on some new pieces and I am concerned about pushing
						myself to the next stage, not doing things which are repetitive. Yet I also
						think it is important to work things through, not be precious, risk losing
						it, experiment on several levels at one time.</p>
					<p>I am interested in how a person changes his/her perception of him/herself
						through both self redefinition and definition by others. Right now I am
						considering a piece which will involve a person, then a group, experiencing
						then reexperiencing them selves through their color aura, their self-color,
						and then their alien color...</p>
					<p>I would like to hear more about the piece you are doing about the "chemistry
						of camera presence" as it is something that has been both a concern and a
						conflict for me. Do you plan to do the same piece twice, with and without a
						camera, and see how they differ?...</p>
					<p>Would you be interested in doing a piece with me? Some thoughts,
						possibilities: (1) Both of us doing the same piece separately. (2)
						Exchanging pieces and carrying out each other’s pieces, then doing our own.
						Showing the four interpretations. (3) Perhaps doing my "Identity Exchange"
						piece together as we are of similar coloring, size, and sign. I have never
						performed this piece myself. It was enacted by Geoff Hendricks in February
						1972 at Rutgers University. If you plan to be in NY we could do it as a
						one-day event. (Like a Saturday in Soho—unofficial use of galleries!)</p>
					<p>I've been taking ballet classes twice a week now since the beginning of July,
						and it is changing my body awareness. It makes me think about movement
						pieces. It would be good to work with a dance group.</p>
					<p>Write and let me know what you are doing and thinking. I am looking forward
						to hearing more about the pieces you mentioned in your card, and everything
						else going on in your life. Let me know when you plan to be in New York
						again, and hopefully we will be able to spend more time together. I will
						take a day off.</p>
					<closer><signed>Jacki</signed></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>October 23, 1973</date></opener>
					<p>Dear Jacki — Your letter put adrenalin back into my blood. Actually, I'm an
						avid letter writer, but I hesitate to write copious letters to non-writers
						or post-carders; now I have an excuse.</p>
					<p>Did I tell you about my "value scale," composed of colors that have emotional
						value for me? When I read the part of your letter about "color aura" I
						started glumping around my empty kitchen making soft exclamatory noises.
						Friday I'm going to a paper company downtown to get a sheet each of
						high-intensity orange, blue, red and green, the colors that represent the
						four points on my emotional compass. I was thinking of making
						calling-card-sized chips of color to place before me as I confront a
						(stranger? Haven’t worked this out yet) during a ten-minute interval. The
						number and combination of chips would suggest the tone of the confrontation
						(for me). As I explained in New York, I used to worry about the content of
						my subjects' consciousness, but it’s too hard to document it. On the other
						hand, for the "Chemistry of Camera-Presence" piece, I've decided the only
						way to keep the element of surprise is for me to surprise other people with
						a camera; since I am going to set up the piece, I would always be aware of
						the possibility of being filmed. I want to blow up the adjustment process as
						an individual realizes s/he is being filmed. Also I want to do a piece next
						week on videotape recording the time it takes me to act out an emotion.
						Method actors recall certain images to make themselves cry, etc. I'm not as
						interested in the tears as I am in the images. These will be written and
						read silently while I'm on camera (?). I've discovered that reading out loud
						does not produce tears or whatever, and neither does description into a
						mike; the intellectual process cancels the emotional experience. Silent
						fantasy is necessary. I'm wondering what the camera will do to me, since I'm
						not an experienced actor....</p>
					<p>Ihave been taking Graphoanalysis by correspondence, and I am happy to inform
						you that you are highly intelligent, have initiative, spurts of enthusiasm
						and determination, don't hold grudges, are sympathetic, not too precise, but
						were pessimistic when you wrote the letter. Oh, yes, very original, as
						indicated by figure-8 "g" formations. I am typing because when I get
						excited, my handwriting becomes code.</p>
					<p>Now for the facts: I plan to cut first term a week short and come to NYC. If
						I came on, say, Monday the 3 of December, could I stay with you through
						Saturday the 8th? We could use the week to get together a performance in 420
						West Broadway such as "Identity Exchange" or we could do our color pieces
						simultaneously and trade off. I could do a reading of "Routine Performance"
						et al. in front of an audience instead of a video camera; also I've been
						wanting to try out "Body Images" on a live audience. I hadn’t thought about
						it before, but perhaps I could do "Composure," the piece which was in the c.
						7,500 show, in front of an audience with the aid of a mirror.</p>
					<p>I have been thinking about "Identity Exchange" and (don't worry, I won’t tell
						you) I can’t help associating New York with you. In your case, I think it is
						valid to associate place with character; I just hope I don’t make you think
						of Mackerel....</p>
					<p>I’d like to attend a women’s meeting in NYC; a group has finally started
						meeting here, but for some reason I don’t feel close to anyone as yet. I'm
						not trying to prove myself as strenuously as I used to through my
						appearance, as they do. Appearance is stil critical to me, but I'm settled
						now and they aren’t. Many of them see me as a teacher (which of course I am
						to some of them) with all the connotations of that position attached: wise,
						old, reserved, yuk.</p>
					<closer>Thanks again for your letter. <salute>Martha</salute></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>January 3, 1974</date>
						<salute>Dear Jacki</salute> — </opener>
					<p>Richards met me at the airport; he and Marcia arrived the day before. He
						guessed that I might sue him, and said I would have to do it, but we reached
						an amicable peace eventually. We sat in the car for an hour talking, and he
						ended up saying that he couldn’t believe how strong I was. Last night I
						didn’t sleep at all and consequently felt rotten all day today, but today I
						got an apartment which I can move into January 12th. I am envious of the way
						Richards looks at Marcia, but that's all. I don’t think Marcia is any
						shakes. She has this defense mechanism, looking wide-eyed, that really
						annoys me.</p>
					<pb n="45"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_045.jpg"/>
					<p>Enough of that. I am depressed but doing rather well.... I wrote a movie on
						the plane. l’II show it to you.</p>
					<closer>Love, <salute>M.</salute></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener>January 13, 1974 <salute>Dear Martha</salute>
					</opener>
					<p>— Chin up and smile. We are all with you all the way. You are going to make
						it, beautifully too. Whenever you begin to feel the depression closing in,
						think of the whole world waiting for you here.</p>
					<p>I'm exhausted. Can’t wait till you get here. For some reason I've had trouble
						getting my fire going since the piece. It’s as if so much power was used,
						such intense concentration, that I need refueling. Talk about an energy
						crisis! I've also discovered how jealous people can get when you get
						yourself together, have any power, and can affect others. The threatened
						ones work very hard at undermining you, searching out your vulnerabilities.
						No wonder the alchemists banded together in secret societies I worked today,
						wrote the second half of the piece up (downtown part). Anne has really come
						out since the piece. She just told her shrink about it this week. He was so
						turned on that he asked to see me. He can hardly believe it, thought it was
						the most extraordinary thing he’d ever heard. Should I charge him 540 an
						hour to talk to me? If he wants to write a paper about it, it will have to
						be with our final approval and permission before release. After all, we have
						"all rights reserved."...</p>
					<p>Have a lot of things to talk to you about. I hope we can share our strengths
						and weaknesses and balance each other, and support each other. I need your
						opinion on a few things...</p>
					<p>Stay strong and don’t let R. screw you out of what’s legally yours by doing a
						number on your emotions.... See you Friday night the 25th. I’ll make a
						lovely leisurely dinner, and we can sit and relax and talk.</p>
					<closer><salute>Take care of yourself. Love,</salute>
						<signed>Jack</signed></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>January 30, 1974</date></opener>
					<p>I noticed after the Bar Mitzvah that when I stood on the corner of 57th and
						6th Avenue in my braless red dress that lots of people looked at me as
						though I was a call girl, even though it was 3:00 in the afternoon.
						Definition by circumstantial evidence. Photographs of me in the same outfit
						on various corners in NYC: 57th and 6th; West Bway and Spring; Ist Ave and
						69th; Wall Street; Bway and 125th. Costume acts as a mirror; bluejeans could
						do the same?</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>February 15, 1974</date></opener>
					<p>Two letters from Martha Wilson. She has become intertwined in my life since
						December, and I ought to examine the events, and the complexities of
						feelings that have come out of them. I am slightly antagonistic towards her
						today. Somewhat resentful of her carelessness, her total self-absorption,
						the complete subjectivity of her way of dealing with things, always seeing
						through her needs, never beyond them or around them. Perhaps it is her
						youth, her limited experience. No matter. Combined with all that intense
						hungry ambition and that fine sharp intellect, it fills me with a vague
						sense of annoyance. I have been very generous with her, given of myself — my
						friends, my home, my clothes, my time, my ideas, experiences, knowledge, my
						food, my energy, and finally advice when asked for. I find her to be less
						sharing. At first her sunshine smile, her eagerness, seemed so unassuming.
						But her apologies are aggressive, and her assumptions border on arrogance.
						Yet underneath there are still the self- degrading gestures, the feelings of
						inadequacy, the fear. She is full of contradictions, inconsistencies.
						Overriding everything is the impressive professionalism of her art.... Our
						relationship seems to have gone around in a full circle. I think we will
						have to talk about these things. </p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>February 28-March 2, 1974</date>
						<salute>Dear Martha</salute> —</opener>
					<p>... Rereading your letter I get the feeling R. and M. are really bugging you
						underneath the bravado. That is very real, a painful fact you have to deal
						with daily. It’s understandable. Hard to avoid them. Glad your friends are
						supportive. Don’t worry. As you’ve begun to discover, facades become
						realities, and it takes about six months and distance for a lover to become
						a stranger in your mind.</p>
					<closer>Love, <signed>Jacki</signed></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>March 8, 1974</date>
						<salute>Jacki</salute> —</opener>
					<p>... I got an assurance that our piece could be shown in the Mezzanine Gallery
						here at NSCAD, so I will take installation photos when it’s up...</p>
					<p>I don’t talk to Richards anymore; we speak if we bump into each other, but
						don’t seek each other out. I'm speaking to a female lawyer on Tuesday and I
						may sue Richards if I'm legally capable because he really did step on me.
						Otherwise I'm dating a concert pianist who lives out in Hubbards. He now
						plays only to amuse himself and directs plays in experimental theatres and
						prisons for his living. He knows I'm leaving in May. He says he was first
						attracted by my independence. Men like that are hard to come by....</p>
					<p>I keep my social life full as possible so I don’t have to think about being
						in Halifax near Richards, etc. I'm going to a shrink who is sending me to
						relaxation therapy because I don’t know how to relax.... I'll let you know
						how the layout progresses.</p>
					<closer><salute>Love,</salute>
						<signed>Martha</signed></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>March 31, 1974</date>
						<salute>Dear Martha</salute> —</opener>
					<p>... There are a lot of things I want to get into in relation to the really
						extraordinary experience that we’ve been through. I don’t think either of us
						realized just how far we had gone. We placed ourselves in the most
						vulnerable of positions. As two strangers we entered into immediate and
						intense intimacy with total trust. We took an enormous gamble. It was very
						daring of us. And I think we both suffered from aftereffects not anticipated
						and not immediately perceived or understood. I don’t have the time right now
						to explore this and I think in another sense it is kind of another piece.
						Certainly the subject of another part of our piece and worth
						investigating....</p>
					<p>This weekend I worked up my "Brunette" piece. It’s turned up some interesting
						surprises for me. Perhaps a subconscious equation — Blonde-Female,
						Brunette-Male (hmmm......) in relation to identity/image projection
						(mine).</p>
					<p>Reading books on Archaeology for the Digging piece in May. Fascinating. Also,
						I'm enjoying my privacy. Like being alone.</p>
					<pb n="46"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_046.jpg"/>
					<p>I'm very glad you called me that day as it cleared a lot of conflicts and
						questions and complex mixed-up feelings all colliding in my head. It
						relieved a few tensions, and I felt a release of certain anxieties after
						talking. It was also good to talk with you as the extra dimension in voice
						clarifies the meaning in words so often misread in print....</p>
					<closer><salute>Take care. Love,</salute>
						<signed>Jacki</signed></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>April 5, 1974</date>
						<salute>Dear Jacki</salute> —</opener>
					<p>... It’s wonderful to hear about L’s interest in the piece. It is so bleak up
						here, and New York gets more and more frightening to contemplate from this
						distance. I keep questioning whether I can survive as an artist and get
						worry wrinkles thinking about it.</p>
					<p>Your letter was tremendously supportive. Today I do a videotape of making
						myself up first as beautiful and then as ugly as I can. I have been thinking
						a lot about "vomiting" on people; I see this as playing a joke on
						myself....</p>
					<closer><salute>Love,</salute>
						<signed>Martha</signed></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>April 28, 1974</date>
						<salute>Dear Martha —</salute></opener>
					<p>I wanted to write to you immediately, as soon as I got back from London, as I
						am bursting with things to tell you. That was two weeks ago, and my life has
						been in turmoil, so I am beyond apologies....</p>
					<p>First I want to tell you about the c. 7,500 show in London. I called Tony
						Stokes (at Garage Arts) when I arrived and he seemed very relieved that I
						was there. On Saturday morning I went down to Garage and then with the help
						of a terrific group of London women artists I installed the show in the
						Warehouse next door. It was a perfect space for the show. Very New York raw!
						I must say I did a fantastic job. Did two terrific walls for us, put ting
						our work next to each other’s. Added the B&amp;W contact sheet from
						"Transformance" with your article in the middle. It really looked
						good....</p>
					<p>I have been going through some fairly difficult changes and conflicts. I long
						for my own psychic space, room to grow in, to experience my art in. The time
						has run out for me to continue in the double life of full-time work (job)
						and full-time art. I am exhausted, overstrained, and colliding with myself,
						struggling with hostilities and overextension emotionally. I don’t have
						enough time and I feel like I'm suffocating from spinning too quickly and
						not being able to slow down to breathe deeply...</p>
					<p>Not having money is as paralyzing as not having time. They equalize and
						neutralize each other. Besides, earning one’s own money is part of both the
						real and psychological independence and liberation from the role of the
						woman-child. So I have to search for alternative possibilities. This is
						especially difficult now because the economy is a disaster area. There are
						no jobs any where.</p>
					<p>I am at a point of change in my life, trying to create new structures. The
						piece we did together was a culmination point for me, the end of a cycle....
						I find myself looking into another mirror, seeing a different image.</p>
					<p>The DIGGING piece has become very complex and multi-layered. It is just a
						beginning now, and it might take months to complete. The actual "dig" itself
						will take place in several weeks. When I think about it I get very excited,
						like someone about to take a journey into unknown territory, like going to a
						foreign city after having read a book about its history.... It will be good
						to see you and sit and talk for hours.</p>
					<p>Also it will be interesting to do a tape about the other part of
						TRANSFORMANCE —what we experienced with each other, the risks we took, how
						far we went, how we reacted later, overreacted, then rebalanced; where we
						are now. We plunged into each other’s lives off a high diving board. We went
						very deep, very quickly, and perhaps suffered the mild bends coming up for
						air. It could be a very important tape to go with the piece. Also maybe a
						photo of us today, six months later. Call me when you get to New
						Jersey....</p>
					<closer><salute>Love</salute>, <signed>Jacki</signed></closer>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>May 3, 1974</date></opener>
					<p>Taking diet pills, haven’t slept in 2 nights. Cried on bus w/ Marcia, talking
						about Primal Scream and ego-coasting, being alone. She said R was
						unoriginal, I was the "individual" which shocked me. She sees me as
						courageous, she said in her letter to me, envies me. I love speed, it
						relieves the panic, the separation, substitutes euphoria, wholeness? I wish
						I could stay on it. Have lost some double chin. Dinner tonight with R and
						Marcia. Sat with R yesterday watching John Watt tapes, didn’t feel much. I
						admire him from a distance. I plan to break down in the car tonight, tell
						him I am alone, afraid. He is my father substitute because of his aloofness.
						I should be doing something all the time, can’t do fruitless activity.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>May 5, 1974</date></opener>
					<p>Kicked and screamed w/ R last night, he said there was no sense pretending he
						wasn’t happy. I saw that he was. I felt very hurt, cried a lot over loss of
						children, middle-class life which his marriage to Marcia represents to me. I
						can’t do that now? Now I'm in the kitchen and I feel lethargic, desperate,
						speechless, embarrassed, like being at home. I have to be intellectual
						around him. Isnap at Damian, can’t play, indulge him. Had a dream that I
						stayed in the room below them. I am a frustrated child and I communicate
						that frustration to Damian, I frustrate him. I don't let myself feel. Ate
						cheesecake out of the fridge this a.m. R represents home situation which I
						am trying to resolve. I feel like I have to perform for him. He came in to
						ask what my plans were and for a split second I felt guilty? Not a barrel of
						fun to be with. Have to learn to love myself, whatever that means. Art about
						performing for others. Double exposure = "Exposure</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>May 11, 1974</date></opener>
					<p>My emotions are frozen. I am frightened, not attracted to men. Metaphor,
						describe my parents as luggage. I do what they and authorities say because I
						am afraid they will not love me.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>May 10, 1974</date></opener>
					<p>Feel generally OK. Felt good to see Jacki last night. Saw Nancy Kitchel show
						at 112 Greene St. which put me in awe.</p>
					<p>Darkness, "masking," lit tables, notebooks, folders for papers. Her
						involvement with Vito, a story about tragic encounter, her grandmother’s
						gestures. Talked w/ (Jane) Kleinberg at Whitney about how women are making
						art about separation. I fantasize about my loft. I discover who I am as I go
						along. "Borders occurs to me. I will take photos of rooms during search. I'm
						tired Art about not knowing how I feel about things. Accept, discard. Divide
						objects. Retouched photos of how I want things to appear. How much are we
						defined by our surroundings. Deprived of middle-class life. Photograph the
						fantasy. Marcia and I occupy the same space in relation to R, but opposite
						sides of a single personality pulled in two directions. Forced into a
						position. Men = authority figures, never women. Dad wanted me to pity him,
						told me he was nearly out of a job. Apparently she is ambitious, an
						egomaniac, a blood-curdling bitch. She uses people, squeezes them dry, dumps
						them. Actually, she’s sensitive, retiring, sweet-tempered. </p>
				</div>
				<pb n="47"
					facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_047.jpg"/>
				<div>
					<opener><date>May 12, 1974</date></opener>
					<p>I used to feel like women were the "enemy," men were my best friends. Then I
						didn’t have any respect for myself, treated them like authorities to please.
						Now I feel more comfortable with women, even have a distaste for men. I look
						at attractive men on the subway and experience revulsion. Dad made me afraid
						of him to cover his weakness. Sylvia Plath got at that real hatred every one
						feels for his/her parents. For how they have hurt you. Trembling hands, my
						own fear of incompetence. Videotape of a simple task, hands hammering nails.
						Unfamiliar, incompetent, bad craftsman, danger, "hammering." Stuttering
						videotape, head w/ eyes closed, Mother &amp; Dad dialogue of unsaid
						phrases.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<opener><date>July 26,1974</date></opener>
					<p>Martha and I have lunch at the Plaza Palm Court. Reprise An attempt to
						reexamine, redefine "Claudia" (TRANSFORMANCE). Same setting, shift in
						context, intent. We want to see how we feel, how we act. The mystique
						dissolves. It is, after all, like having lunch any other place. Just a
						restaurant....</p>
					<p>Over too expensive spinach salad we pursue the question of female
						sensibility, questioning whether women artists have become caught in a web
						of confusion between subject matter and "sensibility. Often they choose
						objects, acts and symbols associated with the stereotypes of the female role
						in our culture as content, when they are in fact the objects and conditions
						created by male sensibility and value systems. Do too many women artists
						perpetuate the "system" by attempting to elevate a certain kind of subject
						matter out of proportion to its significance? On the other hand, liberation
						declaring equality continues to enforce the concept of there being no female
						sensibility. "Anything they can do we can do as well if not better"
						thinking. In the struggle to achieve power and position in the art world we
						charge forth into battle to prove this, and the result, which is often
						successful, is also often indistinguishable from the acclaimed and
						established art created by a male sensibility. Again we reenforce their
						system, their concept of reality. Perhaps the only answer, at least the only
						one we can come up with, is to work through an internal view coming from our
						female experience of reality (or lack of it!), and that out of this will
						come some alternative perspectives that also do not end up putting us all
						together in yet another box. Still the same old questions go round in a
						circle. Cultural conditioning and biology. Well, how do we change the
						patterns of the conditioning, making our viewpoint carry equal weight?
						"Claudia was a magnification of role models and stereotypes of power, media
						images programmed into all of us. The "power" of the beautiful, rich woman.
						The illusion of power. We exaggerated it, "lived" in order to also shatter
						it, expose the illusion, blow it up not reenforce it, or validate it. It’s a
						fine line, a delicate balance of form and content, intent and context. Both
						Martha and I have all kinds of ambivalences about that work and whether it
						worked. In two years perhaps we will be able to see it in the right
						perspective, with the distance to analyze it better, understand it in
						relation to female sensibility and art.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p>Martha Wilson, performance artist, began executing private performances or
				"transformations" in 1971. In 1975 and 1976, she performed five chap ters of The
				Arnotated Alice in which the heroine encounters contemporary conventions —social,
				sexual, logical and linguistic. Jacki Apple began doing performances in 1971. Since
				1975 she has been doing installation works exploring psychological space. She and
				Martine Aballea are writing a collaborative novel between New York and Paris. Martha
				is the founder and executive director of The Franklin Furnace Archive for artists’
				books in New York City, and Jacki is its curator. </p>
		</back>

	</text>
</TEI>
