<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Feminists and Non-Feminists in Psychotherapy</title>
				<author>Teresa Bernardez-Bonesatti</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
					<resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb/>
			<div>
				<pb n="16" facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_016.jpg"/>
				<head>Feminists and Non-Feminists in Psychotherapy</head>
				<byline>Teresa Bernardez-Bonesatti</byline>
				<p> As a therapist I have seen feminists and non-feminists in treatment. The women I
					refer to as non-feminists did not initially mention women’s rights, nor did they
					claim participation of any kind in the Women’s Liberation Movement. When we
					later discussed this issue, their reactions ranged from indifference, to
					sympathy for some (usually less radical) as pects of the movement, to open
					hostility In contrast, the women I call feminists referred to themselves as such
					and explicitly supported various aspects of the women's movement. All of them
					believed that women as a group are oppressed, handicapped or otherwise impeded
					in their full development by external forces, whether social institutions,
					cultural mores or men. While they varied in the degree of their actual
					participation in the move ment, all of them had experience in
					consciousness-raising groups. Most of them chose to see me primarily because I
					am a woman, being fairly convinced that a woman would view their concerns with
					more understanding, that she would be less biased than a man, or simply that
					they could talk more freely with a female.</p>
				<p> I have been struck by the differences be tween these two groups in their views
					of their problems, their behavior in our sessions, and their relation to the
					therapist. And perhaps even more important, I have found that feminists appear
					to have resolved successfully developmental stages that non-feminists have
					avoided. Let me briefly explain. Since feminists seek changes in others as well
					as in themselves, they develop more interpersonal skills and an ever-increasing
					sense of self. They are less afraid of their aggressive impulses — in
					particular, anger. They question the requests and expectations of others.
					Feminists do not dislike their sex and have discovered bonds with other women.
					They have achieved separation from important others, whether parents, husbands
					or children. They have asserted their autonomy by defining, protecting and
					defending their own needs, establishing their own goals and directions, with
					increasing trust in their own perceptions, judgment and experience. All of these
					are characteristics of the healthy adult, although feminists are outside the
					culturally defined "norm" for female behavior.</p>
				<p> My observations are based on a study of 60 women — 32 non-feminists and 28
					feminists, ranging in age from 18 to 45, from varied racial and educational back
					grounds, including single, divorced and married women in both groups. The
					feminist group was younger on the average, the oldest woman being 35. My
					descriptions of the behaviors encountered are based on the first two or three
					interviews with these women, although my hypotheses are based on longer
					observation peri ods during which I intervened as a therapist.</p>
				<p> The non-feminists sought psychiatric help for complaints ranging from vague,
					chronic feelings of dissatisfaction, alienation or depression to marital
					conflicts, in ability to be creative, inhibitions in sexual functioning, phobias
					or problems with their children. All of these women, with out exception,
					presented their problems as signs of personal inadequacy. Frequently, they were
					baffled by their discontent, simultaneously pointing out all the advantages of
					their daily lives. As one of the patients put it, “I have a kind husband, three
					healthy children, no financial problems, freedom to study and l’m not happy —
					what’s wrong with me?" This last question was implicit in the statements of most
					of the non-feminists who expressed their malaise in terms of symptoms, had no
					coherent way to explain them, and saw these symptoms as something in them selves
					that needed correction or change. A few stated their wish for understanding, but
					on further inquiry it became clear that for them "understanding" was something
					that would automatically "dissolve" their discomfort. Others who wished to know
					themselves saw a successful outcome as contingent on their ability to correct
					"whatever I am doing wrong.</p>
				<p> If one couples these statements with the behavior of the non-feminist patients
					in the office, one finds a remarkable congruence: these women were not
					assertive, they behaved in a compliant and submissive manner, and they never
					questioned the examiner. They found it hard to be critical of others, while they
					downgraded their own perceptions and feelings, as if they doubted their
					validity. Their emotional responses tended to be limited to the expression of
					sadness, desolation, pain, very frequently accompanied by crying.</p>
				<p> Passive self-references predominated. The non-feminist often responded to
					questions by repeating observations others had made of her behavior, her needs
					or the purposes of her acts. The absence of an active self-referent was so
					striking, that I began to pay attention to how often and in which context the
					personal pronoun I was used. Comments like "it feels better," “my mother says,
					"friends don’t like me to" or “my husband gets irritated at me if" were
					frequent. My impression was that of a woman accustomed to relying on others’
					understanding or reactions to her and unable or unwilling to attempt a more
					active and self- directed search for definition. This characteristic of defining
					the self via others was found among the non-feminists regardless of their
					education, intelligence, age, race and marital status. It was even present in
					those “active" women who demonstrated competence, at home or at work, in areas
					requiring a certain level of decisiveness and organization.</p>
				<p> In contrast, the feminist patients' complaints were largely related to a set of
					already established ideas or goals. They were dissatisfied at finding remnants
					of old behaviors that contradicted their present goals, at their self-defeat in
					attempting to defy the old order, at the failure of their behaviors to elicit
					the desired good feeling about themselves, at their excessive sensitivity to
					criticism or conflicts originating in their attempts to alter their heterosexual
					behavior and relationships. Some of the most militant were attempting to
					introduce changes in traditional organizations or institutions, or worked in pre
					dominantly masculine occupations and were faced with tremendous pressure to
					conform to mores at variance with their own. Their discouragement and distress
					at the frequently negative responses they encountered led them to reexamine
					their goals and their behavior in order to find a <pb n="17" facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_017.jpg"/> compromise that
					would permit them to continue their own development or interest at less cost to
					the self. If they had "symptoms" such as anxiety, depression, periods of low
					self-esteem, sexual inhibitions or guilt feelings, it was not the symptoms they
					focused on but the behaviors, interactions and conflicts that in their opinion
					resulted in those symptoms. These women appeared to have already made a fairly
					exhaustive analysis of the cause-effect relations between their behaviors and
					experiences and the symp toms they generated. They were explicit about their
					goals and aware of both intrapsychic and interpersonal conflicts.</p>
				<p> In this regard, the feminists’ awareness of external sources of pain and
					confusion, for which they did not feel responsible, seemed to help them make
					more and more discriminating judgments between their problems and those of
					others. Their conscious and purposeful engagement in altering the social context
					in which they lived or the persons to whom they related did not hinder their
					examination of their own motives, needs or inadequacies. This capacity was
					largely responsible for these feminists' positive attitude toward their
					"problems." For although they saw them selves as not quite equal to their
					expectations, they also saw their attempts as a desire to grow, to become more
					capable, more self-reliant and more flexible.</p>
				<p> Awareness of their inadequacy to reach desired goals did not lead these
					feminists to question their sanity or their intrinsic neuroticism. Since for the
					most part they believed that the traditional labels ’ill" or neurotic" had been
					incorrectly attached to the victims of oppression whenever they gave signs of
					their pain, their whole view of "treatment" and the psychiatrist’s role in it
					was very different from that of the non-feminists. The feminists were more
					selective in their choice of therapist, more critical of his/her views, more
					knowledgeable of and attentive to therapists' tactics or ideologies that smacked
					of disguised oppression. While the feminist patients sought alleviation of their
					pain and discomfort, they rejected symptomatic treatments. Drugs and biological
					treatments were suspect as repressive tools. Their active, inquisitive and
					critical attitude toward the therapist contrasted with the pliable, unassuming,
					dependent stance the non-feminists took in the beginning of therapy.</p>
				<p> The non-feminists often portrayed the behavior of others in a way that left the
					listener with no doubt that the behavior was destructive, hostile or decidedly
					unjust. Yet they voiced no criticism, nor did they react with open anger. When
					questioned about their feelings, they seemed to have great difficulty voicing
					their anger, particularly toward those upon whom they were dependent financially
					or other wise; more often than not, their quick acknowledgment of anger was
					followed by guilt, self-incrimination and doubts about their femininity. These
					women appeared to dread becoming the stereotype of the "bitchy," “castrating” or
					otherwise aggressively destructive female. Anger toward men, in particular
					intimate male partners, was frequently subdued, avoided or quickly turned into
					aware ness" of their own “demandingness" or unreasonable dissatisfaction. The
					listener was, however, simultaneously briefed about these men’s demanding
					attitude, their insensitivity, exploitation and other blatantly hostile
					behaviors, as if the patient needed outward sanction of these feelings by having
					the therapist voice them first.</p>
				<p> Anger was more freely expressed toward other women. The non-feminists tended to
					see other women as shallow, empty-headed, jealous and untrustworthy. Aside from
					one or two exceptional" female friends, these women seem ed to believe that
					women (themselves included) were justifiable targets of contempt, tending toward
					envy, selfishness and manipulativeness. They thus found themselves isolated from
					other women and considered their company uninteresting and unsatisfactory. While
					they did not voice such feeling in relation to me, when questioned they did
					state that they were concerned about having a female therapist or that I might
					be one of the exceptions" they could trust. On further exploration, it became
					clear that they had mixed feelings. They felt freer speaking to a woman, but
					this was partly due to their low esteem for women. They clearly felt that the
					important judges of their worth and attractiveness were men and that it mattered
					much less whether a woman found them satisfactory. My status as a psychiatrist
					did, however, tip the scales to the other side. Their tendency to respect my
					role as an "expert" and to trust my opinion somewhat uncritically was in line
					with their tendency to respect "authority (particularly malelike authority) and
					their compliance with it.</p>
				<p> The feminists, on the other hand, displayed a greater capacity for critical
					judgment—of the therapist as well as of their cultural milieu—which was in
					direct relation to their tolerance of and ability to voice angry feelings.
					Although at times the intensity of their anger had a disorganizing and even
					paralyzing effect on them, the freedom to express anger verbally and the ability
					to channel some of it into groups or personal goals (fighting school boards, the
					political system, legislation or simply husbands and bosses), plus the sense of
					inner rightness about their claims, clearly differentiated them from the
					non-feminists.</p>
				<p> Anger was sanctioned and indeed encouraged in groups in which these feminists
					found validation and support for their perception of what made them angry.
					Although they had been or still were fighting the image of the “castrating"
					female, they believed that this specter had been raised to dissuade them from
					openness about their dislikes, or from confronting people with their
					contradictions and put-downs. “C-R groups" gave them an additional chance to
					contradict such stereotypes, for these groups provided a great deal of
					nurturance and mutual support.</p>
				<p> In this regard, an important difference between the two groups was found. The
					feminists were able to feel a bond of loyalty and a common source of concern
					with all women—an important developmental stage for females. Their newly found
					"sisterhood"—based on attempting honest friendship, support without moralistic
					judgment, openness and trust, and on the sharing of deep feelings and
					experiences—was of extraordinary import in their ability to channel, utilize and
					tolerate angry and destructive feelings. Although aware that most women would
					part company with them on sticky issues, they envisioned a potential union with
					them and were sympathetic to the plight of women in general. They explained
					other women’s hostilities as the result of their fear of awareness, their
					indoctrination to see women as enemies, their competitive strivings around men
					and the utterly dependent state of most women.</p>
				<p> The non-feminists were isolated from this realm of female experience, having had
					perhaps a few close women friends, but neither knowing nor believing in women’s
					capacity to help one another and to join in creative action. Being alone, and
					usually able to communicate their deepest worries only to the psychiatrist or
					minister, they had no way of realizing how common their concerns were to those
					of other women, or of discovering their own potential capacity to understand,
					help and decide about their own lives. The feminist women had already tested
					this ground in “rap groups" where they had validated their own perceptions,
					gained confidence in their own experiences, <pb n="18" facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_018.jpg"/> achieved a new sense of
					self-enhancement and the ability to assert the self (yet not at the expense of
					others). Although the feminists felt alienated from much of conventional society
					and had to bear consider able stress, they were not alienated from their own
					sex, and they believed that not knowing who they were or what they wanted was
					more insidiously destructive by far than a rude awakening.</p>
				<p> My underlying contention is that feminists have advanced further on the
					developmental ladder and are at a psychological advantage compared to
					non-feminists. I regard as crucial the role the liberation of aggressive impulse
					plays in regain ing self-esteem, achieving separation-individuation and making
					discriminating critical judgment possible. The freedom to tolerate anger, to
					voice it and to channel it into meaningful activity is a prerequisite for
					further change. The pervasive inhibition of aggressive impulses in non-feminists
					drains them of energy; those impulses tend to be directed against the self,
					result ing in self-depreciation, depression and feelings of worthlessness. This
					state of affairs prevents moves toward self assertion since these moves are
					perceived as threatening the precarious balance of dependency on others. In
					contrast, feminists' attitude of defiance is an affirmative stance that provides
					the ability to weather disapproval and criticism from others. Independence and
					autonomy are achieved by struggling against confining expectations at variance
					with those of the self. This posture of feminists forces active interaction with
					others and opens the way for individuation and self-control. It seems important
					to conduct a further study of feminists and non-feminists who do not seek
					treatment. The findings discussed here are relevant only to those women who have
					actively sought help.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p> Teresa Bernardez-Bonesatti is a feminist psychiatrist whose special research
				interest is women and mental health. She is an associate professor of psychiatry at
				the College of Human Medicine, Michigan State University, and chair person of their
				Affirmative Action Committee. </p>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
