<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Women's Fantasy Environments: Notes on a Project in Process</title>
            <author>Noel Phyllis Birkby and Leslie Kanes Weisman</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="116"
               facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_116.jpg"/>
            <head>Women's Fantasy Environments: Notes on a Project in Process</head>
            <byline>Noel Phyllis Birkby</byline>
            <byline>Leslie Kanes Weisman</byline>

            <p> This project is about the process of women giving birth to a new architecture. It
               emerged in 1973 as part of my search for a feminist consciousness and process of
               woman-identification. I had come to realize my own male-identification and
               conditioning — especially as an architect (registered, licensed, numbered,
               legitimatized by the patriarchy). What would a truly supportive environment be if
               women had their way? Would women design the world differently than men? I purposely
               began workshops with women not professionally involved with architecture to avoid the
               machismo conditioning the professional is subjected to. To some extent all women are
               conditioned by the dominant culture, but they usually do not see themselves as
               creators of the built environment. However, all women experience it, react to it,
               live and work in it, and are affected by it, consciously or not. I wanted to help lay
               a foundation for a new architecture based on the experience, consciousness and
               creative imagination of women in the process of self-definition. — NPB </p>
            <p> In 1968 I began teaching architecture, including design "method ology," the process
               by which subjective experience and intuition are systematically objectified and
               rationalized. I was unaware of how one-dimensional this approach is and how it
               isolates mind from body, feeling from action, and divides people into male female,
               white/non-white, rich/poor, old/young. While objective description is important, it
               is incomplete. As I became involved in the women’s movement, I recognized the
               importance of listening to myself, of trusting my own experience. By 1974 I had
               taught hundreds of students, less than one percent of them women, and was still the
               only woman faculty member in the University of Detroit School of Architecture.
               Despite my strong connection to other feminists, I felt painfully fragmented and
               isolated. I urgent ly needed to explore many conflicts between my woman-identity, my
               teaching and the man-made environment, to discover and embrace the environmental
               sensibilities of other women. —LKW </p>
            <p> We began collaborating in 1974, collecting women's drawings of their environmental
               fantasies in workshops conducted across the country, literally "from Maine to
               California." The women constituted a wide cultural cross-section — diverse in life
               style, age, experience and education.</p>

            <p>A workshop participant notes, "Underlying the fantasies is a common kind of
               understanding. I know the sources from which these needs arise. I feel them too.... I
               can relate to the messages in these drawings because l’ve experienced so many of the
               same frustrations, needs and daydreams. They seem to reflect me in them too. It makes
               me feel really connected to other women.</p>
            <p>Readily apparent is the intense hunger for a truly supportive environment. Although
               many drawings reveal humor, whimsy, imagination and complexities, there are
               frequently signs of neglected and unfulfilled needs. There are expressions of anger
               and rage, often convoluted into a light-hearted joke, a defense mechanism familiar to
               many women. The range of vision is characterized by women's multiple rhythms and
               experiences. There is no one dominant statement. Nevertheless, we have noticed
               patterns that speak of shared experiences and common aspirations.</p>
            <p>AUTONOMY, CHOICE AND CONTROL. We see networks of accessibility, intricate support
               systems, a desire for greater mobility in limitless landscapes, a tremendous openness
               usually qualified by a definite need for protection, through either distance or
               symbolic, metaphysical barriers. Many women depict retreats, but most often with some
               connection to the public domain.</p>
            <p>FLEXIBILITY, ADAPTABILITY AND CHANGE. The drawings relate the shifting of human mood
               to the shifting of environmental form over time. Architecture is not static and
               monolithic, but manipulable, expanding and contracting, organically evolving
               —stretchable nets, systems of attachment and separation, multiple purposes,
               recycleable forms.</p>
            <p>LIFE AS A MOSAIC OF CONTINUOUS EXPERIENCE. Many drawings show a spatial organization
               that is multicentered, fluid, informal and non-linear. Time is perceived as a
               continuum, often embodied in swirling movement and spiraling forms.</p>
            <p>INCLUSION OF THE HUMAN DIMENSION. The expression of physical and emotional intimacy
               is consistent. Although there are vast spaces and vertical forms, there is little
               abstraction or monumentality. Spaces are described directly in terms of human
               activity relaxing, dancing, working, screaming, lovemaking, eating.</p>
            <p>INTEGRATION OF BODY/SENSUALITY AND MIND/ORDER. Sensory stimulation plays an important
               role — temperature and climate, surface textures, sounds, smells, the softening of
               hard-edged shapes into more fluid architectural forms. At the same time, work,
               technology, order, thought and access to information are included within these
               spaces. Water, plants, colored prisms, soft pillows and saunas coexist with
               libraries, toolshops, financial institutions and computers.</p>
            <p>RECOGNITION OF LIFE’S COMPLEXITY AND AMBIGUITY. Forms are often open-ended and
               inclusive — tapestries of complication and detail, wheels within wheels of wavelike
               organization, inclusiveness within a private space that shows an awareness of
               multiple scales of experience and relations.</p>
            <pb n="117"
               facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_117.jpg"/>
            <p> The physical world constitutes a necessary component in this program for change as
               women continue to sort out what they want and need for a new society. We know that
               through our condition ing we can adapt to all kinds of spaces, but we also know that
               space can dominate, inhibit, reinforce role patterns. It can remind us we are small
               or large, with or without will. Space itself can be receptive and intrusive,
               expansive and restrictive. In short, it can be a form of either social control or
               support. A supportive environment may be many things to different people. Its
               physical element is but one aspect of what women conceive of as a context in which
               self-actualization can be achieved. A truly supportive environment would consist of
               cooperative, non-competitive, dynamic, in/out interactions with each other, a lack of
               power over relationships and an economic system and atmosphere that encourage the
               development of feminist institutions housed in appropriate forms and spaces of our
               own making. Since this project began, there has been increasingly visible evidence of
               a new women’s culture. We are reclaiming language, poetry music, art, ritual,
               religion. Architecture, curiously referred to by our culture as the "mother of the
               arts," can be reclaimed too. We can learn much from our past, but there is an urgent
               need to listen to our own experience as women if we are to create the morphology of
               the future. —NPB </p>
            <p> Architecture is rarely created in isolation. It must be evaluated and criticized
               within the semiological framework of history and culture. A closer look at the
               man-made environment from a feminist perspective reveals the iconography of the
               patriarchal culture in spatial metaphors. One of the most obvious is the ex treme
               bifurcation between public and domestic environments. The public world of events,
               "man's world," is associated with objectivity, individuality and rational
               functionalism. The private domain, the single-family detached house, "women's world,"
               is associated with subjectivity, cooperation and nurturance. One of the most
               important responsibilities of architectural feminism is to heal this artificial
               spatial schism. We need to find a new morphology, a new architectural language in
               which the words, grammar and syntax synthesize work and play, intellect and feeling,
               action and compassion. This is not a particularly new insight, but I reiterate it
               here because so many women expressed the same vision in their environmental fantasy
               drawings. A feminist architecture will emerge only from a social and ecological
               evolution embodying feminist sensibilities and ideology. Architectural form making is
               a political act. We will not create a new and integrated environment until our
               society values those aspects of human experience that have been devalued through the
               oppression of women. And no one will ever convince me that we have a "revolution
               until I see feminism institutionalized in the nature and quality of the environments
               we build. — LKW</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <p>Noel Phyllis Birkby is a registered architect in New York and teaches archi tectural
            design at Pratt Institute. Leslie Kanes Weisman is a professor of Architecture and
            Environmental Design at New Jersey Institute of Tech nology. Both are long-time feminist
            activists and among the co-founders of the Women’s School of Planning and Architecture.
            They have written for many feminist and professional journals and hope to share their
            collection of drawings in book form. </p>
      </back>

   </text>
</TEI>
