<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Contributors</title>
            <author>Collective</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <div>
            <pb n="0"/>
            <p> HERESIES is an idea-oriented journal devoted to the examination of art and politics
               from a feminist perspective. We believe that what is commonly called art can have a
               political impact, and that in the making of art and of all cultural artifacts our
               identities as women play a distinct role. We hope that HERESIES will stimulate
               dialogue around radical political and aesthetic theory, encourage the writing of the
               history of femina sapiens, and generate new creative energies among women. It will be
               a place where diversity can be articulated. We are committed to the broadening of the
               definition and function of art.</p>
            <p> HERESIES is structured as a collective of feminists, some of whom are also
               socialists, marxists, lesbian feminists or anarchists; our fields include painting,
               sculpture, writing, anthropology, literature, performance, art history, architecture
               and filmmaking. While the themes of the individual issues will be determined by the
               collective, each issue will have a different editorial staff made up of contributors
               as well as members of the collective. Each issue will take a different visual form,
               chosen by the group responsible. HERESIES will try to be accountable to and in touch
               with the international feminist community. An open evaluation meeting will be held
               after the appearance of each issue. Themes will be announced well in advance in order
               to collect material from many sources. (See inside of back cover for list of
               projected issues.) Possibly satellite pamphlets and broadsides will be produced
               continuing the discussion of each central theme.</p>
            <p> As women, we are aware that historically the connections between our lives, our arts
               and our ideas have been suppressed. Once these connections are clarified they can
               function as a means to dissolve the alienation between artist and audience, and to
               understand the relationship between art and politics, work and workers. As a step
               toward a demystification of art, we reject the standard relationship of criticism to
               art within the present system, which has often become the relationship of advertiser
               to product. We will not advertise a new set of genius-products just because they are
               made by women. We are not committed to any particular style or aesthetic, nor to the
               competitive mentality that pervades the art world. Our view of feminism is one of
               process and change, and we feel that ir the process of this dialogue we can foster a
               change in the meaning of art.</p>
            <p> THE COLLECTIVE: Ida Applebroog, Patsy Beckert, Joan Braderman, Mary Beth Edelson, Su
               Friedrich, Janet Froelich, Harmony Hammond, Sue Heinemann, Elizabeth Hess, Joyce
               Kozloff, Arlene Ladden, Lucy Lippard, Marty Pottenger, Miriam Schapiro, Amy Sillman,
               Joan Snyder, Elke Solomon, Pat Steir, May Stevens, Susana Torre, Elizabeth
               Weatherford, Sally Webster, Nina Yankowitz.</p>
            <p> This issue of HERESIES was edited and produced by three groups which met separately
               and together for more than four months: a nine-woman editorial collective, which
               takes final responsibility for the magazine; an eight-woman adjunct group which
               worked on general ideas, research and specific articles; and a five-woman
               design/production group. Still other women helped with additional aspects, such as
               copyediting, proofreading and mechanicals, and the larger HERESIES Collective
               supported us all. Because of the number of women involved and the number of
               manuscripts received (more than twice as many as were submitted to our first issue),
               the process was complex. Editorial work was new to most of us, and we needed a lot of
               time to listen to each other, to reflect on our disparate experiences and
               viewpoints—and to develop an overview of the magazine, which finally affected our
               decisions almost as much as individual submissions. We worked collectively on each
               piece, arriving at a consensus only after much discussion. Sometimes we frustrated
               those authors and artists who had hoped to hear more from us sooner. As we worked, we
               found that we were indeed involved in a process of communication with all the women
               who wanted to participate in this issue, as well as with each other. If this process
               was at times confusing, it was also intensely satisfying. </p>
            <p> As this issue went into production, Ree Morton, an artist whose friendship, work and
               commitment to feminism made her close to many ofus, died of injuries sustained in an
               automobile accident. We will miss her. </p>
            <p> Editorial group: Patsy Beckert, Lizzie Borden, Janet Froelich, Denise Green, Sue
               Heinemann, Diane Levin, Lucy Lippard, Pat Steir, Elizabeth Weatherford.</p>
            <p> And: Ida Applebroog, Karen Harris, Stephanie Brody Lederman, Karen Shaw, Theodora
               Skipitares, Amy Snider, Carla Tardi, Mimi Weisbord.</p>
            <p> Design/production group: Barbara Coleman, Paula Greif, Suzanne Kuffler, Francesca de
               Majo.</p>
            <p> Our thanks to those who helped get out this issue: Barbara Baracks, Marina
               Cappalletto, Nicole Croiset, Tony DeLuna, Debbie Dominguez, Birgit Flos, Maria
               Friedrich, Su Friedrich, Paula Harper, Laurie Leifer, Diana Long, Mary Lou Lopez,
               Melissa Meyer, Margot Norton, Lawrence Pitkethly, Bernie Rohret, Sarah Schuman, Amy
               Sillman, Jackie Wray, Nil Yalter, Ruth Young; our lawyer, Eleanor Fox; and our
               photographers, eeva- inkeri.</p>
            <p> HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics is published in January, May,
               September and December by Heresies Collective, Inc. at the Fine Arts Building, 105
               Hudson Street, New York, N.Y. 10013. Subscription rates: $10 for four issues; $16 for
               institutions. Outside the U.S. add 52 postage. Single copy: 53. Address all
               correspondence to HERESIES, P.O. Box 766, Canal Street Station, New York, N.Y. 10013.
               HERESIES, ISSN 0146-3411. Vol. 1, No. 2, May 1977. O 1977 Heresies Collective. All
               rights reserved. On publication, all rights revert to authors.</p>
            <p> This issue of HERESIES was typeset by Myrna Zimmerman in Palatino, with headlines
               set by Talbot Typographics, Inc. Also thanks to Daniel Shapiro. Printed by the
               Capital City Press, Montpelier, Vermont. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
