<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>3 Short Fictions</title>
            <author>Lucy Lippard</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="22"/>
            <head>3 short fictions</head>
            <byline>lucy r. lippard</byline>
            <div>
               <head>1. the cries you hear</head>
               <p> The rocks trembled every day for over two months and in parts of Tibet a sick
                  person or a woman who had given birth to a child was carefully prevented from
                  sleeping. Sometimes the flower is so constructed that the insect cannot get at the
                  nectar without brushing against a stigma which, perhaps because males tend to fall
                  asleep more rapidly than females after intercourse, returns to stone needles. In
                  the process of collapse the star’s outer layers compress. Lying naked in the
                  pouring rain, our wetness the world’s wetness, our hard bodies the makings of
                  rock. We took no photographs. The vacant plains were a featureless screen on which
                  we projected our memories of rivers forests oceans and mountains, of elsewhere —
                  quick! Before it....</p>
               <p> Meanwhile, the females of the indispensable earthquake rest quietly in the
                  half-closed blossoms, sharing the power of sleep, oblivious to our pain. I was
                  long in doubt concerning the origins of these conditions of stress, horror and
                  exhaustion. That two different organisms should have simultaneously adapted
                  themselves to each other. During the third severe shock the trees were so
                  violently shaken that the birds flew out with frightened cries. Bubblelike
                  cavities formed by expanding gas. Solid pieces blown violently out of the womb.
                  Glass surfaces, brittle and gleaming, formed by rapid solidification. Touch me
                  here. Wrinkles, pores in the earth’s skin, basalt lavas swelling from beneath,
                  channeled in fissures, dust and ash. The cries you hear are only the continuing
                  shock of life. </p>
               <p> "It is a fatal delusion which presents the earth as the lower half of the
                  universe and the heavens as its upper half. The heavens and earth are not two
                  separate creations, as we have heard repeated thousands and thousands of times.
                  They are only one. The earth is in the heavens. The heavens are infinite space,
                  indefinite expanse, a void without limits; no frontier circumscribes them, they
                  have neither beginning nor end, neither top nor bottom, right nor left; there is
                  an infinity of spaces which succeed each other in every direction.</p>
               <p> A mountain chain is an effective barrier. The slow movement of underground waters
                  carrying silica into sandstone. Limestone metamorphosed is marble. Bedding planes
                  obscured and mineral impurities drawn out into swirling streaks and bands,
                  swirling streaks and bedding planes obscured. He is tall and arrogant, questioning
                  and vulnerable. Cold tar will shatter if struck but will flow downhill if left
                  undisturbed for a long time. Shattered and flowing, flowing and shattered if
                  struck. Hard things that were soft. Soft things that were hard. Hot things that
                  were cold. Cold things that were hot. Wet things that were dry. Dry things that
                  were wet. Old things that were young. Young things that won’t be old. It stops
                  somewhere? Prove it.</p>
               <p> Under the mist a solid prose of rocks, rocks and water, hard rocks and flowing
                  water, safe rocks and treacherous water. Rough rocks, motion frozen to the touch,
                  thorny black volcanic piles, a vein, an aggregate, a channel worn away, a pit
                  blown or swirled out, grains, knife edges vertical. And smooth rocks, covered with
                  pale and slippery algae, soothed to a fine old gentleness. Patterns of water,
                  ancient muds, slow curves.</p>
               <p> In some alpine mountains high above the timberline, sheets of frost-shattered
                  rock fragments creep slowly down the valleys making curious tonguelike forms. My
                  mouth. My tongue makes love to my mouth, searching its cavities for the softest,
                  wettest places to fondle, sliding past and over the hard sharp teeth so that it
                  hurts a little, overlapping, lapping its own roughness, slipping across the
                  toothmounds under the gums and falling into the dark throat. Craving in. Prose,
                  not poetry. Its tentacles reach in more directions at once, from a solider base,
                  at a natural pace. It circles and radiates, has a core and a skin and a network of
                  capillaries instead of only arteries. Memories wear away the present to an older
                  landscape. My leg, thicker at the top than at the bottom, stronger at the bottom
                  than at the top, stranger at the top than at the bottom, more useful at the bottom
                  than at the top. At the top, plump flesh held firmly between thumb and forefinger,
                  a few long fine hairs on the broadest whitest part. Smooth and soft and secret
                  lining where other hairs intrude from other sources - darker, coarser. A crease
                  separating the leg from the rest of the body, a crease that changes character as
                  the leg is used for <pb n="23"/> different things, a soft crease when I am
                  sitting, a mysterious crease when I am lying with one leg curled to my stomach, no
                  crease at all when I am walking, but creased again when running, sometimes. A taut
                  surface when held back, a valley between bulges when not. A leg slimming gradually
                  to a knotted center where the bones assert themselves. A hard hairy hilltop, then
                  a wrinkled old topography flattened into valleys. A leg that swells again, harder
                  this time, smooth again, with a neatly turning strength of its own, a leg that is
                  straight in front and soft-hard in back, flat then rounded, a leg that finally
                  gives way to ankle and foot, the working parts detached from pleasure places
                  above. The bony not so pretty skeletons of motion, fleshed only around the ankle
                  bones, arched over the instep and finally twice in touch with the earth.</p>
               <p> Each major time unit is brought to a close by orogeny, also called revolution.
                  Disturbance, disruption, disintegration, under pressure. Even the strongest rocks
                  may develop fractures. Deep decay and rotting of igneous and metamorphic rocks,
                  from blocks to egg and sphere shapes. Water entering into union with minerals.
                  Metamorphic rocks have undergone kneading and shaping, baking and shaking, shale
                  turning to slate when split by cleavage, by slippage, during the process. Slate
                  when struck sharply rings metallically. Clay comes in all colors. Playing the
                  geomorphic role of a weak rock, staring at each other but not speaking until
                  finally. A poetic geology to take back to the red hills, white clay to merge as
                  pink. Isolated submarine mountains, the ocean floor pulled apart here, causing a
                  rift, a certain cruelty. Alone is better I say. Then stop the invasion. If you see
                  two scorpions together they are either making love or one of them is being eaten.
                  Aries energy stepped back into the earth. My rock, your mesas. Ice needles pry
                  apart joint blocks, tremendous pressures and bare high cliffs fall off into
                  conical forms, especially in dry climates. Niches, shallow caves, rock arches,
                  pits, cliff dwellings. Come now. Yes/No. In deserts, flash floods and earthflows,
                  mudflows result from the inability of the dry land to permeate the perma frost.
                  Shrinking and swelling. Given sufficient time, barriers can be broken down and new
                  topographies arise. An unbridgeable gulf does not exist between organic and
                  inorganic matter.</p>
               <p> Drift, and erratic boulders are ascribed to mineral richness, to the action of
                  great waves, but women’s tides told in the caves refute such theories. Play pale
                  beyond. In a climate warmer than that we warned each other, islands separated from
                  ice cover by a wide expanse of ocean, foregoing clubs for quieter power, fleshed
                  fat and knowing. Warm interglacial leaves, closer to the fires, hands in a ring,
                  shadows on the ceilings, circles drawn at dusk, footsteps from below. The
                  occasional peculiar transportation of boulders in a manner not in harmony with
                  what we see ice doing at the present time. But little girls are crafty. Our
                  laughter pits the ocean floor. Echoing with pebble talk, scratched on anemones.
                  Walls curving inward toward us. No windows. Pictures nonetheless. Melted between
                  sisters in collision. Only global catastrophes could have brought about that
                  smoothness. Only torrential rains, wet hair, wet cheeks. Each other. Barren stone
                  and fragmented debris stops here, swept back while lakes and valleys are dug out
                  by other women. Each a specialist in her field. What generates the enormous forces
                  that bend, break and crush the rocks in mountain zones? What indeed. Women’s
                  cataclysmic work, traced by fingers in the meteoric dust. Giving birth to each
                  other. Excessive.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2. into among</head>
               <p>Stepping down and out. Someone else can move into this house. It looks o.k. from
                  the outside but the inside needs some work. I only regret how long it took to get
                  down those stairs to the basement. Overhead the pretty flowered curtains make
                  wavered patterns on the sunny floor. A tomato is rotting fuzzily in the icebox
                  drawer and other closets capture other odors, other faults. Under the bed dust
                  gathers roses smell acrid. The sheets at the hamper’s bottom were stained last
                  winter, not since. l’ve opened the windows but not the doors. It’s all yours, if
                  you want it.</p>
               <p> Nesting fantasies. I am high in the tallest tree in the world and it sways in the
                  wind. Exhilarating, precarious. I cling to my egg which is disguised as the sea.
                  When the fish hatches I swim through the air until I find a cave, brown, humid,
                  and grainy, where after a night with the boulder another egg is laid, this one
                  transparent. l’m happy watching the beginnings of a new dream. It sometimes has
                  petals, sometimes blades. One morning the walls are opaque and that’s that. Dead
                  leaves turn to stone and I would leave but for the field of snakes that writhes
                  beyond the entrance.</p>
               <p> Shuttered. Unhinged. Falling off the roof. A nice white clapboard house with a
                  soft green lawn, lace curtains at the windows, roses on a trellis over the door,
                  the old fanlight sparkling when the light hits it. We need a very long time to
                  move up the flagstone walk. In the process a war takes place, peace reigns, men
                  land on the moon and women defend it, black blankets of oil are thrown across
                  birds’ coffins and the sea stinks. Still the little house remains, the sun always
                  dappling its freshly painted walls, the sound of piano scales twinkling delicately
                  behind the curtain of warmth. When we reach the door we are exhausted, gray,
                  crippled, and in pain. The doorknob, though brilliantly brass, is cold to our
                  touch and the door sticks. It takes our last strength to open it and throw
                  ourselves across the threshold onto what should be a rosy hearth but is instead a
                  deep dark well, the bottom of which, at this telling, we have not reached.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <pb n="24"/>
               <head>3. headwaters</head>
               <p>
                  <quote>For reasons of their own, women are suspicious of diving and frown on their
                     menfolk going down. D—, who has starred in several underwater films, has never
                     received a fan letter from a woman. </quote>-<ref>Jacques Cousteau</ref> We are
                  already down there. We have already gone down, our breasts bumping the boulders
                  struggling to rise. Our menfolk don’t know where to send the fan letters. Can
                  dive, but not delve. Perhaps far down are boundaries between layers of water not
                  obvious at the surface of the sea and quite independent of surface phenomena. Not
                  just still waters. Rapture of the depths. At a town called Headtide there is an
                  old white church unconsciously marking with its spire the spot where the Sheepscot
                  River, short and wide, a tidal estuary, comes to an end in a stony brook and then
                  goes underground. The term tidal wave is loosely applied. Some rivers braid long
                  plaits of sand with thinning streams, and others — always full, muddy and sated —
                  lag in fat banks. Tides are most marked when the sun is nearest the earth. Tides
                  thigh tickling, oozing over the edges and hummocks, a band of foam, making liquid
                  land. Creeps up me toward immersion. Hold your waters. Making waves, seeing red. I
                  flow she flows we flow. Lunar and solar tides coincide, are fully cumulative only
                  twice each lunar month. While fans unfold, snap shut, and leave the flowers no
                  escape. Underwater, irregularities rise and, cursing, fall. Two or more wave
                  patterns at the same place and time. There can, however, be independent waves. And
                  long rivers pass through different landforms like changing lovers. Impatiently
                  cutting gorges, willing waterfalls and rapids to flatness. Unfamiliar bodies
                  hurled at each other. Beneath the rumbling, boulders lurk and lurch, needing a
                  pool.</p>
               <p>My traveling dreams are washed in foreign waters. In one I swim along a beach. The
                  water is warm and the same pale blue as the sky — bleached but not burning. Behind
                  me swims a large black dog and before me floats a group of exotic birds, brilliant
                  pink feathers wet but still light, raised above the water in a tangle of wings.
                  The end of the beach is distant; all sand, no rocks or trees in sight. My swimming
                  is leisurely but purposeful. In another dream I wake alone and rush to find my
                  lover. He is in the bathtub and I yell desperately at him: Did I sleep alone last
                  night? Did I sleep alone last night? Another night, my child, my lover and I are
                  going to see a lighthouse through a swamp. The waterway is not very wide. Trees
                  hang dense over the edges but in the center where we swim it’s blue, unshaded. A
                  long trip to make boatless, but we are swimming, accompanied at times by a fat
                  friend. l’m not struck by the fact that we are swimming so much as by the length
                  of the trip, not tired so much as a little bored. Once again the water is tepid,
                  body temperature, lulling. The lighthouse when we get there is on a broader bay,
                  still inland, mountains in the distance. There is some talk of leaving and
                  returning in the afternoon. But there isn’t time.</p>
               <p>The waters broke with no warning. Lie still, pretend while it crests. Above our
                  caves the divers’ forms pass dimly, unaware. Destructive advances of the sea upon
                  the coasts have two distinct origins: dreams like sunwarmed flats when the tide
                  comes in very slowly, visibly; earthquakes and storms. Neither related to the
                  tide, and often not actually waves. Floating, I am a fleshy layer between sea and
                  sky. Why go down? Letters melt and corals build. Why go down and not feel the moon
                  in the pit of your stomach? Or hear ripples whisper on the floor? The ocean’s
                  bedrock blurred. Unexpected, the cold and purifying northern channels. With no
                  warning, water on the brain, the belly, breast and buttock. Internal waves stained
                  pink affecting everything below above. Doesn’t hold water, that’s all. Divers ring
                  their bells but fail to reach us, cannot pierce the bubbles that contain them. And
                  we are already down there, friendly, calm, constructing small places in which to
                  wait, making room for others, settling in, exchanging disguises, rearranging caves
                  and mountains, waiting until they stop pouring oil on the waters, till they stop
                  throwing rocks, sinking ships, turning our tides.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <p>Lucy Lippard is a feminist art critic who also writes "fiction"; it has been published
            in Center, Big Deal, Tractor, The World and elsewhere. </p>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
