<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>In Her Image</title>
            <author>Deena Metzgar</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            			<pb n='2'/>
         	<head>In Her Image*</head>
         	<byline>Deena Metzger</byline>
         	<p>* Revised and excerpted from the manuscript of an unpublished book, In Her Image: Woman’s Culture, 1976.</p>
			<p>
				Woman has always been associated with the dark, with the
				unknown. It has been in society’s interest to consider women unknowable; that has been one of the devices to keep us from
				power. Separated then from the "light" of the dominant society,
				we women have perpetuated a culture of our own, expressed in
				our own forms, which has frequently been transmitted, as is the
				case with other oppressed cultures, in subtle, uncodified ways.
				Not taught in schools, it is communicated in the home, through
				kinship lines, laterally through sisters, grandmothers, friends. Influenced and affected by the dominant cultures within or against
				which it must exist, this culture nevertheless seems to incorporate
				certain universal elements which may in part be due to the fact
				that women everywhere are socialized into similar roles and oppressions. Ironically, despite our universal oppression, women
				seem to have survived as the guardians of certain human values
				necessary to the survival of humanity. At the same time, these
				values undermine the anti-human thrust of contemporary industrial and technological life. In bourgeois society, this contradiction is solved through the relegation of women to the home, and
				our isolation from public life, which prevents those values from
				entering the public sphere. Similarly, these contributions are further devalued through their association with women and they
				consequently lose their power to influence the direction of the
				dominant culture. Certain survival values then persist in isolation
				within the circumscribed female domain.
			</p>
			<p>
				Woman’s culture is the complex expression of a woman’s sensibility, the interaction of knowledge, values, rituals, organizations
				and attitudes resulting from the interaction of role, biology, historical conditions and memory. It has developed forms which
				deny aggression, competition, rank and power—essentially nonhierarchical, intimate and cooperative forms. The tone with
				which women address each other when we are alone, calling each
				other immediately by our first names, the conversations women
				have with other women are, in themselves, models of the entire
				culture. Woman’s conversation is a particular form of communication in which seemingly simple interchanges, as well as sophisticated theoretical and analytical discussions, incorporate a complex of other activities. When women speak to each other, the
				sentence functions both to communicate information and to establish intimate connection between women. Woman’s conversa
				tion is often confined to intuition, accompanied by non-verbal
				interaction, touch, eye contact, which enhance the intensity of
				the interchange.
			</p>
			<p>
				Women tend, when possible, to search for the common denominator, for the area of common and meaningful experience.
				Women so often talk about “women’s things" because they are
				more interested in the feeling of community than in an abstract
				interchange, and what are commonly deprecated as "women's
				things" are in fact those events of daily life common to everyone’s
				experience. For example, when we introduce ourselves to each
				other, we tend to avoid professional definitions, offering general
				statements about our lives, some bit of information which can
				create an intimate experience. Particularly since consciousness
				raising, we introduce ourselves in terms of personal struggle,
				openly communicating the current internal dilemma or problem:
				"T’ve just divorced" or "T’m trying to get my life together."
				Women are willing to reveal the raw materials in order to
				explore together. Women’s conversations may have a more "unfinished" quality because we begin at the unknown rather than
				the known. If men’s conversations reveal, women’s conversations
				explore.
			</p>
			<p>
				I wish to create here a form appropriate to the subject of
				woman’s culture which reflects those attitudes and values integral
				to that culture. I think of this article as a conversation rather than
				a monologue and have tried to create spaces that elicit response.
				Rather than embody material, information, illustration in
				footnotes that indicate a secondary status or a formal acknowledgment of authority, I prefer to provide complementary space
				for the other voices which inform this article. A form that more
				honestly acknowledges the informal and constant exchange of
				ideas. I see these pages as places reserved for other women writers
				and artists to participate as partners. I invite the reader to use
				them to respond, think, make notes and add to what I have written according to her own insights and imagination.
			</p>
			<p>
				<quote>
				"And so our mothers and grandmothers have, more often
				than not anonymously, handed on the creative spark, the seed of
				the flower they themselves never hoped to see: or like a sealed
				letter they could not plainly read."</quote> <ref>(Alice Walker, "In Search of
				Our Mothers Gardens," Ms. Magazine, May 1974.)</ref>
			</p>
			<p>
				So we begin again here to negotiate a form as if this were a
				conversation between us which contained references to other conversations, to our work, to those asides wherein we discover how
				we come to know this, reminding each other of previous discussions, those stolen moments in the kitchen, carpooling, when we
				meet in the supermarket, in the offices, the TV stations, the lecture rooms, those moments when we emphasize an idea by extending our hands to each other, the pressure of fingers on the
				upper arm, speaking a sentence of verbs, nouns, prepositions,
				affection, solidarity and acknowledgment. This does not come
				from me alone; I learned it from you; we have been passing it
				through our minds and bodies and conversations for years now.
				Virginia gave it word-flesh when she asked us to create the woman’s sentence. Well, we have made it, we are making it. The
				woman’s sentence, the woman’s paragraph, the woman’s build
				ing, the woman’s design, the woman’s portrait. ..forms as complex as their forms, but our forms, different forms, responsive to
				our own values, experiences, priorities. Each one of us knows one
				form. I will tell one, you another, then Barbara, Jane, Sheila, all
				the women I know.</p>
				<p>"Give an example," Martha says.</p>
				<p>"Okay, Martha. Thank you." Your urging helped me to
				come to this form which is our form, a conversation not a dissertation. Between sentences, I am listening for your comments,
				incorporating them, answering them, and listening for them once
				more. That listening, asking, incorporating, is characteristic of
				us, we who are attentive. But now we bring that form into the
				public domain as one of the new ways.
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>

			<p>
				"Since childhood, women have always been bricoleurs,
				creating structures by means of events, making-do, constructing
				whole lives out of leftovers, devising entire, though miniature
				worlds out of their peripheral status and tasks. Such worlds
				rivaled the male spheres in complexity, interest and involvement.
				They were worlds made of smaller and homelier materials but
				built in proportion, involving the entire range of social processes, as full-bodied as the external, male-dominated realm. In her
				own miniature world, the woman was in charge, using time and
				energy according to her own lights. Within the structured points
				of her day in the household, she did a great many highly diverse
				tasks, all at the same time, always expecting to be interrupted,
				never expecting full closure, bustling from one activity to the
				next, watching her work come undone as soon as completed.
				(Barbara G. Myerhoff, from an unpublished paper “The Older
				Woman as Androgyne: Sexual Stereotypes and Innovations.")
			</p>
			<p>
				Women tend to focus on the person being spoken to. What
				do you want to know? What do you need from me? Women do
				not commonly tell each other jokes or puns, preferring more responsive forms. "You know how it is" invites identification and
				laughter, often bitter. The tendency of some women to raise rather than lower their voices at the end of sentences does not imply
				uncertainty so much as invitation, willingness to negotiate and
				desire for response and interaction.</p>
				<p>One of the basic functions of women’s conversations is nurturance. When women talk to each other, we simultaneously take
				care of each other, provide comfort, communicate information
				and verify a common reality through the discovery of basic common experience. It is not enough to find "common interests” but
				to discover those that are essential to, not oblique to, existence.</p>
				<p>The anxiety aroused because women talk about the essentials allows for our conversation to be characterized as gossip, trivial,
				materialistic. Women, in fact, talk about others, about children,
				clothes, cooking, the "stuff of life," because these are the universals, the common essential ingredients of existence.</p>
				<p>Women who wish to participate in the public sphere as women rather than to conform to male standards as a condition of
				both entry and survival need to examine our own forms and their
				sources in order to integrate these forms into public institutions
				and behaviors.</p>
				<p>How does one communicate this information? The language
				appropriate to formal presentation is heavy and abstract. Each
				idea is confined within a noun and those are arranged in order.
				One says "immediate," "integrated," "continuous," "collective,"
				"personal"... But when we speak about it together, we create
				another tone and style...</p>
				<p>When Sheila is invited to enter a design competition on the
				subject of color, she asks women friends and associates of various
				ages, including young girls, to respond to the color pink on small
				squares. These are organized into a grid in which no piece is more
				important than another. The poster permits women to respond to
				a color which has been socially devaluated. Pink is assigned to
				women; baby pink, thrust upon us during infancy, remains our
				color through old age. Its associations are with infantilism, indulgence, frivolity. How, then, can we claim it? Yet the responses on
				the pink cards indicate strength, assurance, energy. They contradict the preconceptions. When the piece is finished, the color has
				new associations representing a wide range of responses. The individual statements become a collective self-portrait, a self-exami
				nation, facilitating the reevaluation of pink and of ourselves. The
				poster is responsive. It is a non-hierarchical structure. It is a communal effort. It evokes a variety of responses. It is complex. It
				provides for reevaluation. It makes a feminist statement in form
				as well as in content.</p>
				<p>Why do I begin with Sheila? Because we came to this at the
				same time although quite independently. Sheila was the organizer
				of the first Feminist Design Program at Cal Arts. She is also one
				of the organizers of the Feminist Studio Workshop and of the
				Woman’s Building. She was teaching design and I was teaching
				literature. We were both pursuing our private design and writing.
				Looking at women’s work from historical and critical perspectives, we discovered that it exhibited basic affinities despite his
				torical and national barriers. This work does not yield easily to
				analysis with ordinary critical tools, as it departs from the
				dominant modes, goals and value systems. As we attempted to
				weave an appropriate feminist critical perspective, we realized
				that woman’s work corresponds to a particular organization of
				time and space and to a frequent reference to the immediate and
				the everyday.
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				Perhaps we should pause here, creating an interruption corresponding to the interruptions that women expect and incorporate into our own work, the spaces that permit permeation and
				invite response. We are not concerned here with the transfer of
				information so much as a simulation of the experience in which
				we come to know things; we are concerned with the context of
				information, how it comes from us and from our lives. No matter
				hów abstract, no matter how formal, women’s work is connected
				at one point at least to the fundamental realities, to our bodies, to
				our everydays, to our dreams. When our work is our work, it is
				always also of ourselves.
			</p>
			<p>
				It is said that woman is nature and man is culture.... It is
				true that woman, for a variety of reasons, is more sensitive to
				natural forces, cycles, rhythms, as role and biology always thrust
				her into the immediate and domestic existence. If this sensitivity
				is expressed in behaviors that are responsive rather than closed, it
				is mistaken to assume that response is negative or imposed. Response requires openness, willingness, action, and like withdraw
				al, implies choice.</p>
				<p>It has been woman’s habit to create structures and behaviors
				that are both systematic and responsive. Women create culture as
				men do, but not having created a dominant culture, we act privately within forms that remain largely invisible to the public
				scrutiny although they are sufficiently forceful and intense to be
				communicated laterally and historically.</p>
				<p>When we hear the words "immediate" and "everyday," we
				associate them with values ascribed to the woman’s sector. They
				are the mundane, unimportant, banal, and we feel the anxiety
				which Western civilization terms "imprisonment in the here and
				now." "Imprisonment" itself refers to forms of closure that threaten male separateness and disengagement, such as possessiveness,
				enchantment, the vagina dentata. Similarly, "flux" stimulates cultural anxieties associated with chaos, death, unpredictability, sexuality, male anxieties regarding mortality, against which are op
				posed principles of permanence, eternity and transcendence.</p>
				<p>The male-dominated movie screen informs us that modern
				"life" is a series of boring episodes which can only be interrupted
				by violent explosions. But the ordinary, from a woman’s view, is
				hardly ordinary. It is repetitive, it is full of trivia, it is necessary,
				maddening, contingent, it is never-ending, but it is also, as in
				Papilla Estelar, wonder-full or awe-full. And women’s art reflects
				this power of the immediate.</p>
				<p>Gertrude, for example, predicates a style upon the immediate
				or the "continuous present," as she calls it, "using everything and
				beginning again." And beginning again. A cycle of repetition, of
				rhythm, everything told so completely and so simply that existence emerges as a fact and language becomes “an entire space
				always moving not something moving through a space."</p>
				<p>Men are associated with behaviors that strive toward permanence as opposed to continuousness. That men legislate and
				women gossip may be a reflection of men’s interest in autonomous social control as opposed to personal interaction. An organized and ordered society emerges. Facts of nature become
				anomalies, violations. Economic cycles, plagues, age, rain, children, sun, disease, menstruation, fatigue, fiesta, are all disturbances of the perfect unchanging order, inconveniences rather
				than essential conditions, factors to be mitigated or eliminated.
			</p>
			<p>
				Interruption is a basic condition of a mother’s life. One of the
				reasons for the segregation of the work world from the home is in
				order to avoid the interruptions of the daily life. In the home, one
				is constantly interrupted by need and continuous time is not
				available. Home is not the place where one can establish a hierarchy of priorities. It may be more "important” to write an
				address to the United Nations, but the crying baby takes precedence nevertheless. Women know that life has the terrible habit
				of asserting itself. The woman writing her doctoral thesis, the
				judge presiding at a trial, is also, simultaneously, thinking about
				the broccoli for dinner, the child’s dentist appointment, the death
				of a friend. Women’s art forms reflect the condition of interruption and simultaneity in a variety of ways.
				Scars on the Body Politic, a novel I completed in 1975, is
				actually interrupted several times by actual events, equivalents of
				the “crying child." They imposed “non-negotiable demands"
				upon the material; they had to be heeded and incorporated in the
				framework of the book. In one section I actually say, “This is the
				place where the book was interrupted."</p>
				<p>Similarly, women’s works often have an unfinished quality
				— are anti-art art pieces, more faithful to the reality corresponding to the idea that only art, not life, can ever be finished. A journal, for example, which women are coming to recognize as a
				work in itself, and not the source for the work, is often a collection of thoughts, fragments, ideas, perceptions, descriptions,
				dreams, conversations, jotted down at odd moments, in sentences
				or codes, according to time and mood. In a class taught on
				“Autobiography, Journals and Life Histories,” the students wrote
				more fluently when they were freed from the tyranny of the complete sentence. Given permission to write in fragments and notes,
				they could record their lives in a way they felt was more appropriate to their experience. The women more than the men responded to the more open form.
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				Integration is a significant characteristic of woman’s work
				Many parts tend to be represented in a single work. Into the daily
				life come the essential realities of existence, biology and death.
				The universal weds the specific; the ordinary and extraordinary
				dance; the wonderful refuses to be separated from the mundane.
				Remedios Varo captures this integration in Papilla Estelar
				(1958). The painting shows a woman dressed in black, seated in a
				poor, cramped and barren house set within the heavens. She is
				grinding the stars through a kitchen meat grinder and feeding this
				stellar mixture to a domesticated moon confined within a bird
				cage. The eternal and the contingent, the metaphysical and the
				mundane coexist. This is one of several paintings by Remedios
				Varo that capture the forms of woman’s culture. It is ironic that
				Remedios is categorized by art critics as a surrealist. Extraordinary as her vision may appear to the dominant culture, it is for us
				simply the complex accurate image of a female world view.
			</p>
			<p>
				Woman is more sensitive to flux, cycle, to the transitory as
				the basis of experience. Change is part of her daily life while permanence, fixity are eccentric events. The cycle is a concept which
				coordinates repetition and change. Completeness has a satisfying
				resonance and is a reasonable female goal. Intensity rather than
				eternity. That work and art which reflect these female concerns do
				not always look like "work" because they are organized differently
				is another reflection of the simplifying tendencies of the dominant
				culture.</p>
				<p>Sheila observes: “The organization of material in fragments,
				multiple peaks rather than single climactic moment, has a quality
				and rhythm which may parallel woman’s ontological experience,
				particularly her experience of time. .. There are several genres of
				women’s work, quilts and blankets, for example, which are as
				semblages of fragments generated whenever there is time, which
				are in their method of creation as well as in their aesthetic form,
				visually organized into many centers. The quilting bee, as well as
				the quilt itself, is an example of an essentially non-hierarchal
				organization."</p>
				<p>Not exactly the lady one associates with quilting bees and
				other domestic tasks, the monumental Gertrude Stein nevertheless
				knit from one soldier’s hospital bed to another during World War
				I, providing cheer, socks and letter-writing services. In this behavior we can see the patterns which she also translated into literary
				form. "You see," she says, "Itried to convey the idea of each part of
				a composition being as important as the whole... After all, to me
				one human being is as important as another being, and you might
				say that the landscape has the same values, a blade of grass has the
				same value as a tree."</p>
				<p>An assemblage of fragments free of hierarchy. “Certainly,"
				Sheila continues, "the quality of time in a woman’s life, particularly if she is not involved in the career thrust toward fame and
				fortune, is distinct from the quality of time experienced by men
				and women who are caught up in the progress of a career. The
				linearity of time is foreign to the actual structure of a day as well as
				to the rhythm of women’s monthly biological time. .. The assemblage of fragments, the organization of forms in a complex matrix,
				projects this experience of time, suggests depth and intensity as an
				alternative to progress."</p>
				<p>Our different organization of time and space requires that we
				react differently to phenomena. We do not know things in isolation or in a continuum so much as we know everything at once.
				The cycle is the long whole moment. (The implications of a different thought process ought to be considered seriously by psychologists and educators.) To know everything at once requires
				that we utilize every sense.</p>
				<p>Woman's intuition," then, is the direct result of holding oneself completely open to the entire experience in its immediacy and
				completeness. Intuition is simply knowing at the moment and
				knowing entirely with one’s intellect, memory, body, emotions; it
				is knowing caringly, evoking information and ordering it through
				the personal context.</p>
				<p>Intuition is simply testament to a context; it is knowledge
				which exists in a complete relationship. To the extent that men isolate experience in order to know, they separate it from themselves
				in the belief that emotion contaminates information. The subjective, the personal, the immediate, the evocative are seen as screens
				preventing the analytical mind from knowing things in themselves, out of flux, out of the conditional.
				But much of what we know, we know exactly in the condition, in the daily life, the actual, the flux, the contingent and with
				emotion...
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				“The materials I use in my work are found objects, discards
				and natural objects. ..shells, feathers, etc. I merely recycle them.
				A particular object may suggest a piece. Maybe a feeling about a
				color or certain image or symbol will conjure a piece...</p>
				<p>"I may work on several pieces at once, going from one to
				another, selecting, rejecting objects, images, symbols, as if in a
				trance. But it works. The fragments fit, the message is revealed
				and again the magic happens. Dat Ol' Black Magicl" Bettye Saar,
				in Art: A Woman’s Sensibility, California Institute of the Arts,
				1975.)
			</p>
			<p>
				"... what might have gone on last night while four women taled
				about a quilt:
				<quote>how it grows rather than being planned. aletheia’s hair
				piled on her head—the hair works loose through the
				evening—one long strand of it falls on her neck. they see
				it grow longer and longer until it’s the longest strand of
				hair in the world. it reaches the floor, then through the
				house, out of the back door, around the neighborhood
				—playing with children, talking hopefully to old people
				and censes—moving on, still attaches to aletheia’s head.
				the hair</quote>
				and the quilt as the time that moves in front of us. streets and
				stores and traffic lights and the strangers that repeat every day,
				always and never the same. (Holly Prado, Feasts, Momentum
				Press, Los Angeles, 1976.)
			</p>
			<p>
				The quilt has come to be symbolic because it is an assemblage of odd bits, organized in a non-hierarchical order, and
				because the quilting bee itself, the circle of women, remains to us
				as a form of non-hierarchical collective labor.</p>
				<p>"In the Smithsonian Institution in Washington, D.C. there
				hangs a quilt unlike any other in the world. In fanciful, inspired,
				and yet simple and identifiable figures, it portrays the story of the
				Crucifixion. It is considered rare, beyond price. Though it follows no known pattern of quilt-making, and though it is made of
				bits and pieces of worthless rags, it is obviously the work of a
				person of imagination and deep spiritual feeling. Below this quilt
				I saw a note that says it was made by ’an anonymous Black
				woman in Alabama, a hundred years ago.'
				"If we could locate this ’anonymous’ Black woman from Alabama, she would turn out to be one of our grandmothers — an
				artist who left her mark in the only materials she could afford,
				and in the only medium her position in society allowed her to
				use." (Alice Walker, "In Search of Our Mothers’ Gardens," Ms.
				Magazine, May 1974.)
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				The leaderless group, the circular form, the non-hierarchical
				structure are perhaps the most socially significant contributions
				of the women’s movement.</p>
				<p>Classrooms, organizing meetings, work sessions are physically organized to diminish the distance between individuals. In
				contrast to seating arrangements in the male-dominated society,
				where desks, stages, lecterns, daises both separate and indicate
				rank and authority, physical position does not create hierarchical
				structure. Women tend to sit close to each other in formations
				which allow for the mingling of work, play, intellectual activity,
				emotional nurturance.</p>
				<p>In this meeting of the Feminist Studio Workshop, one cannot
				distinguish the leaders from the participants, professors from students. Likewise, there is mingling of ages, both children and older
				people are present. A number of activities are occurring simultaneously...
			</p>
			<p>
				The first extant autobiography was written in English by a
				woman. The Book of Margery Kempe is the first extant woman’s
				book. Today it seems that all of us are keeping journals, recording our own lives passionately. We use these forms for documentation and disclosure. The last few years have shown an undress
				ing of woman’s experience which seems in inverse proportion to
				the intensity of the taboo against woman’s nakedness. We are
				becoming more and more naked. And then we peel away the
				skin. Relentlessly naked. It is difficult to look. But we persist.
				Sometimes the images are so strong we look away. The vulval
				ecstasy of Monique Wittig’s Les Guërillères has that character,
				or the overwhelming honesty of Kate Millett’s Flying, or the
				fecund kitchen dissections of Sylvia Plath and Gilah Hirsch, or
				the psychological exploration in the art of Frida Kahlo which is
				unprecedented in self-portraiture. In The Two Fridas she is herself one of the fates, holding the scissors which sever the lifeline -
				her own artery. The portrait examines the complexity, duality
				and contradiction of the personality.
			</p>
			<p>
				As I read these words, I want to tell you everything I know
				at once and everything in at least three voices. Just as our days
				are layered (I used to say "laminated" but Barbara said that was
				too rigid, too hard, so I suggested "days like strudel" and she
				agreed), so our experiences are strudeled and we want to bite into
				them at once.</p>
				<p>The cyclical form results in a literature and art that is dense,
				consisting of many coexisting layers. It creates a book that is
				neither journal nor novel, but what Kate Millett refers to as a new
				form of literature, the experiential book. The new critical standard in literature seems to de-emphasize plot, aesthetic beauty and
				form for a concern with the depth and intensity of the reality
				presented. Once the relationship between plot and form is seen,
				the arbitrary nature of plot is revealed. Plot, after all, is a pattern,
				familiar and reproducible, which can be repeated, albeit with variation, in novel after novel. Plot may be convenient for the
				writer, but it does not necessarily correspond to the way things
				are. Plot demands abstraction, elimination, selection, editing. It
				is a diminution of experience according to literary preconceptions. It removes the novel from the buzz.
				As Doris Lessing asks in The Golden Notebook, “Why a
				story at all... why not simply the truth?"
			</p>
			<p>
				The daily and essential realities are the focus of women's
				lives and work. “Do I repeat myself? Well, then, I repeat myself.
				The statement is Whitman’s. Perhaps it is not ironic that Whitman is a poet of power whose masculinity is always questioned.
				Is it because of his repetitions that we recognize the female sensibility, or is it because he never forgot how close grass ought to be
				to the skin? Life and work—how did they become separated, is
				perhaps a more sensible question than why we are so intent on
				integrating them.</p>
				<p>Even the popular media are occasionally sensitive to the narrow focus on work which is characteristic of the male dominant
				society and which is always puzzling to women. It is the male
				who creates industries, commercial centers, educational institutions that exclude children and other life forces from their boun
				daries. And it is women who have demanded that the doors be
				opened, to day-care centers, older children, the elderly, to greenery and the humanities of home.
				Each day is a tapestry, threads of broccoli, promotion,
				couches, children, politics, shopping, building, planting, thinking
				interweave in intimate connection with the insistent cycles of
				birth, existence and death.</p>
				<p>Women are aware of their bodies very early and very completely although this awareness has not been shared until now.
				Menstruation, lactation, pregnancy, menopause are long-term
				conditions of physical reorganization. When the blood comes at
				thirteen, we are always astonished even if we are well prepared.
				My mother slapped my face in the Jewish tradition "to bring the
				blood to my cheeks" and to punctuate the moment. The menstrual cycle is a repeated cycle of astonishments, physical disturbance
				and enlightenment forming a bond of intimacy between women
				based upon this shared experience. For years we have confessed
				that we are irritable at such times, but now we also need to admit
				that this is the time it seems to us we see most clearly. Perhaps
				this clarity comes from the regular cyclical connection with life
				and death symbolized by blood. Life is both prepared for and
				shed every month.</p>
				<p>Is this the reason why women do not make war?
			</p>
			<pb n='8'/>
			<p>
				The body, as one’s own, and as a woman’s body, is the first
				force that prevents women from becoming distracted by abstract
				intellectual behaviors, providing the immediate and intense private experience which simultaneously connects us with others.
				This dynamic is evident in the journal and the autobiography,
				which are particularly female forms. Personal revelation is one
				foundation of feminism and the new women’s consciousness. The
				journal, as significant as consciousness raising, is a serious activity which cannot be pursued at proscribed times.</p>
				<p>Recently I conducted a class in Secrets at Chino State Prison
				for Women. While it was relatively easy to deal with some of the
				consequences of search, seizure, scrutiny by wardens and guards,
				it was more difficult to evaluate the risk of revelation to one's
				fellow prisoners. It was relatively easy to understand that the
				prison authorities were simply the active instruments of social
				oppression and that acts of solidarity and revelation between
				women inevitably undermined the oppressive forces. However, it
				was more difficult to gauge the trust that was possible between
				women living under these conditions, whose lives were often
				regulated through the subtle manipulation of one woman against
				another. How much could they reveal to each other? How carefully would they honor each other’s secrets?</p>
				<p>As an act of faith, I first read a "secret" from my novel.
			</p>
			<p>
				Then each woman wrote a "secret" to another woman in the
				room, with whom she could but was not obliged to share her
				writing. One woman decided to share her secret with the entire
				group, confiding in us that this was the first time she had revealed
				the event to anyone, despite three years of psychoanalysis. This
				was perhaps the first moment of social trust she had experienced.
				The secret, read in a trembling voice, was an agonized memory of
				sadistic and sexual cruelty perpetrated upon her, pregnant at fifteen, by someone she trusted and loved. Reading her own words,
				she now knew that she had not been responsible for provoking
				this incident. Fifteen years of guilt laid aside. Yet, listening to her
				revelation in the hushed silence of the prison classroom, I wondered if the support and love which allowed her to speak these
				words were temporary. Would she be betrayed later? And how?
				In any form, the guilt and pain had been a worm far more raven
				ous and lethal than any revelation could be now. Nevertheless, I
				hoped she would not pay the penalty that is often exacted by such
				nakedness.
			</p>
			<p>
				Skin: Shadows
				From SILENCE : A Love Letter in the Form of the Novel,
				West Coast Poetry Review, Reno, Nevada, 1976.
				It is afternoon. You’ve heard this story before. This is the
				story I will tell twice and then again. It does not empty easily
				This story has left a scar and the scar needs to be cut out. This
				story will be told again.
				It is afternoon. I am alone. In an office. It is afternoon. I am
				alone. In an office. It is afternoon. I am alone.
				There is a knock at the door. Or the sound of the door open
				ing in the outer office. Or a knock and the sound of a door open
				ing in the outer office this afternoon. I am alone. Thinking of
				things one thinks when one is alone in the afternoon. Almost a
				daydream. Allowed to think. Why should I be startled by a
				knock at my door or the sound of another door opening. Why
				should I hear the door or even interrupt my thoughts which are so
				pleasant this quiet afternoon. All the work is done.
				Why bother to turn my head when I hear the floor creak?
				My thoughts are so pleasant, nothing can interrupt them. This is
				my time to muse. A rare afternoon alone. All the work is done.
				Probably it is not a knock at the door that I hear and do not
				respond to. Probably it is the sound of a door opening quietly
				and of soft footprints across the floor. Or maybe it is the sound of
				a knock, a tentative tap to see if l am in. But it is a quiet afternoon
				and all the work is done and I am in to no one but myself, so I do
				not answer the door. Probably there is no sound. It is not that I
				refuse to be interrupted but that my dreams are so intense that I
				hear nothing, not the initial knock on the outer door, (if indeed
				there was a knock — probably there was no knock) nor the sound
				of the lock turning, nor the cautious feet across the floor, nor the
				cautious turning of the lock to my inner office and the stealthy
				opening of the door, nor the hand raised against me. Nothing. It
				is afternoon and I hear nothing, suspect nothing, till the gun is
				pressed against my head and the hand muzzles my mouth.
				Say nothing," he whispers.
				It is a gun which is against my head. There is a man holding
				it. I cannot see him. But I do not think I know him. He ties an
				unclean and wrinkled handkerchief across my mouth. I close my
				eyes because I am afraid to know him. Simultaneously I keep
				them open in order to see this man. But I think I can see nothing.
				“Take your clothes off," he says. Everything he says is in a
				strained and I assume disguised voice. Perhaps he is someone I
				know. Which is more awful—an anonymous assault by a stran-
				ger or by a friend?
			</p>
			<pb n='9'/>
			<p>
				n struggling to
				My hands are shaking and he i
				obey. My feet are shaking also.
				I can only see his feet. I have told you before about his
				scuffed black shoes which look like those with steel linings in the
				toes. They are laced with frayed black laces. His socks are white.
				Dirty white. His feet are wide. I suspect his legs are hairy and that
				the hairs are damp.
				It is afternoon. A quiet afternoon. No one is about.
				No one is knocking at the door. “Take off your clothes,
				says. My body is shaking. The dress peels from me like skin, a
				heap of feathers disordered, plucked live from the skin, a mound
				of fresh leather in a corner. And the animal is still alivel And the
				deer stretches denuded flanks, twitching. I can see the blood rur
				across the hooves.
				I am naked. He is wearing clothes. I do not wish to see his
				legs hairy at the ankle bone. I cannot bear to see his clothes
				against my skin. I am naked. He is fully clothed
				I remember nothing. I will remember nothing. I tell you this
				without hearing my own voice. I tell you this again and again so I
				will never remember it. I remember how naked I am next to his
				clothed legs in order to forget everything.
				Handprints on my back. Indelible markings. In later mirrors
				it seems my back grows away from his hands. An announcement
				in reversal. In recoil.
				An invasion. A tree opening to fire. And a black hollow
				from which no twig can emerge again. Perhaps it is a gun pene
				trating me and orgasm will be a round of bullets. Pain is a relief. I
				cherish it as a distraction from knowing. I am an enemy country.
				Destroy me with fire. But there is no distraction. The cloth rubs
				against my legs. There is a gun resting on my shoulder. I do not
				forget that death is the voyeur at this encounter.
				Turning. Turning. The flesh of the spitted deer crackles
				against the fire. I want to reach for a knife to carve myself into
				morsels, to divide into portions, to carve a slit downwards from
				my navel to my spine.
				There is a circle of steel against my ear.
				I have told this before. It is afternoon, a quiet afternoon, and
				the taste of my own meat smeared on unknown flesh is in my
				mouth. I choke upon it. It is afternoon. I do not know what is
				thrust in my mouth. What banquet is this? What severed legi
				What joint? What goat, deer, bone? I wish blood were dripping
				down my throat now. How long can I hold his sperm in my
				mouth without swallowing?
				It is afternoon. I have told you this before. It is a quiet after
				noon. I do not hear the sound of someone knocking at my door
				I try to say, “Come in." I would like someone to help me
				from the floor. I need a pillow under my head. Wrap me in a
				blanket. Turn the lights out.
				It is early evening. It is night. It is tomorrow. I would like
				someone to help me up from the floor. I cannot say, “Come in.
				to the knock on the door. I cannot yell for help. I need to be
				wrapped in a blanket. I need a pillow under my head. And a
				nightdress. And a cover of white cloth.
				Everything is quiet. My body is numb. I feel nothing. My
				body is dumb. It is early evening.
				There is a knock on the door. I cannot hear the knock at the
				door. I cannot say, “Come in." I need..
				There is a knock at the door. I cannot say... I...
				There is a knock... I can not... I..
				I can not...
			</p>
			<p>
				Honor Moore’s Mourning Pictures, an eloquent play about
				the death of the playwright's mother, closed after its first day on
				Broadway because, according to Clive Barnes, it did not tran
				scend the experience of personal loss. Women are choosing to
				achieve "universality” through the exposure and identification of
				the personal moment rather than through its transcendence. The
				most powerful lines in the play are also the simplest: “Ladies and
				Gentlemen, my mother is dying.
				Women are the Fourth World say the women of North Viet-
				nam. We read each other’s autobiographies as if they were our
				own lives. Nakedness is an ambivalent state implying weakness
				and power simultaneously. The naked person is an image of help
				lessness and yet nudity is terrifying to the observer. There has
				been much critical distaste expressed for the confessional mode of
				woman’s art, which has been considered blatant, vulnerable, self
				pitying, raw, untransformed. Not often admitted is the puritani
				cal base for the anxiety felt before work which, as an editor told
				me about my own, is produced by "unrelieved personal dis
				closure."
			</p>
			<p>
				This common interest in our history and experience is not
				only the response to historic anonymity, it is not merely a first
				step toward liberation, but the revitalization and making public
				of an honored female form which integrates the private and the
				public worlds, the individual and the collective sensibilities.
				"I am not completely satisfied," Martha Lifson says, "by the
				autobiographies of Gertrude Stein as they emphasize the public
				world and the people she meets. I prefer the diaries of Dorothy
				Wordsworth where the work and the ideas, commentary and
				portraits are braided through the gardening, reading, cooking
				and conversation. I am interested in the entire life and the whole
				day.
				Intense revelation, but not confession. Because we are so
				accustomed to confining intimacy to the private sector, the form
				disconcerts us when it is present in the public world. Women
				break down the wooden house and the anonymity and objectivi
				ty of the psychiatric privacy. We do not wish to speak alone. We
				demand that the listener be a participant. We tell our secrets
				openly and publicly without erasing them. We say, “These are
				our lives." We insist on telling these secrets to each other because
				we know it makes a difference. That is intimacy—the insistence
				upon response and equality. We want our talk to make a differ
				ence to ourselves and to others. We create open forms so that
				someone can answer us.
			</p>
			<pb n='10'/>
			<p>
				What word can we interject to convey our meaning of tan
				gible and certain? In lieu of concrete can we say braided, be
				fabric, be cloth?
				"All mother goddesses spin and weave. In their concealed
				workshops they weave veins, fibers and nerve strands into the
				miraculous substance of the live body. Everything that is comes
				out of them: they weave the world tapestry out of genesis and
				demise, threads appearing and disappearing rhythmically.
				I wonder how to credit Helen Diner for the above quote.
				Everything in me rebels against the learned footnote which does
				not provide a space for the essential information—the thrill of
				recognition which occurs when it is read. In graduate school I
				vowed to avoid all the Latin forms, the op. cits., loc. cits., ibids.,
				which represented distant authority. But now it is possible to use
				footnotes again and even to peruse them eagerly before one reads
				the papers they are included in. Women’s footnotes are of another
				form. They are not authoritarian, they do not necessarily refer to
				texts, to abstract tomes, to objective external sources. Often emo
				tional statements or conversational asides, they serve to enrich
				the material by bringing in the strands, the choruses, the associa
				tions. They are informal, spontaneous interjections permeating
				more formal, carefully constructed works.
				There are times when I do not know at all which ideas were
				mine, which Barbara’s, Jane’s, Sheila’s. The ideas pass back and
				forth between us, and our shared experience and communication
				is their real source. The ivory tower shatters as an image for those
				of us who cannot and will not segregate our creativity, finding it
				as often as not in the kitchen as in the study. Footnotes no longer
				function only to identify a single authority, but can also challenge
				the concept in order to acknowledge and record collective efforts.
			</p>
			<p>
				It is important to realize that for women the process of per
				sonal confession implies collective revelation. This is the recur
				ring experience of journal classes, women’s writing groups and
				consciousness raising.
				One of the projects of the Feminist Design Program at Cali
				fornia Institute of the Arts, directed by Sheila de Bretteville, was
				a series of videotapes about menstruation. The groups consisted
				of older women, young women, teenagers and mixed groups of
				boys and girls exchanging information, personal experience. This
				was one of the first attempts to eliminate the body of misinforma
				tion, prejudice, fear, and often self-hate which arises from the
				combination of silence and social anxiety. The anxiety is easily
				detected in the language which surrounds menstruation: “the
				curse," "falling off the roof," “on the rag," "unwell," etc.
				Menstruation has indeed been a “red flag" (to borrow the
				title of Judy Chicago’s well-known lithograph) for those who
				accepted the taboo regarding the discussion of menstruation or
				the use of female imagery in art. This visual confrontation with
				the female reality is part of women’s contemporary insistence
				upon being naked, breaking the silence that has surrounded us
				and particularly our bodies. Looking at female biology is one part
				of telling the story of our lives and breaking the mystery that is a
				patriarchal prison, helping to create the mythos, the mystique of
				woman.
				Often revelation has political consequences beyond con
				sciousness, as did the public acknowledgment by hundreds of
				French women that they had had abortions, in order to achieve
				liberalization of abortion laws. Other times the revelation breaks
				a taboo or allows others to claim and understand their own
				experiences which have often been deadened by seeming unique
				or eccentric.
			</p>
			<p>
				"When a woman artist positively identifies herself to us
				through her work, she commits a courageous and daring act of
				self-exposure, because her contribution has neither spoken to nor
				been understood by the mainstream of the culture, and the con
				tent of her art has been bypassed by interpretations which could
				reveal it. Thus a woman’s saying, Tam, I know myself, and I feel
				a fundamental optimism —a grasp upon my own survival as a
				model for human survival, is saying something which challenges
				the prevailing worldview. If consciousness is the content of femi
				nist art, this level of human responsibility and hope is the content
				of consciousness." (Arlene Raven, feminist art historian, one of
				the organizers of the Feminist Studio Workshop and the Woman's
				Building.)
			</p>
			<pb n='11'/>
			<p>
				Performance is a natural form of expression for women
				whose history has been limited primarily to oral forms. Perfor
				mance like conversation is flexible, often without script, respon
				sive, and invites participation. It is not meant primarily for pub
				lication or to have a long run, but is often conceived for a par
				ticular moment. Like gossip, performance can be seen as a form
				of social regulation which depends upon intimacy and associatior
				with the subject. Like journals, performances allow for the collec
				tive and public scrutiny of women’s past and-contemporary roles
				in order to create attitudinal and behavioral change. Perfor
				mances therefore often have a personal as well as a social, didac
				tic function. Performance is also a way of modeling, providing
				not only a critique of the past but alternatives for the future. Now
				that the journal is becoming a public document, and we are re
				véaled in each other’s books, the journal also may be a new
				benign and creative moral imperative.
			</p>
			<p>
				The woman’s form is connective. It is a tapestry or a quilt, a
				weaving or collage, an interlacing of all the diverse parts which
				are obsessively differentiated in the dominant culture. For women
				to come into the public world we must be cognizant of our his
				toric and contemporary forms of organization and expression in
				order to survive. At the least we must struggle like Penelope,
				weaving half the day, unraveling half the night.
				Within woman’s culture, because of its plurality and toler
				ance, man can exist; within man’s culture woman is destroyed by
				individualism and abstraction. Woman is an appropriate word
				for Man. She is an appropriate substitute for He/She because he
				is contained in she—orthographically, physiologically, but more
				significantly, ontologically. One culture encloses within; the
				other segregates out.
				Despite the frequent critical stance that female imagery,
				woman’s art, female sensibility is a limitation imposed upon cul
				ture, a narrowing of vision, it should by now be abundantly clear
				that woman’s culture, being primarily integrative rather than
				analytical, offers as rich and deep a universe as that which has
				been the basis of “civilization" until now. To define a woman's
				culture is not to delimit or to create orthodoxy, but rather to
				expand current cultural horizons and to provide the opportunity
				to explore experience in new areas through the validation of
				hitherto unrecognized and devalued expression.
				Woman’s culture is not a set of rules or restrictions, rather it
				is a direction, an eye, a broad intellectual framework for dis
				covering form and meaning. In its underground forms it is avail
				able to a few women and fewer men; named and public it is avail
				able to everyone. Now when we come into the world, it is in our
				image—as Eve—the image of integration and relationship. In that
				act woman challenges the dominant world culture.
			</p>
			<p>
				Deena Metzger is a feminist writer, poet and lecturer who is direc
				tor of the Writing Program at the Feminist Studio Workshop at
				the Woman’s Building in Los Angeles. She is the author of a novel,
				Skin. Shadows (West Coast Poetry Review, 1976) and a radio play,
				SILENCE
				The Book of Hags.
			</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
